<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" PriestsOnly="true" Agpeya="true">   
   <Title>
      <Language id="English">Priests</Language>
   </Title>
   
   <Title>
      <Language id="English">
         Psalms Recited on the Way to Church
      </Language>      
      <Language id="Arabic">
         المزامير التي تتلى في الطريق إلى الكنيسة
      </Language>
   </Title>
   
   <Section expanded="true">
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Psalm 26 - The Lord is my light...
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور السادس والعشرون - الربّ نوري...
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            The Lord is my light and my salvation; whom will I fear? The Lord is the defender of my life; of whom will I be afraid? When the wicked drew near against me to eat up my flesh, those who distress me and my enemies, they fainted and fell. Though an army should fight me, my heart shall not be afraid; though war should rise up against me, in this I am confident.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            الربُّ نوري وخلاصي مِمَنْ أخافُ؟! الربُّ حِصنُ حياتي مِمَنْ أجزعُ؟! عِندما يقترِبُ الأشرارُ مني ليأكلوا لَحمي، مُضايقيَّ وَأعدائي عثَروا وسقَطوا. إن يُحاربْني جيشٌ فلَن يخافَ قلبي. وإن قامَ عليَّ قتالٌ ففي هذا أنا أطمئنُ.
         </Language>
      </Text>
            
      <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         One thing I have asked of the Lord, this also I will seek, that I should dwell in the house of the Lord all the days of my life, that I should behold the fair beauty of the Lord, and visit His holy temple. For in the day of my afflictions He hid me in His tabernacle; He sheltered me in the secret of His tabernacle; He set me up on a rock. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         واحدةً سألتُ مِنَ الربِّ وإيَّاها ألتمسُ. أن أسكنَ في بيتِ الربِّ كلَّ أيامِ حياتي. لكي أنظرَ نعيمَ الربِّ، وأتفرسَ في هيكلِهِ المُقدسِ. لأنَّه أخفاني في خيمتِهِ. في يومِ شِدَّتي، ستَرَني بسِترِ مظلَّتِهِ. وعلى صخرةٍ رفعَني.
      </Language>
   </Text>
<Text>
         <Language id="English">
            And now, behold, He has lifted up my head over my enemies; I went round and offered in His tabernacle a sacrifice of joy; I shall sing, and sing psalms to the Lord.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            والآنَ هوذا قد رفعَ رأسي على أعدائي. طُفتُ وذَبحتُ في مظلَّتِهِ ذبيحةَ التهليلِ، أسبِّحُ وأرتِّلُ للربِّ.
         </Language>
      </Text>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            Hear, O Lord, my voice which I have uttered aloud; have mercy on me, and hearken to me. For You are He to whom my heart said, “I have sought Your face; Your face, O Lord, I will seek.” Do not turn away Your face from me, do not reject Your servant in anger. Be a helper to me, and do not forsake me; and do not overlook me, O God my Savior. For my father and my mother have forsaken me, but the Lord has accepted me unto Himself. Set a law for me, O Lord, in Your ways, and guide me in a right path, because of my enemies. Do not deliver me over to the hands of those who afflict me; for unjust witnesses have risen up against me, and injustice has lied to itself. I believe that I shall see the goodness of the Lord in the land of the living. Wait for the Lord; be of good cheer and let your heart be strengthened, and wait for the Lord. ALLELUIA.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            استمِعْ يا ربُّ صوتي الذي بِهِ دعوتُكَ. ارحَمْني واستجِبْ لي فإنَّهُ لكَ قالَ قلبي: طلبتُ وجهَكَ، ووجهَكَ يا ربُّ ألتمِسُ. لا تحجُبْ وجهَكَ عنِّي، ولا تنبُذْ بغضبٍ عبدكَ. كُنْ لي مُعيناً، لا تخذِلْني ولا ترفُضْني يا اللهُ مُخلِّصي. فإنَّ أبي وأمِّي قد ترَكاني، وأمَّا الربُّ فقبِلَني. علِّمْني ياربُّ طريقَكَ، واهدِني في سبيلٍ مُستقيمٍ مِنْ أجلِ أعدائي. لا تُسلِّمْني إلى أيدي مُضايقيَّ، لأنَّهُ قد قامَ عليَّ شهودُ زورٍ، وكذِبوا عليَّ ظُلماً. وأنا أؤمِنُ أني أعاينُ خيراتِ الربِّ في أرضِ الأحياءِ. انتظرْ الربَّ، تقوَّ وليتشدَدْ قلبُكَ وانتظرْ الربَّ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
<Section expanded="true">
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Psalm 46 - Clap your hands...
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور السادس والأربعون - يا جميعَ الأممِ صفِّقوا بأيديكُم...
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            Clap your hands, all you nations; shout to God with a voice of exultation. For the Lord is most high and fearful; He is a great king over all the earth. He has subdued peoples under us, and nations under our feet. He has chosen us for His inheritance, the beauty of Jacob whom He loved.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            يا جميعَ الأممِ صفِّقوا بأيديكُم، هلّلوا للهِ بصوتِ الابتهاجِ. لأنَّ الربَّ عالٍ ومرهوبٌ، ملكٌ كبيرٌ على كافّةِ الأرضِ. أخضعَ الشعوبَ لنا، والأممَ تحتَ أقدامِنا، اختارَنا ميراثاً لهُ، جمالَ يعقوبَ الذي أحبَّهُ.
         </Language>
      </Text>
       
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            God has ascended with a shout, and the Lord with a sound of a trumpet. Sing praises to our God, sing praises; sing praises to our King, sing praises; for God is king of all the earth. Sing praises with understanding, for the Lord reigned over all the nations; God sits upon His holy throne. Rulers of the people have assembled with God of Abraham, for God's mighty ones have been greatly exalted upon the earth. ALLELUIA.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            صعِدَ اللهُ بتهليلٍ، والربُّ بصوتِ البوقِ. رتِّلوا لإلهِنا رتِّلوا، رتِّلوا لمليكِنا رتِّلوا، لأنَّ الربَّ هو ملكُ الأرضِ كلِّها. رتِّلوا بفهمٍ لأنَّ الربَّ قد ملكَ على جميعِ الأممِ. اللهُ جلسَ على كرسيّهِ المُقدَّسِ. رؤساءُ الشعوبِ اجتمعوا معَ إلهِ إبراهيمَ، لأنَّ أعزاءَ اللهِ قد ارتفعوا في الأرضِ جداً. هَلِّلُويا.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
<Section expanded="true">
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Psalm 121 - I was glad for those...
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والحادي والعشرونَ - فرِحتُ بالقائلينَ...
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            I was glad for those who said to me, “We will go into the house of the Lord.” Our feet stood in the courts of Jerusalem, Jerusalem which is built as a city that is closely compacted together. For there the tribes went up, the tribes of the Lord, as a testimony for Israel, to give thanks to the name of the Lord. For there are set thrones for judgment, even thrones for the house of David.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            فرِحتُ بالقائلينَ لي إلى بيتِ الربِّ نذهبُ. وقفَت أرجُلُنا في ديارِ أورُشَليمَ، أورُشَليمُ المبنيَّةُ مِثلُ مدينةٍ مُتَّصِلةٍ بعضِها ببعضٍ. لأنَّ هُناكَ صعِدَتْ القبائلُ، قبائلُ الربِّ، شهادةً لإسرائيلَ، يعترِفونَ لاسمِ الربِّ. هُناكَ نُصِبَتْ كراسيُّ للقضاءِ، كراسيُّ بيتِ داودَ.
         </Language>
      </Text>
       
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            Ask for the things which are for the peace of Jerusalem, and for the prosperity to those who love you. Let peace be within your strength, and prosperity in your heavy towers. For the sake of my brethren and my companions, I have indeed spoken peace concerning you. Because of the house of the Lord our God, I have diligently sought good things for you. ALLELUIA.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            اسألوا السلامَ لأورُشَليمَ والخِصبَ لمُحبّيكِ. ليكُنْ السلامُ في حِصنِكِ والخِصبُ في أبراجِكِ الرصينةِ. مِنْ أجلِ إخوتي وأقربائي تكلَّمتُ مِنْ أجلِكِ بالسلامِ، ومِنْ أجلِ بيتِ الربِّ إلهِنا التمستُ لكِ الخيراتِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
<Title>
      <Language id="English">
         Psalms Recited While Putting On Vestments
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         المزامير التي تتلى عند لبس ثياب الخدمة
      </Language>
   </Title>
   
   <Section expanded="true">
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Psalm 29 - I will exalt You...
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور التاسع والعشرون - أعظمُكَ ياربُّ...
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            I will exalt You, O Lord, for You have accepted me, and not caused my enemies to rejoice over me. O Lord, my God, I cried to You, and You have healed me. O Lord, You have brought up my soul from Hades, You have delivered me from those who will go down to the pit.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            أعظِّمُكَ ياربُّ لأنكَ احتضنتَني، ولم تُشمِتْ بي أعدائي. أيُها الربُّ إلهي، صرختُ إليكَ فشفَيتَني. ياربُّ أصعدتَ مِنَ الجحيمِ نفسي، وخلّصتَني مِنَ الهابطينَ في الجُبِّ.
         </Language>
      </Text>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            Sing to the Lord, all you His saints, and confess the remembrance of His holiness. For anger is in His wrath, but life in His favor; weeping shall be for the evening, but joy shall be in the morning.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            رتّلوا للربِّ يا جميعَ قديسيهِ، واعترفوا لذكرِ قُدسِهِ. لأنَّ سَخَطاً في غضبِهِ، وحياةً في رضاهُ. في العشاءِ يحلُّ البكاءُ، وفي الصباحِ السرورُ.
         </Language>
      </Text>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            I said in my prosperity, I shall never be moved. O Lord, in Your will You gave strength to my beauty, but You turned away Your face from me, and I became troubled. To You, O Lord, I shall cry, and to my God I shall make supplication. What profit is there in my blood, when I go down to destruction? Shall the dust confess to You? Or shall it declare Your truth?
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            أنا قلتُ في نعيمي لا أتزعزعُ إلى الدهرِ، ياربُّ بمسرَّتِكَ أعطيتَ جَمالي قوةً. صرفتَ وجهَكَ عنّي، فصِرتُ قلِقاً. إليكَ ياربُّ أصرخُ، وإلى إلهي أتضرَّعُ. أيّةُ منفعةٍ مِنْ دمي إذا هبَطتُ إلى الجحيمِ؟ هل يعترفُ لكَ الترابُ أو يُخبرُ بحقِّكَ؟
         </Language>
      </Text>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            The Lord heard, and had mercy upon me; the Lord became to me a helper. You have turned my mourning into joy for me; You have rent off my sackcloth, and girded me with gladness, that my glory may sing praise to You, and I shall not be troubled at heart. O Lord, my God, I will confess to You forever. ALLELUIA.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            سمعَ الربُّ فرحمَني، الربُّ صارَ لي عوناً. حوّلتَ نَوحي إلى فرحٍ لي، مزّقتَ مِسْحي ومنطقتَني سُروراً. لكي تُرتِلَ لكَ نفسي ولا يحزنَ قلبي. أيُها الربُّ إلهي إلى الأبدِ أعترفُ لكَ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
<Section expanded="true">
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Psalm 92 - The Lord has reigned; He has clothed...
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الثاني والتسعون - الربُّ قد ملكَ، ولبسَ...
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            The Lord has reigned; He has clothed Himself with beauty. The Lord has clothed and girded Himself with strength; for He has established the world, which shall not be moved. Your throne is prepared from the beginning; You are from everlasting. The rivers have lifted up, O Lord; the rivers have lifted up their voices; the rivers shall lift up their voices, from the voices of many waters. The billows of the waves of the sea are wonderful; the Lord is wonderful in the highest. His testimonies are very sure; holiness is worthy of Your house, O Lord, unto length of days. ALLELUIA.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            الربُّ قد ملَكَ، ولبِسَ الجلالَ. لبِسَ الربُّ القوةَ، وتمنطقَ بها. لأنَّهُ ثبَّتَ المسكونةَ فلن تتزعزعَ. كرسيُّكَ ثابتٌ مُنذُ البدءِ، وأنتَ هو مُنذُ الأزلِ. رفعتِ الأنهارُ ياربُّ، رفعتِ الأنهارُ صوتَها. ترفعُ الأنهارُ صوتَها، مِنْ صوتِ مياهٍ كثيرةٍ. عجيبةٌ هي أهوالُ البحرِ، وعجيبٌ هو الربُّ في الأعالي. شهاداتُهُ صادقةٌ جداً، لبيتِكَ ينبغي التقديسُ ياربُّ طولَ الأيامِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
<Title>
      <Language id="English">Absolution of the Priests</Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">تحليل الكهنة</Language>
   </Title>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         We ask You and thank You, O Master Lord Jesus Christ, Son of the living God, existing in light before all ages, Light of Light: enlighten O Lord, our minds and hearts and shine on our understanding, that we may understand Your life-giving word. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         نَسْألُكَ ونَشكُركَ، أيُّها السَّيِّدُ الرَّبُّ يَسوعُ المسِيحُ، ابن الله الحيُّ الأزَليُّ، الكائِنُ في النُّورِ قَبْلَ كُلِّ الدُّهُورِ، نُورٌ مِنْ نُورٌ: أنِرْ يَاربُّ عُقُولَنا وقُلوبَنَا، وأضِيء أفْهامَنا، لنَفْهمَ كَلامَكَ المُحْيي.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Raise us from darkness of sin that kills the soul. Make us worthy to be upright in doing good and righteousness. At the time of Your awesome Second Coming to judge the world, make us worthy of hearing the voice full of happiness, gladness, comfort and joy from Your divine mouth, saying, “Come, you blessed of My Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world.” (Matthew 25:34). 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         وأقِمْنَا مِنْ ظُلْمَةِ الخَطيئة القَاتِلةِ للنَّفْسِ. واجْعَلنَا مُستَحقِّينَ أنْ نَكونَ مُستقِيمينَ في عَمَلِ الخَيْرِ والصَّلاحِ. وفْي وقْتِ مَجيِئكَ الثَّانِي المرْهُوبِ لتَدِينَ فِيهِ العَالمَ، فلْنَسْتحِقَّ سَمَاعَ ذَلكَ الصَّوْتِ المَمْلوءِ فَرحاً، وبَهْجةً، وعَزاءً، وسروراً، ونَعِيماً مِنْ فَمِكَ الإلَهِي القَائِلُ: "تَعالَوْا إليَّ يا مُبَارَكي أبي، رِثُوا المُلكَ المُعَدُّ لكُم قَبْل إنْشَاءِ العَالَم."
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Yes, O Lord, help us to be on that day and in that hour without fear or blemish or terror or falling or straying. Do not condemn us, O Lord, for the multitude of our sins. Forgive us, O Lord, all our transgressions, iniquities, mistakes, and shortcomings. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         نَعَم أيُّها الرَّبُّ إلهنا: وَفِّقْنَا أنْ نَكونَ في ذَلكَ اليَوْمِ وتِلْكَ السَّاعَةِ بِغَيْرِ خَوفٍ، ولا عَيْبٍ، ولا إنْزعاجٍ، ولا سقوطٍ، ولا إنْحِرافٍ. ولا تُؤاخِذْنَا ياربُّ بكَثرةِ آثَامِنَا. اصْفَحْ يَاربُّ عَنْ جَمِيعِ سَيِّئاتِنا، وزَلاَّتِنَا، وغَلَطاتِنَا، وهَفَواتِنا.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Take away from us and from the whole world death, inflation, plagues, destruction, evacuation, the sword of enemies, the conspiracy of devils, the evil of fire and drowning, the fight of evil-doers, the deception of the wicked, and the injustice of the ruler. Abolish from us the conspiracy of those who are opposing us.          </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         وارْفَعْ يارَبُّ عنَّا وعَنْ جَمِيعِ العَالَمِ: المَوْتَ، والغَلاءَ، والوَبَاءَ، والفَنَاءَ، والجلاءَ، وسَيفَ الأعْداءِ، ومُؤامَرةَ الشَّياطِينِ، وشَرَّ الحَريقِ والغَرقِ، ومُقاوَمَةَ الأشْرَارِ، وكَيْدَ الفُجَّارِ، وجَوْرَ السُّلْطَانِ. وأبطِلْ مؤامِرةَ المُعَانِدِينَ لنا.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         O God, You are our Lord and our God; have compassion on us and do not throw us in the seas of destruction or the paths of punishment, but deliver us and keep us and cover us and raise us from our boredom, slothfulness and laziness. Do not let our enemy, the devil, deceive us by false hopes, but alert our minds and wake up our hearts from the sleep of carelessness and wasting life in vain. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         اللَّهُمَّ إنَّكَ ربُّنا وإلَهنا، تراءَفْ عَليْنا، ولا تَطْرَحْنا في بِحارِ المَهَالِكِ، ولا عِقابَ المسَالِكِ. لَكنْ نَجِّنا، واحْفَظْنا، واسْتُرنَا، وانْهِضْنا مِنَ الملَلِ، والضَّجَرِ، والتَّوانِي، والكَسَلِ. ولا تَدَعْ العَدُوَّ الشَّيْطانَ يُطْغِينَا بوسْعِ الأملِ. بَلْ نَبِّهْ عقولَنا، وأيْقِظ قُلوبَنا مِنْ نَومِ الغَفْلةِ وتَسْويفِ العُمْرِ بَاطِلاً.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         O God, forsake our sins. Forgive our iniquities. Do not remember our trespasses. Do not be angry with us, and do not let Your anger endure forever. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         اللَّهُمَّ اتْرُكْ آثَامَنَا، وأصْفَحْ عَن زَلاَّتنَا، ولا تَذْكُر خَطايَانَا ولا سَيِّئاتِنا، ولا تَغْضَب عَليْنا، ولا يَدُمْ غَضَبُكَ إلى الأبَدِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Have mercy on us, O Lord, and have mercy on us, for we are weak and poor and drowning in the sea of sins. We cry unto You; we worship You; we confess You; we entreat You. Do not dash, O Lord, our hope in Your mercy. Do not shut the door of Your mercy in our faces. Graciously save us and lead us to Your mercy. Make us to hear Your joyful voice. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         ارْحَمْنَا يَاربُّ ثم ارْحَمْنَا، فإنَّنا ضُعَفَاءٌ ومَسَاكِينٌ، وفي بِحَارِ الخَطايَا غَارقينَ. فإليكَ نَصْرخُ، ولَكَ نسْجدُ، وبِكَ نَعْترفُ، وإليكَ نَرْغبُ. لا تَقْطَعْ رَجاءَنَا يا سَيِّدِي مِنْ رَحْمَتِكَ، ولا تُغْلقْ بَابَ رَحْمَتِكَ في وجُوهِنا. بَلْ بفَضْلِكَ خَلِّصْنا، وإلى رَحْمَتِكَ وَفِّقْنا، وصَوْتَكَ الفَرحُ إسْمِعْنا.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         O God, purify us and sanctify our hearts from evil, defiled, and bad thoughts. Remove from us, O Lord, and from all Your people, all devilish dreams and illusions. Raise us, O God, from every fall and affliction. Confirm in us, O God, patience, hope, love and the orthodox faith. Count us with Your sheep at Your right hand. Set us down with those who sit at Your heavenly banquet. Forgive us every iniquity, trespass, and sin. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         اللَّهُمَّ طهِّرنَا، وطَهِّرْ قُلوبَنا مِنَ الأفْكارِ الخَبِيثةِ، النَّجسَةِ، الرَّديئةِ. وابْطِلْ عنَّا يَاربُّ وعن كل شَعْبكَ، كُلَّ الأحْلامِ والخَيالاتِ، والهوَاجِسِ الشَّيْطانِيَّةِ. أقِمْنا يا اللَّهُ مِنْ كُلِّ سَقْطةٍ وبَليَّةٍ. ثَبِّتْ فِينَا يا اللَّهُ الصَّبْرَ، والرَّجاءَ، والمحَبَّةَ، والإيمَانَ الأرْثُوذُكسِي. واحْسبْنَا مِنْ خِرافِكَ اليَمينِيَّة. وأجْلِسْنَا مَعَ الذِينَ يتَّكِئونَ في وَليمَتِك السَّمائِيَّةِ. واغْفرْ لنا كُلَّ إثْمٍ وذَنْبٍ وخَطيَّةٍ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Fortify us with the strength of Your heavenly angels of light, for we have no salvation except through Your grace for our trust, belief, and hope are in You. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         وحَصِّنَّا بحِصْنِ جُنودِ مَلائِكتِكَ النُّورانِيَّة. فإنَّهُ ليسَ لنَا خَلاصٌ إلاَّ برَحْمَتِكَ، وإتِّكالِنا عَليكَ، وإيمَانِنا بِكَ، ورَجائِنَا فِيكَ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Accept from us, O Lord, our supplication at this present time and at all times. All those who have bidden and asked us to remember them in prayers, liturgies, and commemorations, the living and the dead, remember them, along with us, O Lord, for that which is good in the heavenly Jerusalem, in the kingdom of heaven. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         اقْبَل مِنَّا ياربُّ دُعاءَنَا في هَذا الوَقْتِ الحاضِر، وكُلِّ الأوقَاتِ. وكُلُّ الذِينَ أمَرونَا وأوْصَونَاَ أنْ نَذْكُرَهُم في الصَّلَواتِ، والقُدَّاسَاتِ، والقَنَاديلِ، والتِّذْكارَاتِ، الأحْيَاءَ مِنُهُم والأمْواتِ. أذكُرنَا ياربُّ نحنُ وإيَّاهُم بالصَّالِحاتِ، في أورشَلِيمَ السَّمائيَّةِ، في مَلكوتِ السَّمَواتِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Blot out, O Lord, our trespasses. As for those who have trespassed against us, forgive them and us. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         امْحُ يَاربُّ سَيِّئاتِنَا. والذينَ أسَاءوا إلَينَا أتْرُكْ لهُم ولنا.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Through Your mercy, O Lord, save the souls of us all. O Lord, save Your people. Bless Your inheritance. Shepherd them and raise them up forever. Save all those who are in afflictions, tribulations, or sorrows. Release those who are captive by the bonds of the devils. Satisfy the hungry with good things. Comfort those who are sad in heart and soul. Raise the fallen. Confirm the upright. Bring back those who have strayed. Support the widows and orphans. Help the needy. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         برَحْمَتِكَ ياربُّ خَلِّصْ نُفوسَنَا أجْمَعِين. ياربُّ خَلِّصْ شَعْبكَ، بَارِكْ مِيراثَكَ، ارْعَهُمْ وسُسْهُمْ إلى الأبَدِ. خَلِّصْ الذينَ في الشَّدائدِ، والضِّيقَاتِ، والأحْزان. حلَّ المأسُورينَ مِنْ رباطِ الشَّيَاطِينِ، أشْبعْ الجيَاعَ مِنَ الخَيْراتِ، عَزِّ صَغِيرِي القُلوبِ والنُّفوسِ. أقِمْ السَّاقِطينَ، ثَبِّتْ القائِمينَ، رُدَّ الضَّالَّينَ، عُلْ الأرَامِلَ والأيْتامَ، أسعفْ المُعْوزِيِنَ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Give blessing to the fruits of the earth, good temper to the air, growth to the trees, and full measure to the rivers. Bless dew and rain. Give contentment to the poor. Pay for the debtors. Gather together the dispersed. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         أعْطِ بَركَةً لِثِمارِ الأرضِ، مِزاجاً طيِّباً للهواَءِ، نُمواً للأشْجارِ، صُعوداً كامِلاً لميَاهِ الأنْهارِ. بَارِكْ في النَّدَى والأمْطَارِ. أعْطِ قَناعةً للمُحتَاجِينَ. أوْفِ عَن المَديونينَ. اجْمَعْ شِتَاتَ المُتَفرِّقينَ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Accept the repentance of the repentant. Receive the confession of the confessors. Give understanding to the catechumens. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         اقْبَلْ تَوبَةَ التَّائبِينَ. اقْبَلْ إعتِرافَ المُعْتَرِفينَ. أعْطِ فَهماً للموْعوظينَ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Judge, O Lord, in favor of the oppressed. Fill our hearts with happiness, gladness, comfort and joy that we, having sufficiency in everything, always may abound in good and acceptable deeds. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         احْكُمْ يَاربُّ للمَظْلومِينَ. إمْلأ قُلوبَنَا فَرحاً، وبَهجةً، وعَزاءً، وسُرُوراً، ونَعِيماً لكيْما إذا نِلْنَا الكفاية في كُلِّ شئٍ، نَتَناهَى في الأعْمالِ الصَّالحَةِ المَرضِيَّةِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Bless, O Lord, the harvest with Your heavenly blessings. Bless the crown of this year with Your goodness. Bless, O Lord, those who sow, plant, and reap, as You blessed for the children of Israel the harvest of the sixth year.  
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         بَارِكْ ياربُّ في الغَلاَّتِ بالبَرَكاتِ السَّمائِيَّةِ. بَارِكْ ياربُّ إكليلَ هذه السَّنَةِ بصَلاحِكَ. بَارِكْ ياربُّ للبَاذِرِ، والزَّارعِ، والغَارسِ، والحَاصِدِ، كما بَاركْتَ لِبَنِي إسْرائِيلَ في غَلاَّتِ العَامِ السَّادسِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Bless, O Lord, this, our congregation and all congregations of the orthodox people. Keep for us and upon us the life and standing of our honored father the patriarch, Pope Abba (...), the patriarch of this time (and his partner in the apostolic liturgy, our father the bishop (metropolitan) Abba (...); save him (them), O Lord, and save his (their) people from all afflictions, temptations, and hardships, along with his (their) partners in the apostolic service, our fathers the metropolitans, our fathers the bishops, our fathers the hegumens, our fathers the priests, our brothers the deacons, our fathers the monks, and our brethren the laymen. As for those who came now, attending and participating with us in this prayer and all orthodox prayers, asking forgiveness of their sins and mercy for their souls, bless us and bless them; absolve us and absolve them; forgive our sins and their sins, in the past and in the future, the personal and impersonal, the sins of the day and sins of the night, the hidden and manifest. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         بَارِكْ ياربُّ في إجْتِماعِنَا هذا، وكُلِّ إجْتِماعِ الشُّعوبِ الأرْثُوذُكسِيِّين. واحْفَظْ لنَا وعَليْنا، حَيَاةَ وقيامَ أبِينا السَّيِّدِ الأبِ البَطريَركِ أنبا ... بَطريَركُ هذا الزَّمَانِ. [وشريكه في الخدمة الرسولية أبينا الأسقف (المطران) المكرم الأنبا ...]، خَلِّصْهُ (ما) ياربُّ وخَلِّصْ شَعْبَهُ (ما) مِنْ جَمِيعِ البَلايَا والتَّجارُبِ والأحْزانِ. وكذلكَ شُركاءَهُ في الخدمَةِ الرسوليَّةِ: آبَاءَنَا المَطارِنَةِ، وآبَاءَنَا الأسَاقِفةِ، وآبَاءَنَا القَمامِصَةِ، وآبَاءَنَا القُسوسِ، وإخْوتَنَا الشَّمامِسَةِ، وآبَاءَنَا الرُّهْبَانِ، وإخْوتَنَا العلمانِيِّينَ، والذينَ أتَوا وحَضروا واشتَركوا مَعنَا في هذه الصَّلاةِ، وكُلِّ صَلواتِ الأرثُوذُكسِيِّينَ، الآنَ، طَالِبينَ مغفِرةَ خَطايَاهُم، ورَحْمَةً لِنُفُوسِهِم. بَارِكْنَا وبَارِكْهُم، حَالِلْنَا وحَالِلهُم. اغْفِرْ خَطايَانَا وخَطايَاهُم: الماضِيَّةَ والمُستَأنفَةَ، الذَّاتِيَّةَ وغَيرَ الذَّاتِيَّةِ، اللَّيليَّة والنَّهاريَّةَ، الظَّاهرةَ والخَفِيَّةَ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Keep, O Lord, the liveliness of holy orthodox congregations, churches, and monasteries, and the elders who live in them, and those who are serving them, those who are managing them and those who are dwelling in them. Grant that security, peace, love, and stability be in them. Subdue the evil enemy under their feet and our feet. Do not allow him to have any part in them or in us, neither by the left attack or the right attack. Keep them with Your most high hand and strong arm. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         أدِمْ ياربُّ عَمَارَ المجَامِعِ، والبِيَّعِ المُقدَّسَةِ، والبَراري الأرثُوذكْسِيَّةِ، والشُّيوخِ السَّاكِنينَ فيها، وخُدَّامِها ونُظارِها ومَنْ بِهَا، وأجْعَلْ الأمنَ، والسَّلامَ، والمحَبَّةَ، والطمأنِينَةَ بَيْنَهُم. وأخْضِعْ العَدوَّ الشِّرِّيرَ تَحْتَ أقْدامِنا وأقْدامِهِم. ولا تَجْعَلْ لهُ فِينَا ولا فيهُم نَصيباً، لا بضَربَةِ شِمالٍ ولا بِضَربةِ يَمينٍ. وأحْفَظْهُم بِيَدِكَ العَاليَةِ وذراعِكَ الحَصِينَةِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Deliver us, O my Master, from bad temptations and traps that are set, seen or unseen. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         نجِّنا يا سَيِّدي مِنَ التَّجاربِ الرَّديئةِ، والأشْراكِ المَنصُوبَةِ، المَرئيَّةِ وغَير المرئيَّةِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Remember, O Lord, our fathers, our mothers, our brethren, our families, our relatives, our teachers, our spiritual and natural children, and all of the children of baptism. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         أذكُرْ ياربُّ آباءَنَا، وأُمَّهاتِنَا، وإخوتَنَا، وأهْلنَا، وأقاربَنَا، ومُعلِّمِينَا، وأولادَنا الرُّوحيينَ، والجَسَدِيِّينَ، وسَائِرَ بَني المَعموديَّةِ أجْمعِينَ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Remember, O Lord, those from whom we ate and drank of their effort and labor, and who sheltered us in their houses and gave us from their hands. Reward them, O Lord, and give them the incorruptible instead of the corruptible, the heavenly instead of the earthly. Fill their houses and stores with all good things. Reward them, O Lord, thirty, sixty, and a hundred-fold, along with the forgiveness of their sins in the kingdom of heaven. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         أذكُرْ ياربُّ الذينَ لهُم مَعنا تعبٌ وشركةٌ. أذكُرْ ياربُّ الذينَ أكَلنا وشَرِبْنا مِنْ كَدَّهِم وتَعَبهم، وآوونَا في مَنازِلهم، وأعْطُونا مِنْ أيْديهِم. عَوِّضْهُم ياربُّ عِوَضَ الفَانِياتِ بالبَاقياتِ، والأرْضيَّاتِ بالسَّمائِيَّاتِ. إمْلأ بيوتَهُمْ ومَخازِنَهُمْ مِنْ كُلَّ الخَيراتِ. عَوِّضْهُمْ ياربُّ عِوَضَ الواحد ثَلاثِينَ وسِتِّينَ ومَائةً، وغُفْرانَ خَطايَاهُمْ في مَلكوتِ السَّمَواتِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Remember O Lord, those who give alms to us or to our brethren the needy in all forms of charity, for loving You and honoring Your holy name; bless them. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         أذكُرْ ياربُّ الذين أحْسَنُوا إلينَا وإلى إخْوتِنَا المسَاكِينِ بجَمِيع وجُوهِ الحَسَناتِ، مَحبَّةً فِيكَ وإكراماً لإسْمِكَ القُدُّوسِ، باركْهُم.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Remember, O Lord, those who care for the sacrifices, oblations, donations, wine, oil, first-fruits, incense, coverings, vows, books and all altar vessels; reward them O Lord, for their gifts by the forgiveness of their sins. Grant them a happy life in this present age, and the eternal life in the age to come.
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         أذكُرْ ياربُّ المُهْتَمِّينَ بالصَّعائِدِ، والقَرابِينِ، والمُحْرَقَاتِ، والخَمْرِ، والزَّيْتِ، والبُكورِ، والبَخُورِ، والسُّتُورِ، والنُّذورِ، وكُتبِ القراءةِ، وكُلِّ أوانِي المَذْبَحِ جَميعاً. عَوِّضهُم ياربُّ عن عَطايَاهُم بغُفرانِ خَطايَاهُم، وهَبْ لهُم في هذا الدَّهرِ الحَاضِرِ الحَياةَ الهَنيئَةَ، وفي الدَّهر الآتِي الحَيَاةَ الأبَدِيَّةَ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Remember, O Lord, our fathers and brethren who have already fallen asleep and reposed in the orthodox faith; repose, O Lord, all their souls in the bosom of our fathers, Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, in the region of the living, in the heavenly Jerusalem. As for us, the living, help us for the salvation of our souls. Manage our lives according to Your good will.
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         أذكُرْ ياربُّ آباءَنَا وإخْوتَنا الذينَ سَبقوا فَرَقَدوا وأضطجعوا وتَنَيَّحوا في الإيمَان المُستقِيمِ بالمسِيحِ. نَيِّحْ ياربُّ نُفُوسَهُمْ أجْمَعِينَ في حِضنّ آبَائِنا القِدِّيسِينَ إبراهيمَ وإسحَقَ ويَعْقُوبَ، في كُورةِ الأحْياءِ في فِرْدَوس النَّعِيمِ. أمَّا نَحنُ الأحْياءَ فأعِنَّا على خَلاصِ نُفُوسِنا، ودَبِّرْ حَياتَنَا حَسَبَ إرادَتِكَ الصَّالِحَةِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Graciously, O Lord, remember my abject self, my poverty, and my weakness. I, the sinner and miserable, who is not worthy to stand in Your presence due to the multitude of my sins and iniquities, do not reject me. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         تَفضَّل ياربُّ أذكُرْ حَقارَتِي وذُلِّي وضَعْفِي، أنا الخَاطِئُ الشَّقِيُّ غير المُسْتَحقِّ الوقوفِ بينَ يَديْكَ مِنْ أجْلِ كَثْرةِ خَطَايَايَ وذُنُوبِي، لا ترْذلْني.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Raise, O Lord, a horn of salvation for your people by the sign of Your life-giving cross. Grant, O Lord, Your relief during tribulations, Your help during hardships and disasters. Save us, O Lord, and save all those who are in distress. Heal the sick of Your people. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         أقِمْ ياربُّ قَرْنَ خَلاصِ شَعْبِكَ بإشَارةِ صَليبِكَ المُحْيي. فَرَجُكَ ياربُّ عِندَ الشِّدَّةِ، وعَونُكَ ياربُّ عِندَ الكَربِ والذِّلةِ. خَلِّصْنَا ياربُّ وخَلِّصْ كُلَّ مَنْ في شِدَّةٍ، ومَرضَى شَعْبِكَ أشفِهِم.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Make, O Lord, Your Christian people, those who are present with us, and those who are absent, to be blessed and absolved from Your divine mouth, from the rising of the sun to its setting, and from the north to the south. Accept us unto You, as You accepted the thief on the right hand while You were on the tree of the cross, and granted him the Paradise of Joy. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         واجْعَلْ ياربُّ شَعْبَكَ المسِيحيِّينَ الحَاضِرِينَ مَعَنا والغَائِبينَ عنَّا أنْ يَكونُوا مُبارَكِينَ، مُحالَلِينَ، مِنْ فَمِكَ الإلهِي، مِنْ مَشارقِ الشَّمس إلى مَغاربهَا، ومِنَ الشَّمَالِ إلى اَلْجَنُوبِ. وأقبَلنَا إليْكَ كمَا قَبِلْتَ اللِّصَّ اليَمِينَ، وأنتَ على خَشَبةِ الصَّلِيبِ، ووَهَبْتَ لهُ فِردَوسَ النَّعيمِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Remember, O Lord, the orphans, the widows, the isolated, the incapacitated, and those who have no one to mention them. Remember them and us, O Lord, in the heavenly Jerusalem. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         أذكُرْ ياربُّ الأيْتامَ، والأرامِلَ، والمُنْقَطِعينَ، والعَاجِزِينَ، والذينَ ليسَ لهُمْ أحدٌ يَذكُرَهُمْ. أذكُرْنَا ياربُّ نَحنُ وإيَّاهُم في أورشَليم السَّمائيَّةِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Remember, O Lord, those who are standing up or sitting down, or laying down or ejected; those who are traveling by land, sea or air, in rough or smooth ways, in valleys, roadways, mountaintops, hills or caves. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         أذكُرْ ياربُّ القَائمِينَ والقَاعدِينَ، والرَّاقدِينَ والمَطْروحِينَ، والمُسافِرينَ في البَرِّ والبَحْرِ والهَواءِ، والسَّهْلِ والوَعْرِ، والأوديَةِ والطُّرُقاتِ، ورُؤوسِ الجِبالِ والتِّلالِ والمغَايرِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Those who are in dungeons or prisons, and those who are in exile or captivity, and those who are held in the bondage of authorities and devils, deliver them. Bring them back and bring them all into a safe haven, victorious, satisfied, and healthy in soul, body and spirit. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         والذِينَ في المطَابقِ والسُّجُونِ، والذِينَ في السَّبْي والنَّفي، والمأسُورينَ والمرْبُوطِينَ بربَاطِ السَّلاطِينِ والشَّياطِينِ. رُدَّهُمْ وأْتِ بِهمْ جَمِيعاً إلى المِيناءِ سَالِمينَ، غَانِمينَ، كَاسِبينَ، رابحِينَ، مُعافِي النَّفْسَ والجَسَدَ والرُّوحَ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Grant, my Lord Jesus Christ, that this, our prayer, be acceptable to You, without hypocrisy, pride, haughtiness or blemish. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         واجْعَلْ يا ربِّي يَسُوعُ المسيحُ صَلاتَنَا هذه أنْ تَكونَ مَقْبُولةً أمَامَكَ، بغَيْرِ رياءٍ، ولا كِبْريَاءٍ، ولا عَظَمَةٍ، ولا إفْتِخَارٍ، ولا عَيْبٍ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Help us, O God, to please You. Help us to follow Your commandments. Help us to overcome the pangs of death, before death and after death, for You are a good God, longsuffering and abundant in mercy and compassion. O God, make the door of Your church to be open for us through the ages and to the end of all ages. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         أعِنَّا يا اللَّهُ على رضَاكَ، أعِنَّا على العَمَل بوصَايَاكَ، أعِنَّا على سَكَراتِ المَوت، وما قَبْلَ المَوتِ، وما بَعدَ المَوتِ. لأنَّكَ أنْتَ إلهٌ صَالِحٌ، طويلُ الرُّوحِ، كثيرُ الرَّحمَةِ والتَحنُّن. اللَّهُمَّ اجْعَلْ بابَ بِيِعَتِكَ مفْتُوحاً أمَامَ وجوهِنَا على مَمَرَّ الدُّهُورِ والأزمانِ، وإلى آخِرِ كُلِّ زَمانٍ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         Have mercy on us, O God, according to Your great mercy, through the great intercessor, the source of purity, generosity and blessedness, the Lady of us all, the pride of our race, the Virgin, the chosen St. Mary, the honorable martyr St. Mark, the evangelist, the apostle and the preacher of the land of Egypt, and all the angels, patriarchs, prophets, apostles, martyrs, saints, anchorites, worshippers, hermits, strivers and those who pleased You by their good deeds, from Adam to the end of ages. 
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         ارْحَمْنَا يا اللَّهُ كَعَظِيمِ رَحْمَتِكَ. بشَفاعَةِ ذَاتِ الشَّفاعَاتِ، مَعْدن الطُّهْرِ والجودِ والبَركاتِ، سَيِّدتِنا كُلنا، وفَخْر جِنْسِنا، العَذراءِ البَتولِ الزكيَّةِ مرتمريمَ، والشَّهيدِ المُكَرَّم مَارمُرقسَ الإنْجِيليِّ الرَّسُولِ كاروزِ الدِّيارِ المصريَّةِ، وكافَّةِ الملائِكةِ، والآباءِ، والأنبياءِ، والرُّسلِ، والشُّهداءِ، والقدِّيسِينَ، والسُّواحِ، والعُبَّادِ، والنُّسَّاكِ المُجَاهدينَ، والذينَ أرضوا الربُّ بأعمالِهِم الصَّالِحَةِ مُنذُ آدمَ إلى آخِرِ الدُّهُورِ.
      </Language>
   </Text>
         
   <Text>
      <Language id="English">
         We worship You, O Holy Trinity, the Father, and the Son and the Holy Spirit. Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.
      </Language>
      <Language id="Arabic">
         ولكَ نَسْجُدُ أيُّها الثَّالوثُ القُدُّوس الآبُ والابنُ والرُّوحُ القُدُسُ، الآنَ وكُلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دَهرِ الدَّاهِرِين، أمين.
      </Language>
   </Text>
</Document>