<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<ns0:Document xmlns:ns0="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" Agpeya="true">
   <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">The Prayer of the Veil</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">صلاةُ السِتَارِ</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         This prayer concerns monks, yet it is suitable for individual meditation. It is prayed daily in monasteries.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وهي خاصَّةٌ بالآباءِ الرُّهبانِ، ولكِنَّها مُناسِبةٌ أيضاً للتأمُلِ الفردي. ويُصلَّى بها يومياً في الأديُرةِ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
      
   <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Introduction of Every Hour</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">مُقدِمةُ كلِّ ساعةٍ</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
    
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ ⲫ̀ⲣⲁⲛ ⲙ̀Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In the name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, one God. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         باسمِ الآبِ والابنِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ الإلهِ الواحدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         <ns0:span class="Coptic">Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ</ns0:span>. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord bless us. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         <ns0:span class="Coptic">Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ.</ns0:span>  ياربُّ ارحَمْ. ياربُّ ارحَمْ. ياربُّ بارِكْ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit. Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجدُ للآبِ والابنِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Our Father</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">أبانا الذي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲧⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲁ ⲛ̀ϫⲟⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Make us worthy to pray thankfully:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اللهُمَّ اجعلْنا مُستحقينَ أن نقولَ بشكرٍ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ Ⲡⲉⲛⲓⲱⲧ ⲉⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be Thy name.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أبانا الذي في السماواتِ ليتقدسِ اسمُكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲥⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ: ⲡⲉⲧⲉϩⲛⲁⲕ ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥϣⲱⲡⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲕⲁϩⲓ:  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Thy kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليأتِ ملكوتُكَ، لتكُن مشيئتُكَ، كما في السماءِ كذلكَ على الأرضِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲓⲕ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲣⲁⲥϯ ⲙⲏⲓϥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲫⲟⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲣⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Give us this day our daily bread and forgive us our trespasses, as we forgive those who trespass against us and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         خبزَنا الذي للغدِّ أعطِنا اليومَ، واغفِرْ لنا ذنوبَنا كما نغفِرُ نحنُ أيضاً للمُذنبينَ إلينا، ولا تُدخِلنا في تجرِبةٍ لكِنْ نجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ: ϫⲉ ⲑⲱⲕ ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In Christ Jesus our Lord. For Thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, forever. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِّنا. لأنَّ لكَ المُلكَ والقوةَ والمجدَ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">The Prayer of Thanksgiving</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">صلاةُ الشكر</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>

      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲛϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲟⲧϥ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲉϥⲉⲣⲡⲉⲑⲛⲁⲛⲉϥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲏⲧ: Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲛⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Let us give thanks to the beneficent and merciful God, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         فلنشكرْ صانعَ الخيراتِ، الرحومَ اللهَ أبا ربِّنا وإلَهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>   
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ ⲁϥⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲕⲉⲡⲁⲍⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲁϥⲉⲣⲃⲟⲏ̀ⲑⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁϥⲁ̀ⲣⲉϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁϥϣⲟⲡⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟϥ ⲁϥϯⲁ̀ⲥⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁϥϯⲧⲟⲧⲉⲛ ⲁϥⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲓⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩ ⲑⲁⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         For He has covered us, helped us, guarded us, accepted us to Himself, spared us, supported us, and has brought us to this hour.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         لأنهُ سترَنا وأعانَنا وحفظَنا وقبلَنا إليهِ وأشفقَ علَينا وعضدَنا وأتى بِنا إلى هذهِ الساعةِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲛⲑⲟϥ ⲟⲛ ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟϥ ϩⲟⲡⲱⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲁ̀ⲣⲉϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲁⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲛϧ: ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲓⲣⲏⲛⲏ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲓⲡⲁⲛⲧⲟⲕⲣⲁⲧⲱⲣ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Let us also ask Him, the Lord our God, the Pantocrator, to guard us in all peace this holy day and all the days of our life.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         هو أيضاً فلنسألْهُ أن يحفظَنا في هذا اليومِ المُقدسِ، وكلِّ أيامِ حياتِنا بكلِّ سلامٍ، الضابطَ الكلِّ الربَّ إلهَنا.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲛⲏⲃ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲡⲓⲡⲁⲛⲧⲟⲕⲣⲁⲧⲱⲣ: Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲛⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Master, Lord, God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أيها السيدُ الربُّ الإلهُ ضابطُ الكلِّ، أبو ربِّنا وإلَهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>   
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲟⲧⲕ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         we thank You for everything, concerning everything, and in everything.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نشكرُكَ على كلِّ حالٍ، ومِنْ أجلِ كلِّ حالٍ، وفي كلِّ حالٍ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ ⲁⲕⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲕⲉⲡⲁⲍⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲁⲕⲉⲣⲃⲟⲏ̀ⲑⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁⲕⲁ̀ⲣⲉϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁⲕϣⲟⲡⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ: ⲁⲕϯⲁ̀ⲥⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁⲕϯⲧⲟⲧⲉⲛ ⲁⲕⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲓⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩ ⲑⲁⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         For You have covered us, helped us, guarded us, accepted us to Yourself, spared us, supported us, and have brought us to this hour.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         لأنكَ سترتَنا وأعنتَنا وحفظتَنا، وقبلتَنا إليكَ، وأشفقتَ علينا وعضَّدتَنا وأتيتَ بنا إلى هذهِ الساعةِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲧⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲧⲉⲛⲧⲱⲃϩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ ⲡⲓⲙⲁⲓⲣⲱⲙⲓ: ⲙⲏⲓⲥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉⲑⲣⲉⲛϫⲱⲕ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲙ̀ⲡⲁⲓⲕⲉⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲫⲁⲓ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲛϧ: ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲓⲣⲏⲛⲏ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲧⲉⲕϩⲟϯ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Therefore, we ask and entreat Your goodness, O Lover of Mankind, grant us to complete this holy day and all the days of our life in all peace with Your fear.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         مِنْ أجلِ هذا نسألُ ونطلبُ مِنْ صلاحِكَ يا محبَّ البشرِ، امنحنا أن نكمِّلَ هذا اليومَ المُقدسَ، وكلَّ أيامِ حياتِنا بكلِّ سلامٍ معَ خوفِكَ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲑⲟⲛⲟⲥ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ⲉ̀ⲛⲉⲣⲅⲓⲁ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡ̀ⲥⲁⲧⲁⲛⲁⲥ: ⲡ̀ⲥⲟϭⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ϩⲁⲛⲣⲱⲙⲓ ⲉⲩϩⲱⲟⲩ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡ̀ⲧⲱⲛϥ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ϣⲱⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ϩⲁⲛϫⲁϫⲓ ⲛⲏⲉⲧϩⲏⲡ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉⲑⲟⲩⲱⲛϩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         All envy, all temptation, all the work of Satan, the counsel of wicked men and the rising up of enemies, hidden and manifest,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         كلُّ حسدٍ وكلُّ تجربةٍ وكلُّ فعلِ الشيطانِ، ومؤامرةُ الناسِ الأشرارِ، وقيامُ الأعداءِ الخفيينَ والظاهرينَ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="!Agpeya">
         <ns0:Comment>         
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               The priest bows his head toward the East and signs himself with the sign of the cross, saying:
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               يطامن الكاهن رأسه إلى الشرق ويرشم ذاته بمثال الصليب قائلاً:
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Comment>         
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲁ̀ⲗⲓⲧⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁⲣⲟⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         take them away from us
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         انزعْها عنَّا.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="!Agpeya">
         <ns0:Comment>         
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Then he turns toward the west from his right and makes the sign of the cross over the people, saying the following. If the Pope, a metropolitan, or a bishop is present, he makes the sign of the cross over the people and says the following instead of the priest.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               ثم يلتفت إلى الغرب عن يمينه ويرشم الشعب قائلاً:[إذا كان الأب البابا أو المطران أو الأسقف حاضراً فهو الذي يرشم الشعب ويقول ذلك.]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲉⲕⲗⲁⲟⲥ ⲧⲏⲣϥ
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         and from all Your people,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وعن سائرِ شعبِكَ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="Baptism | Unction | LiturgyOfTheWaters | Engagement | Crowning | FuneralPrayer | GeneralFuneralPrayer | Ordination">
         <ns0:Group>
            <ns0:Season id="ConsecrationOfWaters | BathingPrayer | LiturgyOfTheWaters">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲕⲟⲗⲩⲙⲃⲏⲑⲣⲁ ⲑⲁⲓ
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this basin,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذه الفسقيةِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="AbsolutionOfWoman">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲥ̀ϩⲓⲙⲓ ⲑⲁⲓ:
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this woman,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذه المرأةِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Unction">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉⲧϣⲱⲛⲓ 
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this infirm person,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذا المريضِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Engagement">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉⲧⲁϥⲱⲡ ⲛ̀ⲥⲁ ⲑⲁⲓ
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this betrothed couple,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذين الخطيبين
                  </ns0:Language>
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Crowning">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲛⲁⲓⲡⲁⲧϣⲉⲗⲉⲧ ⲛⲁⲓ
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this bridegroom and bride,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذين العروسين.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="(FuneralPrayer ^ !FuneralMemorial) | GeneralFuneralPrayer">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲯⲩⲭⲏ ⲑⲁⲓ 
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this soul,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذه النفسِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Ordination">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this Your servant,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن عبدك هذا.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
         </ns0:Group>
         
         <ns0:Group>
            <ns0:Season id="!Agpeya">
               <ns0:Comment>         
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     Then he turns towards the East, making the sign of the cross, saying:
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     ثم يلتفت إلى الشرق قائلا:
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Comment>
            </ns0:Season>
         </ns0:Group>
      </ns0:Season>

      <ns0:Season id="HomeBlessing">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲁⲓⲏⲓ ⲫⲁⲓ
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               and from this house,
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وعن هذا البيتِ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>

      <ns0:Season id="!OfferingOfLamb ^ !Agpeya ^ !Ordination">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲉⲕⲕ̀ⲗⲏⲥⲓⲁ̀ ⲑⲁⲓ
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               and from this church,
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وعن هذه الكنيسةِ.
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
         
         <ns0:Comment>         
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Then he turns toward the East, making the sign of the cross on the altar, saying:
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               ثم يلتفت إلى الشرق ويرشم على المذبح قائلاً:
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="OfferingOfLamb">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲧ̀ⲣⲁⲡⲉⲍⲁ ⲑⲁⲓ
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               and from this table,
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وعن هذه المائدة،
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲁⲓⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲕ ⲫⲁⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         and from this Your holy place.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وعن موضعِكَ المُقدسِ هذا.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲛⲏ ⲇⲉ ⲉⲑⲛⲁⲛⲉⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉⲧⲉⲣⲛⲟϥⲣⲓ ⲥⲁϩⲛⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲱⲟⲩ ⲛⲁⲛ: ϫⲉ ⲛ̀ⲑⲟⲕ ⲡⲉ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲕϯ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲉⲣϣⲓϣⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲉ̀ϩⲱⲙⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ⲛⲓϩⲟϥ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓϭ̀ⲗⲏ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲧⲏⲣⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲓϫⲁϫⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         But those things which are good and profitable do provide for us, for it is You who have given us the authority to tread on serpents and scorpions, and upon all the power of the enemy.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أمَّا الصالحاتُ والنافعاتُ فارزقنا إياها لأنكَ أنتَ الذي أعطيتَنا السلطانَ أن ندوسَ على الحياتِ والعقاربَ وعلى كلِّ قوةِ العدوِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ: ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ولا تُدْخِلْنا في تجربةٍ لكن نَجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲓϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓⲙⲉⲧϣⲉⲛϩⲏⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲙⲁⲓⲣⲱⲙⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲙⲟⲛⲟⲅⲉⲛⲏⲥ ⲛ̀Ϣⲏⲣⲓ: Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲛⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Through the grace, compassion, and love-of-mankind of Your only-begotten Son, our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالنعمةِ والرأفاتِ ومحبةِ البشرِ اللواتي لابنِكَ الوحيدِ، ربِّنا وإلهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲓⲧⲟⲧϥ ⲉ̀ⲣⲉ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲧⲁⲓⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲁ̀ⲙⲁϩⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲕⲩⲛⲏⲥⲓⲥ: ⲉⲣⲡ̀ⲣⲉⲡⲓ ⲛⲁⲕ ⲛⲉⲙⲁϥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲛ̀ⲣⲉϥⲧⲁⲛϧⲟ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ⲟ̀ⲙⲟⲟⲩⲥⲓⲟⲥ ⲛⲉⲙⲁⲕ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         through whom the glory, honor, dominion, and worship are due unto You, with Him and the Holy Spirit, the Giver of Life, who is of one essence with You,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         هذا الذي مِنْ قبَلِه، المجدُ والكرامةُ والعزة والسجودُ، تليقُ بكَ معَهُ، ومعَ الرّوحِ القُدُسِ المُحيي المساوي لكَ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϯⲛⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛ̀ⲥⲏⲟⲩ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         now and at all times and unto the age of all ages. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ كلِّها. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 50
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ الخمسونَ
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲏⲓ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ⲡⲉⲕⲛⲓϣϯ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲓ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ⲡ̀ⲁ̀ϣⲁⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧϣⲉⲛϩⲏⲧ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲥⲱⲗϫ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲁ̀ⲙⲟⲛⲓⲁ̀: ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲣⲁϧⲧ ⲛ̀ϩⲟⲩⲟ̀ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲁⲛⲟⲃⲓ: ϫⲉ ⲧⲁⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ̀ ⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲕ ϯⲥⲱⲟⲩⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲥ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲁⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡⲁⲙ̀ⲑⲟ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗⲛ̀ⲥⲏⲟⲩ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Have mercy upon me, O God, according to Your great mercy; and according to the multitude of Your compassions blot out my iniquity. Wash me thoroughly from my iniquity, and cleanse me from my sin. For I am conscious of my iniquity; and my sin is at all times before me.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ارحَمْنِي يا اللهُ كَعَظيمِ رَحْمتِكَ، ومِثْلِ كَثْرةِ رَأفتِكَ امْحُ إثْمِي واغْسلْنِي كَثيراً مِنْ إثْمِي، ومِنْ خَطيئَتِي طهِّرْنِي. لأنِّي أنا عارِفٌ بإثْمِي، وخَطيئَتِي أمَامِي في كلِّ حينٍ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲛⲑⲟⲕ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁⲩⲁⲧⲕ ⲁⲓⲉⲣⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ ⲁⲓⲁⲓϥ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕⲙ̀ⲑⲟ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ϩⲟⲡⲱⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲁⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲕⲥⲁϫⲓ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲕ ϭⲣⲟ ⲉⲕⲛⲁϭⲓϩⲁⲡ. Hⲏⲡⲡⲉ ⲅⲁⲣ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ̀ ⲁⲩⲉⲣⲃⲟⲕⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲓ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲁ̀ ⲧⲁⲙⲁⲩ ϭⲓϣϣⲱⲟⲩ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲓ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Against You only I have sinned, and done evil before You, that You might be just in Your sayings, and might overcome when You are judged. For, behold, I was conceived in iniquities, and in sins my mother conceived me.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لَكَ وحْدَكَ أخْطأْتُ، والشَّرَّ قدامَكَ صَنعْتُ، لِكيْ تَتَبرَّرَ في أقْوالِكَ، وتَغْلبَ إذَا حوكِمْتَ. لأنِّي هَأنَذَا بالإثْمِ حُبِلَ بِي، وبالَخَطايَا ولدَتْني أمِّي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Hⲏⲡⲡⲉ ⲅⲁⲣ ⲁⲕⲙⲉⲛⲣⲉ ⲑ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: ⲛⲏⲉⲧϩⲏⲡ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛ̀ⲥⲉⲟⲩⲱⲛϩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲁⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲥⲟⲫⲓⲁ ⲁⲕⲧⲁⲙⲟⲓ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ. Ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲛⲟⲩϫϧ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕϣⲉⲛϩⲩⲥⲱⲡⲟⲛ: ⲉⲓⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲣⲁϧⲧ ⲉⲓⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲃⲁϣ ⲉ̀ϩⲟⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲭⲓⲱⲛ: ⲉⲕⲉⲑ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲱⲧⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲟⲩⲟⲩⲛⲟϥ: ⲉⲩⲉ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲛⲓⲕⲁⲥ ⲉⲧⲑⲉⲃⲓⲏⲟⲩⲧ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            For, behold, You have loved the truth; You have manifested to me the hidden and unrevealed things of Your wisdom. You shall sprinkle me with Your hyssop, and I shall be purified. You shall wash me, and I shall be made whiter than snow. You shall make me to hear gladness and joy; the humbled bones shall rejoice.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لأنَّكَ هَكَذا قَدْ أحْبَبتَ الحقَّ، إذْ أوْضَحتَ لِي غَوامِضَ حِكْمتِكَ ومَسْتُورَاتِها. تَنضَحُ عَليَّ بِزُوفَاكَ فأُطَهَّرُ، تَغْسلُنِي فَأبْيضُّ أكْثَرَ مِنَ الثَّلجِ. تُسْمعُنِي سُرُوراً وفَرحاً، فتَبْتهجُ عِظامِي المتواضِعةُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲙⲁⲧⲁⲥⲑⲟ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕϩⲟ ⲥⲁⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲛⲟⲃⲓ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛⲁⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ̀ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲥⲟⲗϫⲟⲩ. Ⲟⲩϩⲏⲧ ⲉϥⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲥⲟⲛⲧϥ ⲛ̀ϧⲏⲧ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ: ⲟⲩⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉϥⲥⲟⲩⲧⲱⲛ ⲁ̀ⲣⲓⲧϥ ⲙ̀ⲃⲉⲣⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲏⲉⲧⲥⲁϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲃⲉⲣⲃⲱⲣⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲉⲕϩⲟ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲕⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲟⲗϥ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁⲣⲟⲓ. Ⲙⲟⲓ ⲛⲏⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲟⲩϫⲁⲓ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲛ̀ϩⲏⲅⲉⲙⲱⲛⲓⲕⲟⲛ ⲙⲁⲧⲁϫⲣⲟⲓ: ⲉⲓⲉ̀ⲧ̀ⲥⲁⲃⲉ ⲛⲓⲁⲛⲟⲙⲟⲥ ϩⲓ ⲛⲉⲕⲙⲱⲓⲧ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛⲓⲁⲥⲉⲃⲏⲥ ⲉⲩⲉ̀ⲕⲟⲧⲟⲩ ϩⲁⲣⲟⲕ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Turn away Your face from my sins, and blot out all my iniquities. Create in me a clean heart, O God; and renew a right spirit in my inward parts. Do not cast me away from Your face; and do not remove Your Holy Spirit from me. Give me the joy of Your salvation, and uphold me with a directing spirit. Then I shall teach the transgressors Your ways; and the ungodly men shall turn to You.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اصْرِفْ وجْهَكَ عَنْ خَطايَايَ وامْحُ كلَّ آثَامِي. قَلباً نَقياً اخْلقْ فيَّ يا اللهُ، ورُوحاً مُسْتَقيماً جدِّدهُ في أحْشَائِي. لا تَطْرحْنِي مِنْ قُدَّامِ وجْهِكَ، ورُوحُكَ القُدُّوسُ لا تَنْزعْهُ مِنِّي. امْنَحْنِي بَهْجةَ خَلاصِكَ، وبرُوحٍ رئاسيٍ اعْضُدْنِي فأُعلِّمُ الأثَمَةَ طُرُقَكَ، والمنَافِقونَ إليكَ يَرجِعونَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛⲥ̀ⲛⲟϥ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ: Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲧⲁⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣⲓⲁ: ⲉϥⲉ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲁⲗⲁⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧⲉⲕⲇⲓⲕⲉⲟⲥⲩⲛⲏ. Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲥ̀ⲫⲟⲧⲟⲩ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲉ ⲣⲱⲓ ϫⲱ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕⲥ̀ⲙⲟⲩ: ϫⲉ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉ ⲁⲕⲟⲩⲱϣ ϣⲟⲩϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ: ⲛⲁⲓⲛⲁϯ ⲟⲛ ⲡⲉ: ϩⲁⲛϭⲗⲓⲗ ⲛ̀ϫⲟϥϫⲉϥ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕϯⲙⲁϯ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲟⲩ. Ⲡⲓϣⲟⲩϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉϥⲧⲉⲛⲛⲏⲟⲩⲧ ⲡⲉ: ⲟⲩϩⲏⲧ ⲉϥⲧⲉⲛⲛⲏⲟⲩⲧ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲉϥⲉ̀ⲑⲉⲃⲓⲏⲟⲩⲧ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲛ̀ⲛⲉ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ϣⲟϣϥ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Deliver me from blood, O God, the God of my salvation, and my tongue shall rejoice in Your righteousness. O Lord, You shall open my lips, and my mouth shall declare Your praise. For if You desired sacrifice, I would have given it; You do not take pleasure in burnt offerings. The sacrifice of God is a broken spirit; a broken and humbled heart God shall not despise.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            نَجِّنِي مِنَ الدِّماءِ يا اللهُ إلَهَ خَلاصِي، فيَبتهِجُ لِسانِي بعَدلِكَ. ياربُّ افْتَحْ شَفتَيَّ، فَيُخبرُ فَمِي بَتَسْبيحِكَ. لأنَّكَ لَوْ آثَرتَ الذَّبيحةَ لَكُنْتُ الآنَ أعْطِي؛ ولَكنَّكَ لا تُسرُّ بالَمُحْرقَاتِ فالذَبيحَةُ للهِ رُوحٌ مُنْسحقٌ. القَلْبُ المنْكسِرُ والمتَواضِعُ لا يُرْذلُهُ اللهُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲁⲣⲓⲡⲉⲑⲛⲁⲛⲉϥ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲉⲕϯⲙⲁϯ ⲉ̀Ⲥⲓⲱⲛ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛⲓⲥⲟⲃⲧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ Ⲓⲉⲣⲟⲩⲥⲁⲗⲏⲙ ⲙⲁⲣⲟⲩⲕⲟⲧⲟⲩ: ⲧⲟⲧⲉ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ϯⲙⲁϯ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛϣⲟⲩϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲉⲑⲙⲏⲓ: ⲟⲩⲁⲛⲁⲫⲟⲣⲁ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲁⲛϭⲗⲓⲗ: ⲧⲟⲧⲉ ⲉⲩⲉ̀ⲓ̀ⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ϩⲁⲛⲙⲁⲥⲓ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ⲱϣⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲉⲕⲙⲁⲛ̀ⲉⲣϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Do good, O Lord, in Your good pleasure to Zion; and let the walls of Jerusalem be built. Then You shall be pleased with sacrifices of righteousness, offering, and burnt sacrifices: then they shall offer calves upon Your altar. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أنْعِمْ ياربُّ بِمَسرتِكَ عَلى صِهْيَونَ ولْتُبنَ أسْوَارُ أورُشَلِيمَ. حِينَئذٍ تُسرُّ بذَبائِحِ العدلِ، قرباناً ومُحْرقَاتٍ. حينَئذٍ يُقرِّبونَ عَلى مَذابِحِكَ العُجُولَ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>     
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Role id="Introduction">
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The blessed prayer of the veil, we offer to Christ our King and our God, beseeching Him to forgive us our sins.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            تسبحةُ السِتارِ أقدِّمُها للمسيحِ ملِكي وإلهي وأرجوهُ أنْ يغفِرَ لي خطايايَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Role>
         
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         From the Psalms of our teacher David the prophet.  May his blessings be upon us all. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         مِنْ مزاميرِ مُعلِّمِنا داودَ النبي بركاتِهِ علينا. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>    
<ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         The following psalms are reserved to be prayed by the priest:
         <ns0:ul>
            <ns0:li>Psalm 4</ns0:li>
            <ns0:li>Psalm 118 (20)</ns0:li>
            <ns0:li>Psalm 118 (21)</ns0:li>
            <ns0:li>Psalm 118 (22)</ns0:li>
         </ns0:ul>
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
   
   <ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         The following Psalms from the First Hour are prayed:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 4 - When I cried out...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الرابع - إذ دعوتُ استجبتَ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            When I cried out, God of my righteousness heard me: in tribulation You have made room for me; have compassion upon me, O Lord, and hear my prayer.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            إذ دعوتُ استجبْتَ لي يا إلهَ برِّي. في الشدِّةِ فرَّجتَ عنِّي. تراءفْ عليَّ ياربُّ واسمعْ صلاتي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O you, sons of men, how long will your hearts be heavy? Why do you love vanity, and seek falsehood? Know you that the Lord has made His Holy One wondrous. The Lord hears me when I cry to Him. Be angry, and do not sin; feel sorrow upon your beds for what you say in your hearts. Offer the sacrifice of righteousness, and trust in the Lord.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يا بني البشرِ، حتَّى متى تثقلُ قلوبُكُم؟ لماذا تحبُّونَ الباطلَ وتبتغونَ الكذِبَ؟ اعلموا أنَّ الربَّ قد جعلَ صفيَّهُ عجَباً. الربُّ يستجيبُ لي إذا ما صرختُ إليهِ. اغضَبوا ولا تخطئوا، الذي تقولونُهُ في قلوبِكُم اندَموا عليهِ في مضاجِعِكُم. اذبحوا ذبيحةَ البرِّ، وتوَّكلوا على الربِّ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Many say, “Who can show us the good things?” The light of Your countenance, O Lord, has been shined upon us. You have given gladness to my heart; they have been multiplied with the fruit of their wheat and wine and oil. I shall both lie down in peace and sleep, for You alone, O Lord, have caused me to dwell in hope. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            كثيرونَ يقولونَ: مَنْ يُرينا الخيراتِ؟ قد أضاءَ علَينا نورُ وجهِكَ ياربُّ. أعطيتَ سروراً لقلبي أوفرَ مِنَ الذين كثُرتْ حنطتُهم وخمرُهم وزيتُهم. فبالسلامةِ أضطجعُ أيضاً وأنامُ، لأنَّكَ أنتَ وحدَكَ ياربُّ أسكنتَني على الرجاءِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 6 - O Lord, do not rebuke me...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور السادس - يا ربّ لا تُبكّتني...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord, do not rebuke me in Your anger, nor chasten me in Your wrath. Have mercy on me, O Lord, for I am weak; heal me, O Lord, for my bones are troubled, and my soul is grievously troubled. But You, O Lord, how long? Return, deliver my soul; revive me for the sake of Your mercy. For in death there is no one who is remembering You; and in Hades who is able to give thanks to You? I became wearied in my groaning; I shall wash my bed every night; I shall wet my couch with my tears. My eye is troubled because of anger; I have grown old because of all my enemies.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ياربُّ لا تُبكِّتْني بغضبِكَ، ولا تؤدِّبْني بسخطِكَ. ارحَمْني ياربُّ فإنِّي ضعيفٌ، اشفِني ياربُّ فإنَّ عظامي قد اضطربَتْ ونفسي قد انزعجَتْ جداً. وأنتَ ياربُّ فإلى متى؟ عُدْ ونجِّ نفسي، وأحيني مِنْ أجلِ رحمتِكَ. لأنَّه ليسَ في الموتِ مَنْ يذكرُكَ ولا في الجحيمِ مَنْ يعترفُ لكَ. تعبتُ في تنهُّدي. أعوِّمُ كلَّ ليلةٍ سَريري، وبدموعي أبِلُّ فِراشي. تعكَّرتْ مِنَ الغضبِ عينايَ. شاخَتْ مِنْ سائرِ أعدائي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Depart away from me, all who do iniquity, for the Lord has heard the voice of my weeping. The Lord has heard my petition; the Lord has accepted my prayer. All my enemies shall be put to shame and greatly troubled; they shall be turned back and put to shame speedily. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ابعدوا عنِّي يا جميعَ فاعلي الإثمِ. لأنَّ الربَّ قد سمعَ صوتَ بُكائي. الربُّ سمعَ تضرُّعي، الربُّ لصلاتي قبِلَ، فليخزَ وليضطرِبْ جداً جميعُ أعدائي، وليرتدُّوا إلى ورائهِم بالخزي سريعاً جِداً. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 12 -  How long, O Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الثاني عشر - إلى متى يا ربّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            How long, O Lord, do You forget me, for ever? How long do You turn Your face away from me? How long do I put these counsels in my soul, and these sorrows in my heart for the whole day? How long does my enemy exalt over me?
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            إلى متى ياربُّ تنساني؟ إلى الانقضاءِ؟ حتَّى متى تصرفُ وجهكَ عنِّي؟ إلى متى أردِّدُ هذهِ المشوراتِ في نفسي، وهذهِ الأوجاعَ في قلبي النهارَ كلَّهُ؟ إلى متى يرتفعُ عدوي عليَّ؟
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Look, hearken to me, O Lord my God: enlighten my eyes, lest I sleep in death; lest my enemy say, “I have prevailed against him;” those who distress me will rejoice if ever I stumble. But I have hoped in Your mercy; my heart will rejoice in Your salvation. I will praise the Lord who has done good to me, and I will sing to the name of the Lord Most High. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            انظرْ واستجِبْ لي يا ربِّي وإلهي. أنِرْ عينيَّ لئلا أنامُ نومَ الموتِ، لئلا يقولُ عدوِّي: إنِّي قد قويتُ علَيهِ. الذين يُحزنونَني يتهلَّلونَ إن أنا زللتُ. أمَّا أنا فعلى رحمتِكَ توَّكلتُ. يبتهجُ قلبي بخلاصِكَ. أسبِّحُ الربَّ المُحسنَ إليَّ، وأرتلُ لاسمِ الربِّ العليِّ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 15 - Keep me, O Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الخامس عشر - إحفظني يا ربّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Keep me, O Lord, for I have hoped in You. I said to the Lord, “You are my Lord, and You have no need of my goodness.” He has manifested His wonders to His saints who are in His earth, and He has wrought all His desires in them. Their ailments have been multiplied who hastened after another god. I will not assemble their meetings of blood, nor make mention of their names with my lips. The Lord is the portion of my inheritance and my cup. You are He who brings my inheritance back to me. The measuring lines have fallen to me among the best, and my inheritance is confirmed for me.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            إحفظْني ياربُّ فإنِّي عليكَ توَّكلتُ. قلتُ للربِّ: أنتَ ربِّي، ولا تحتاجُ إلى صلاحي. أظهرَ عجائبَهُ لقديسيهِ الذين في أرضِهِ، وصنعَ فيهِم كلَّ مشيئاتِهِ. كثُرَتْ أمراضُهُم الذين أسرعوا وراءَ آخرٍ. لا أجمعُ مجامِعَهُم مِنَ الدماءِ، ولا أذكرُ أسماءَهُم بشفتيَّ. الربُّ هو نصيبُ مِيراثي وكأسي. أنتَ الذي تردُّ إليَّ مِيراثي. حبالُ المساحةِ وقعتْ لي في أرضٍ خصبةٍ، وإنَّ ميراثي لثابتٌ لي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            I will bless the Lord who has given me understanding; my reins too have instructed me even till the night. I foresaw the Lord always before me; He is on my right hand, that I should not be moved. Therefore my heart rejoiced and my tongue exulted; moreover also my flesh shall live in hope: because You shall not leave my soul in Hades, neither shall You suffer Your holy One to see corruption. You have made known to me the ways of life; You will fill me with joy with Your face; delight is in Your right hand forever.  ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أبارِكُ الربَّ الذي أفهمَني. وأيضاً إلى الليل تُنذِرُني كليتايَ. تقدمتُ فرأيتُ الربَّ أمامي في كلِّ حينٍ، لأنَّهُ عَن يميني لكي لا أتزعزعَ. مِنْ أجلِ هذا فرِحَ قلبي وتهلَّلَ لساني. وأيضاً جسدي يسكنُ على الرجاءِ. لأنَّكَ لا تتركُ نفسي في الجحيمِ. ولا تدَعُ قدوسَّكَ يرى فساداً. قد عرَّفتَني سُبُلَ الحياةِ. تملأُني فرحاً مع وجهِكَ. البهجةُ في يمينِكَ إلى الانقضاءِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 24 - To You, O Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الرابع والعشرون - إليكَ يا ربّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            To You, O Lord, I have lifted up my soul. O my God, I have trusted in You; let me not be ashamed forever, nor let my enemies mock me. For all who wait for You shall not be ashamed; let them be ashamed who wrought iniquity in vain. Show me Your ways, O Lord, and teach me Your paths. Lead me to Your truth, and teach me; for You are God my Savior; and for You I have waited the whole day. Remember, O Lord, Your compassions and Your mercies, for they exist from everlasting. The sins of my youth and those of my ignorance do not remember; and according to Your mercy remember me, for the sake of Your goodness, O Lord.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            إليكَ ياربُّ رفعتُ نفسي، يا إلهي عليكَ توَّكلتُ. فلا تُخزِني إلى الأبدِ، ولا تشْمتْ بي أعدائي. لأنَّ جميعَ الذين ينتظرونَكَ لا يُخزَونَ. ليُخزَ الذين يصنعون الإثمَ باطِلاً. أظهِرْ لي ياربُّ طُرقَكَ، وعلِّمْني سُبُلَكَ. اهدِني إلى عدلِكَ وعلِّمْني. لأنَّكَ أنتَ هو اللهُ مُخلِّصي، وإياكَ انتظرتُ النهارَ كلَّهُ. اذكُرْ ياربُّ رأفاتِكَ ومراحِمَكَ، لأنَّها ثابتةٌ مُنذُ الأزلِ. خطايا شبابي وجهالاتي لا تذكُرْ. كرحمَتِكَ اذكُرْني أنتَ مِنْ أجلِ صلاحِكَ ياربُّ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            For good and upright is the Lord; therefore He shall set a law for those who sin in the way. He shall guide the meek in judgment. He shall teach the meek His ways. All the ways of the Lord are mercy and truth to those who keep His covenant and His testimonies. For the sake of Your name, O Lord, You shall forgive my sin, for it is great.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الربُّ صالِحٌ ومُستقيمٌ، لذلِكَ يُرشِدُ الذين يُخطئونَ في الطريقِ. يَهدي الودعاءَ في الحُكمِ، يُعلِّمُ الودعاءَ طُرُقَهُ. جميعُ طُرُقِ الربِّ رحمةٌ وحقٌ لحافِظي عهدِهِ وشهاداتِهِ. مِنْ أجلِ اسمِكَ ياربُّ اغفِرْ لي خَطيئَتِي لأنَّها كثيرةٌ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Who is the man that fears the Lord? He shall set a law for him in the way which pleases Him. His soul shall dwell in good things, and his seed shall inherit the earth. The Lord is the strength of those who fear Him, and the name of the Lord is for those who revere Him, and His covenant He will manifest to them. My eyes are ever looking towards the Lord, for He will draw my feet out of the snare.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            مَنْ هو الإنسانُ الخائفُ الربَّ، يُرشِدُهُ في الطريقِ التي ارتضاها. نفسُهُ في الخيراتِ تثبتُ، ونسلُهُ يرثُ الأرضَ. الربُّ عِزٌّ لخائفيهِ، واسمُ الربِّ لأتقيائِهِ. ولهُم يُعلنُ عهدَهُ. عينايَ تنظُرانِ إلى الربِّ في كلِّ حينٍ، لأنَّهُ يجتذِبُ مِنَ الفخِّ رِجلِي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Look upon me, and have mercy on me, for I am an only child and poor. The afflictions of my heart have been multiplied; bring me out of my troubles. Behold my lowliness and my toil, and forgive all my sins. Look upon my enemies, for they have multiplied, and they have hated me with an unjust hatred. Keep my soul, and deliver me. Let me not be put to shame, for I have hoped in You. The harmless and upright joined themselves to me, for I waited for You, O Lord. Deliver Israel, O God, out of all his afflictions. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            انظُرْ إليَّ وارحَمْني، لأنِّي ابنٌ وحيدٌ وفقيرٌ أنا. أحزانُ قلبي قد كثُرَتْ، أخرِجْني مِنْ شَدائدي. انظُرْ إلى ذُلِّي وتعبي. واغفِرْ لي جميعَ خطايايَ. انظُرْ إلى أعدائي فإنَّهُم قد كثُروا وأبغضوني ظُلْماً. احفظْ نَفسي ونجِّني، لا أُخزى لأنِّي عليكَ توَّكلتُ. الذين لا شرَّ فيهِم والمستقيمونَ لصقوا بي، لأنِّي انتظرتُكَ ياربُّ. يا اللهُ أنقِذْ إسرائيلَ مِنْ جميعِ شدائدِهِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 26 - The Lord is my light...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور السادس والعشرون - الربّ نوري...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord is my light and my salvation; whom will I fear? The Lord is the defender of my life; of whom will I be afraid? When the wicked drew near against me to eat up my flesh, those who distress me and my enemies, they fainted and fell. Though an army should fight me, my heart shall not be afraid; though war should rise up against me, in this I am confident.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الربُّ نوري وخلاصي مِمَنْ أخافُ؟! الربُّ حِصنُ حياتي مِمَنْ أجزعُ؟! عِندما يقترِبُ الأشرارُ مني ليأكلوا لَحمي، مُضايقيَّ وَأعدائي عثَروا وسقَطوا. إن يُحاربْني جيشٌ فلَن يخافَ قلبي. وإن قامَ عليَّ قتالٌ ففي هذا أنا أطمئنُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         One thing I have asked of the Lord, this also I will seek, that I should dwell in the house of the Lord all the days of my life, that I should behold the fair beauty of the Lord, and visit His holy temple. For in the day of my afflictions He hid me in His tabernacle; He sheltered me in the secret of His tabernacle; He set me up on a rock. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         واحدةً سألتُ مِنَ الربِّ وإيَّاها ألتمسُ. أن أسكنَ في بيتِ الربِّ كلَّ أيامِ حياتي. لكي أنظرَ نعيمَ الربِّ، وأتفرسَ في هيكلِهِ المُقدسِ. لأنَّه أخفاني في خيمتِهِ. في يومِ شِدَّتي، ستَرَني بسِترِ مظلَّتِهِ. وعلى صخرةٍ رفعَني.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            And now, behold, He has lifted up my head over my enemies; I went round and offered in His tabernacle a sacrifice of joy; I shall sing, and sing psalms to the Lord.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            والآنَ هوذا قد رفعَ رأسي على أعدائي. طُفتُ وذَبحتُ في مظلَّتِهِ ذبيحةَ التهليلِ، أسبِّحُ وأرتِّلُ للربِّ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Hear, O Lord, my voice which I have uttered aloud; have mercy on me, and hearken to me. For You are He to whom my heart said, “I have sought Your face; Your face, O Lord, I will seek.” Do not turn away Your face from me, do not reject Your servant in anger. Be a helper to me, and do not forsake me; and do not overlook me, O God my Savior. For my father and my mother have forsaken me, but the Lord has accepted me unto Himself. Set a law for me, O Lord, in Your ways, and guide me in a right path, because of my enemies. Do not deliver me over to the hands of those who afflict me; for unjust witnesses have risen up against me, and injustice has lied to itself. I believe that I shall see the goodness of the Lord in the land of the living. Wait for the Lord; be of good cheer and let your heart be strengthened, and wait for the Lord. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            استمِعْ يا ربُّ صوتي الذي بِهِ دعوتُكَ. ارحَمْني واستجِبْ لي فإنَّهُ لكَ قالَ قلبي: طلبتُ وجهَكَ، ووجهَكَ يا ربُّ ألتمِسُ. لا تحجُبْ وجهَكَ عنِّي، ولا تنبُذْ بغضبٍ عبدكَ. كُنْ لي مُعيناً، لا تخذِلْني ولا ترفُضْني يا اللهُ مُخلِّصي. فإنَّ أبي وأمِّي قد ترَكاني، وأمَّا الربُّ فقبِلَني. علِّمْني ياربُّ طريقَكَ، واهدِني في سبيلٍ مُستقيمٍ مِنْ أجلِ أعدائي. لا تُسلِّمْني إلى أيدي مُضايقيَّ، لأنَّهُ قد قامَ عليَّ شهودُ زورٍ، وكذِبوا عليَّ ظُلماً. وأنا أؤمِنُ أني أعاينُ خيراتِ الربِّ في أرضِ الأحياءِ. انتظرْ الربَّ، تقوَّ وليتشدَدْ قلبُكَ وانتظرْ الربَّ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 66 - God shall pity us...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور السادس والستون - ليتراءفْ اللهُ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            God shall pity us, and bless us, and reveal His face upon us and have mercy on us; that Your way may be known on the earth, Your salvation among all nations. Let the peoples, O God, give praise to You; let all the peoples give praise to You. Let the nations rejoice and exult, for You will judge peoples in equity, and guide nations on the earth. Let the peoples, O God, give praise to You; let all the peoples give praise to You. The earth has yielded its fruit. God, our God, shall bless us; God shall bless us, and all the ends of the earth shall fear Him. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ليتراءفْ اللهُ علَينا ويبارِكْنا، وليُظهِرْ وجهَهُ علينا ويرحمْنا. لتُعرَفْ في الأرضِ طريقُكَ، وفي جميعِ الأممِ خلاصُكَ. فلتعترفْ لكَ الشعوبُ يا اللهُ، فلتعترفْ لكَ الشعوبُ كلُّها. لتفرحْ الأممُ وتبتهجُ، لأنَّكَ تحكُمُ في الشعوبِ بالاستقامةِ، وتهدي الأممَ في الأرضِ. فلتعترفْ لكَ الشعوبُ يا اللهُ، فلتعترفْ لكَ الشعوبُ جميعاً. الأرضُ أعطتْ ثمرتَها، فليبارِكْنا اللهُ إلهُنا. ليبارِكْنا اللهُ، فلتَخشَهُ جميعُ أقطارِ الأرضِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 69 - O God, be mindful...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور التاسع والستون - اللهُمّ التفِتْ إلى معونَتي...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O God, be mindful to my help; make haste, O Lord, to help me. Let them be ashamed and be scorned, those who seek my soul; let them be turned backward and put to shame, those who wish to do evil unto me. Let those who say to me, “Aha, aha,” be turned back in shame immediately. Let all who seek You exult and be glad in You, and let those who love Your salvation say continually, “Let the Lord be magnified.” But I am poor and weak, O God, help me. You are my Helper and Savior, O Lord, do not delay. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اللهُمَّ التفِتْ إلى معونَتي، ياربُّ أسرعْ وأعِنِّي. ليُخزَ ويخجلْ طالِبو نفسي، وليرتدّْ إلى خلفٍ ويخجلْ الذين يبتغونَ ليَ الشرَّ. وليرجعْ بالخزي سريعاً القائلونَ لي: نَعِمَّاً نَعِمَّاً. وليبتهِجْ ويفرحْ بكَ جميعُ الذين يلتمِسونَكَ، وليقُلْ في كلِّ حينٍ مُحِبُّو خلاصِكَ: فليتعظمْ الربُّ. وأمَّا أنا فمسكينٌ وفقيرٌ، اللهُمَّ أعِنِّي. أنتَ مُعيني ومُخلِّصي ياربُّ فلا تُبطئْ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         The following Psalms from the Third Hour are prayed:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 22 - The Lord is He who shepherds me...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الثاني والعشرون - الربُّ يرعاني...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord is He who shepherds me; I shall need nothing. In a place of green pasture, there He has made me dwell; by the water of rest, He has tended me. He has restored my soul; He has guided me into the paths of righteousness, for His name’s sake. Even if I walk in the midst of the shadow of death, I shall not fear evil things, for You are with me; Your rod and Your staff, these comfort me. You have prepared a table before me in the presence of those who afflict me. You have anointed my head with oil, and Your cup makes me drunk like power. Your mercy shall follow me all the days of my life, and my dwelling shall be in the house of the Lord unto length of days. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الربُّ يرعاني فلا يُعوزُني شيءٌ. في مراعٍ خُضرٍ يُسكنُني، إلى ماءِ الراحةِ يُوردُني. يردُّ نفسي. يهديني إلى سُبلِ البرِّ مِنْ أجلِ اسمِهِ. إن سلكتُ في وسطِ ظِلالِ الموتِ فلا أخافُ شرّاً، لأنَّكَ أنتَ معي. عصاكَ وعكازُكَ هُما يُعزّيانَني. هيّأتَ قدّامي مائدةً تُجاهَ مُضايقيَّ. مسحتَ بالزيتِ رأسي، وكأسُكَ روتْني بقوةٍ. ورحمتُكَ تُدركُني جميعَ أيامِ حياتي، ومسكني في بيتِ الربِّ إلى مدى الأيامِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 29 - I will exalt You...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور التاسع والعشرون - أعظمُكَ ياربُّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            I will exalt You, O Lord, for You have accepted me, and not caused my enemies to rejoice over me. O Lord, my God, I cried to You, and You have healed me. O Lord, You have brought up my soul from Hades, You have delivered me from those who will go down to the pit.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أعظِّمُكَ ياربُّ لأنكَ احتضنتَني، ولم تُشمِتْ بي أعدائي. أيُها الربُّ إلهي، صرختُ إليكَ فشفَيتَني. ياربُّ أصعدتَ مِنَ الجحيمِ نفسي، وخلّصتَني مِنَ الهابطينَ في الجُبِّ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Sing to the Lord, all you His saints, and confess the remembrance of His holiness. For anger is in His wrath, but life in His favor; weeping shall be for the evening, but joy shall be in the morning.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            رتّلوا للربِّ يا جميعَ قديسيهِ، واعترفوا لذكرِ قُدسِهِ. لأنَّ سَخَطاً في غضبِهِ، وحياةً في رضاهُ. في العشاءِ يحلُّ البكاءُ، وفي الصباحِ السرورُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            I said in my prosperity, I shall never be moved. O Lord, in Your will You gave strength to my beauty, but You turned away Your face from me, and I became troubled. To You, O Lord, I shall cry, and to my God I shall make supplication. What profit is there in my blood, when I go down to destruction? Shall the dust confess to You? Or shall it declare Your truth?
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أنا قلتُ في نعيمي لا أتزعزعُ إلى الدهرِ، ياربُّ بمسرَّتِكَ أعطيتَ جَمالي قوةً. صرفتَ وجهَكَ عنّي، فصِرتُ قلِقاً. إليكَ ياربُّ أصرخُ، وإلى إلهي أتضرَّعُ. أيّةُ منفعةٍ مِنْ دمي إذا هبَطتُ إلى الجحيمِ؟ هل يعترفُ لكَ الترابُ أو يُخبرُ بحقِّكَ؟
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord heard, and had mercy upon me; the Lord became to me a helper. You have turned my mourning into joy for me; You have rent off my sackcloth, and girded me with gladness, that my glory may sing praise to You, and I shall not be troubled at heart. O Lord, my God, I will confess to You forever. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            سمعَ الربُّ فرحمَني، الربُّ صارَ لي عوناً. حوّلتَ نَوحي إلى فرحٍ لي، مزّقتَ مِسْحي ومنطقتَني سُروراً. لكي تُرتِلَ لكَ نفسي ولا يحزنَ قلبي. أيُها الربُّ إلهي إلى الأبدِ أعترفُ لكَ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 42 - Judge me, O Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الثاني والأربعون - احكُمْ لي ياربُّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Judge me, O Lord, and avenge my case, against an impure nation; You shall deliver me from the unjust and crafty man. For You are my God and my strength; why have You cast me off? And why do I walk gloomingly, while the enemy oppresses me? Send forth Your light and Your truth; they have led me, and brought me to Your holy mountain, and to Your dwelling. And I will go into the altar of God, before the face of God who gladdens my youth; I will give praise to You with the harp, O God, my God.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            احكُمْ لي ياربُّ وانتقمْ لمَظلمَتي، مِنْ أمّةٍ غيرِ بارّةٍ. ومِنْ إنسانٍ ظالمٍ وغاشٍ نجِّني، لأنكَ أنتَ هو إلهي وقوَّتي. لماذا أقصيتَني؟ ولماذا أسلكُ كئيباً مِنْ مُضايقةِ عدُوّي؟ أرسلْ نورَكَ وحقَّكَ، فإنهُما يَهديانَني ويُصعدانَني إلى جبلِكَ المقدّسِ وإلى مسكنِكَ. فأدخلُ إلى مذبحِ اللهِ، تُجاهَ وجهِ اللهِ الذي يُفرّحُ شبابي. أعترفُ لكَ بالقيثارةِ يا اللهُ إلهي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Why are you sad, O my soul? And why do you trouble me? Hope in God, for I will give thanks to Him. The salvation of my face is my God. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لماذا أنتِ حزينةٌ يا نفسي، ولماذا تُزعجينَني؟ توكّلي على اللهِ فإني أعترِفُ لهُ، خلاصُ وجهي هو إلهي. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         The following Psalms from the Sixth Hour are prayed:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
         
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 56 - Have mercy upon me...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور السادس والخمسون - ارحمْني يا اللهُ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Have mercy upon me, O God, have mercy upon me; for my soul has trusted in You, and in the shadow of Your wings I will hope, until the iniquity passes away. I will cry to God Most High; God who has benefitted me. He sent from heaven and saved me; He gave over to reproach those who trampled on me. God has sent forth His mercy and His truth, and He has delivered my soul from the midst of young lions; I laid down to sleep, while troubled. As for the sons of men, their teeth are weapons and arrows, and their tongue a sharp sword.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ارحمْني يا اللهُ ارحمْني، فإنَّهُ عليكَ توكلَتْ نفسي. وبظلِّ جناحَيكَ أعتصِمُ، إلى أن يعبرَ الإثمُ. أصرخُ إلى اللهِ العليِّ، الإلهِ المُحسنِ إليَّ. أرسلَ مِنَ السماءِ فخلَّصَني، وجعلَ العارَ على الذينَ يطأونَني. أرسلَ اللهُ رحمتَهُ وحقَّهُ، وخلَّصَ نفسي مِنْ بينِ الأشبالِ إذ نمتُ مُضطرباً. أسنانُ أبناءِ البشرِ سلاحٌ وسهامٌ، ولسانُهُم سيفٌ مرهفٌ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Be You exalted, O God, above the heavens, and Your glory above all the earth. They have prepared snares for my feet, and have bowed down my soul; they have dug a pit before me, and fallen into it.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اللهُمَّ ارتفعْ على السماواتِ، وليرتفعْ مجدُكَ على سائرِ الأرضِ. نصبوا لرجليَّ فِخاخاً وأحنوا نفسي، حفروا قُدامَ وجهي حُفرةً فسقطوا فيها.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            My heart, O God, is ready, my heart is ready; I will sing, and chant in my glory. Arise, my glory; arise, psaltery and harp; I will rise early. O Lord, I will give thanks to You among the peoples; I will sing to You among the nations. For Your mercy has been magnified up to the heavens, and Your truth up to the clouds. Be You exalted, O God, above the heavens, and Your glory above all the earth. ALLELUIA
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            مُستعِدٌ قلبي يا اللهُ، مُستعِدٌ قلبي، أسبِّحُ وأرتِّلُ في تمجيدي. استيقظْ يا مجدي، استيقظْ أيها المِزمارُ والقيثارةُ. أنا أستيقظُ مُبكراً. أعترفُ لكَ في الشعوبِ ياربُّ، وأرتِّلُ لكَ في الأممِ. لأنَّ رحمتَكَ قد عظُمَتْ إلى السماواتِ، وإلى السحابِ عدلُكَ. اللهُمَّ ارتفعْ على السماواتِ، وليرتفعْ مجدُكَ على سائرِ الأرضِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 85 - Incline Your ear...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الخامس والثمانون - أمِلْ ياربُّ أذنَكَ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Incline Your ear, O Lord, and hear me, for I am poor and weak. Preserve my soul, for I am pure; save Your servant, O my God, who hopes in You. Have mercy on me, O Lord, for to You I will cry the whole day. Rejoice the soul of Your servant, for to You, O Lord, I have lifted up my soul. For You, O Lord, are righteous, and gentle, and plenteous is Your mercy to all who call upon You. Give ear to my prayer, O Lord, and attend to the voice of my supplication. In the day of my trouble I cried to You, for You heard me.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أمِلْ ياربُّ أذنَكَ واستمَعْني، لأنِّي مِسكينٌ وبائسٌ أنا. احفظْ نفسي لأنِّي بارٌ، يا إلهي خلِّصْ عبدَكَ المُتكِّلَ عليكَ. ارحمْني ياربُّ، لأنِّي إليكَ أصرخُ اليومَ كلَّهُ. فرِّحْ نفسَ عبدِكَ، لأنِّي إليكَ ياربُّ رفعتُ نفسي. لأنَّكَ أنتَ ياربُّ صالحٌ ووديعٌ، ورحمتُكَ كثيرةٌ لكافةِ المستغيثينَ بكَ. أنصِتْ ياربُّ إلى صلاتي، واصغَ إلى صوتِ تضرُّعي. في يومِ شدَّتي إليكَ صرختُ فأجبتَني.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            There is none like You, O Lord, among the gods, and there is none that is able to do Your works. All nations whom You have made shall come, and shall worship before You, O Lord, and shall glorify Your name. For You are great, and do wonders; You alone are the great God.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            فليسَ لكَ شبيهٌ في الآلهةِ ياربُّ، ولا مَنْ يصنعُ كأعمالِكَ. كلُّ الأممِ الذينَ خلقتَهُم يأتونَ ويسجدونَ أمامَكَ ياربُّ، ويُمجدونَ اسمَكَ. لأنَّكَ أنتَ عظيمٌ وصانعُ العجائبَ، أنتَ وحدَكَ الإلهُ العظيمُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Guide me, O Lord, in Your way, and I shall walk in Your truth; let my heart rejoice, that I may fear Your name. I will give thanks to You, O Lord my God, with all my heart, and I will glorify Your name forever. For Your mercy is great toward me, and You have delivered my soul from the lowest Hades.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اهدِني ياربُّ إلى طريقِكَ فأسلكُ في حقِكَ، ليفرحْ قلبي عِندَ خوفِهِ مِنْ اسمِكَ. أعترفُ لكَ أيها الربُّ إلهي مِنْ كلِّ قلبي، وأمجِّدُ اسمَكَ إلى الأبدِ. لأنَّ رحمتَكَ عظيمةٌ عليَّ، وقد نجَّيتَ نفسي مِنَ الجحيمِ السُفلي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O God, transgressors have risen up against me, and an assembly of violent men have sought my soul, and have not, at first, set You before them. But You, O Lord God, are compassionate and merciful, longsuffering, and abundant in mercy and truth. Look down upon me, and have mercy on me; give strength to Your servant, and save the son of Your handmaid. Establish with me a sign for good, and let those who hate me see and be ashamed, because You, O Lord, have helped me, and comforted me. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اللهُمَّ إنَّ مُخالفي الناموسِ قد قاموا عليَّ ومجمعَ الأعزاءِ طلبوا نفسي، ولم يسبقوا أن يجعلوكَ أمامَهُم. وأنتَ أيها الربُّ الإلهُ أنتَ رؤوفٌ ورحيمٌ. أنتَ طويلُ الروحِ، وكثيرُ الرحمةِ وصادقٌ. انظرْ إليَّ وارحمْني. أعطِ عزةً لعبدِكَ، وخلِّصْ ابنَ أمتِكَ. اصنعْ معي آيةً صالحةً، ليرى ذلكَ مُبغضيَّ فيَخزوا. لأنَّكَ أنتَ ياربُّ أعنتَني وعزَّيتَني. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 90 - He who dwells...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور التسعون - الساكِنُ في...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            He who dwells in the help of the Most High, shall rest under the shelter of the God of heaven. He shall say to the Lord, “You are my defender and my refuge, my God; I will hope in Him.” For He shall deliver you from the snare of the hunter, and from a troublesome matter. He shall overshadow you in the midst of His shoulders, and you shall hope under His wings; His truth shall encompass you as a shield. You shall not be afraid of the terror of the night, nor of an arrow flying in the day, nor of a matter walking in darkness, nor of calamity and demon of noon-day. A thousand shall fall at your left hand, and ten thousand at your right hand, but they shall not be able to come near you. Only with your eyes shall you observe, and see the reward of sinners. For You, O Lord, are my hope. You have made the Most High your refuge. No evil things shall come upon you, and no plague shall draw near to your dwelling. For He shall give his angels charge concerning you, to keep you in all your ways. They shall bear you up on their hands, lest you stumble Your foot against a stone. You shall tread on the serpent and basilisk, and You shall trample on the lion and dragon. For he has hoped in Me, and I shall deliver him; I shall protect him, because he has known My name. He shall beseech Me, and I shall hear him; I am with him in affliction, and I shall deliver him, and glorify him. I shall satisfy him with length of days, and show him My salvation. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الساكِنُ في عونِ العَليِّ، يستريحُ في ظلِّ إلهِ السماءِ. يقولُ للربِّ أنتَ هو ناصري وملجأي، إلهي فأتّكِلُ عليهِ. لأنَّهُ يُنجِّيكَ مِنْ فخِّ الصيادِ، ومِنْ كلمةٍ مُقلقةٍ. في وَسَطِ مَنكِبَيهِ يُظللُكَ، وتحتَ جناحَيهِ تعتصِمُ، عدلُهُ يُحيطُ بِكَ كالسلاحِ. فلا تخشى مِنْ خوفِ الليلِ، ولا مِنْ سهمٍ يطيرُ في النهارِ. ولا مِنْ أمرٍ يسلُكُ في الظُلمةِ، ولا مِنْ سقطةٍ وشيطانِ الظهيرةِ. يسقطُ عن يسارِكَ ألوفٌ، وعن يمينِكَ رِبواتٌ، وأما أنتَ فلا يقتربونَ إليكَ. بل بعينيكَ تتأملُ، ومجازاةَ الخطاةِ تُبصِرُ. لأنَّكَ أنتَ ياربُّ رجائي. جعلتَ العليَّ ملجأكَ. فلا تُصيبُكَ الشرورُ، ولا تدنو ضربةٌ مِنْ مسكنِكَ. لأنَّهُ يوصِي ملائكتَهُ بِكَ، ليحفظوكَ في سائرِ طرقِكَ. وعلى أيديهِم يحمِلونَكَ، لئلا تعثُرُ بحجرٍ رجلُكَ. تطأُ الأفعى وملِكَ الحيَّاتِ، وتسحقُ الأسدَ والتنينَ. لأنَّهُ عليَّ أتكلَ فأنجّيهِ، أرَفِّعُهُ (أسترُهُ) لأنَّهُ عرَفَ اسمي. يدعوني فأستجيبُ لهُ. معَهُ أنا في الشدةِ، أنقذُهُ وأمجِّدُهُ. ومِنْ طولِ الأيامِ أشبعُهُ، وأريهِ خلاصي. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         The following Psalms from the Ninth Hour are prayed:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 96 - The Lord reigned, let the earth exult...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ السادسُ والتسعونَ - الربُّ قدْ ملَكَ فلتتهلّلِ الأرضُ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord reigned, let the earth exult, let the many islands rejoice. Clouds and darkness are round about Him; righteousness and judgment are the uprightness of His throne. Fire shall precede Him, and with a flame shall burn up His enemies who surround Him. His lightings lightened the world; the earth saw, and trembled. The mountains melted like wax before the face of the Lord, before the face of the Lord of the whole earth. The heavens have declared His righteousness, and all the peoples have seen His glory.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الربُّ قدْ ملَكَ فلتتهلَّلِ الأرضُ، ولتفرحِ الجزائرُ الكثيرةُ. سحابٌ وضبابٌ حولَهُ، العدلُ والقضاءُ قِوامُ كرسيِّهِ، النارُ تسبِقُ فتسلُكُ أمامَهُ، وبلهيبٍ تُحرِقُ أعداءَهُ الذينَ حولَهُ. أضاءتْ بروقُهُ المسكونةَ. نظرتْ الأرضُ فتزلزلتْ، ذابتِ الجِبالُ مثلَ الشمعِ مِنْ قدامِ وجهِ الربِّ، مِنْ أمامِ وجهِ ربِّ الأرضِ كلِّها. أخبرَتِ السماواتُ بعدلِهِ، وعاينَتْ جميعُ الشُعوبِ مجدَهُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Let all those who worship graven images and boast in their idols be ashamed. Worship Him all you His angels.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يَخزى جميعُ الساجدينَ لصنعةِ الأيدي، المُفتخرينَ بأصنامِهِم. اسجُدوا للهِ يا جميعَ ملائكتِهِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Zion heard and rejoiced, and the daughters of Judea exulted, because of Your judgments, O Lord. For You are the Lord most high over all the earth; You are greatly exalted above all gods.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            سمِعتْ صِهيَونُ ففرِحتْ، وتهلَّلتْ بناتُ يهوذا، مِنْ أجلِ أحكامِكَ ياربُّ. لأنَّكَ أنتَ هو الربُّ العالي على كلِّ الأرضِ، ارتفعتَ جداً فوقَ جميعِ الآلِهةِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            You who love the Lord, hate evil; the Lord preserves the souls of His saints; He will deliver them from the hands of the sinners. Light has shined for the righteous, and gladness for the upright in their heart. Rejoice in the Lord, you righteous, and praise the remembrance of His holiness. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يا مُحبِّي الربِّ أبغِضوا الشرَّ. إنَّ الربَّ يحفظُ نفوسَ أبرارِهِ، ويُنجيهِم مِنْ أيدي الخُطاةِ. نورٌ أشرقَ للصدِّيقينَ وفرحٌ للمُستقيمي القلوبِ. افرحوا أيها الصدِّيقونَ بالربِّ. واعترِفوا لذكرِ قُدسِهِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 109 - The Lord said to my Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والتاسعُ - قالَ الربُّ لربِّي...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord said to my Lord, “Sit on My right hand, until I place Your enemies under Your feet.” A rod of power, the Lord shall send out for You out of Zion, and You shall rule in the midst of Your enemies. With You is dominion in the day of Your power, in the splendor of the saints. From the womb before the morning star I have begotten You.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            قالَ الربُّ لربِّي: اجلسْ عن يميني حتَّى أضعَ أعداءَكَ تحتَ موطِئِ قدمَيكَ. عصا قوةٍ يُرسِلُ لكَ الربُّ مِنْ صِهيَونَ وتسودُ في وسَطِ أعدائِكَ. معَكَ الرياسةُ في يومِ قُوتِكَ، في بهاءِ القدِّيسينَ. مِنَ البطنِ قبلَ كَوكبِ الصُبحِ ولدتُكَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord has sworn and shall not repent: “You are the Priest forever, after the order of Melchizedek.” The Lord is at Your right hand; He shall dash kings in the day of His wrath. He shall judge among the nations. He shall fill them with dead bodies; He shall crush the heads of many on the earth. He shall drink of the brook in the way; therefore He shall lift up the head. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أقسمَ الربُّ ولن يندمَ أنَّكَ أنتَ هو الكاهِنُ إلى الأبدِ على طقسِ ملكِيصادَقَ. الربُّ عن يمينِكَ، يُحطِّمُ في يومِ رِجزِهِ مُلوكاً، يقضي بينَ الأممِ ويملأُهُم جُثثاً، يسحقُ رؤوسَ كثيرينَ على الأرضِ. وفي الطريقِ يشربُ الماءَ مِنَ الوادي. لذلكَ يرفعُ رأسَهُ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 114 -  I loved, because the Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والرابعَ عشرَ - أحببتُ أن يسمعَ الربُّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
      
      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         I loved, because the Lord will hear the voice of my supplication. Because He has inclined His ear to me, I will call upon Him in all my days. The pains of death grasped me; the dangers of Hades have found me; I found affliction and sorrow. Then I called on the name of the Lord, “O Lord, deliver my soul.”
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أحببتُ أن يسمعَ الربُّ صوتَ تضرُّعي. لأنَّهُ أمالَ أذنَهُ إليَّ فأدعوهُ كلَّ أيامي. لأنَّ أوجاعَ الموتِ اكتنفَتْني وشدائِدَ الجحيمِ أصابتني. ضِيقاً وحُزناً وجدتُ، وباسمِ الربِّ دعوتُ: ياربُّ نجِّ نفسي.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         The Lord is merciful and righteous, and our God has mercy. The Lord preserves the infants; I was brought low, and He saved me.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         الربُّ رحيمٌ وصدّيقٌ وإلهُنا يرحمُ. الذي يحفظُ الأطفالَ هو الربُّ. اتضعتُ فخلَّصَني.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
         
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Return to your resting place, O my soul, for the Lord has dealt bountifully with you. He has delivered my soul from death, my eyes from tears, and my feet from falling. I shall be pleasing before the Lord in the land of the living. ALLELUIA.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ارجِعي يا نفسي إلى موضِعِ راحتِكِ، لأنَّ الربَّ قدْ أحسنَ إليَّ، وأنقذَ نفسي مِنَ الموتِ وعينيَّ مِنَ الدُموعِ ورجليَّ مِنَ الزللِ، أُرضي الربَّ أمامَهُ في كُورةِ الأحياءِ. هَلِّلُويا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 115 - I believed, therefore, I have spoken...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والخامسَ عشرَ - آمنتُ لذلِكَ تكلَّمتُ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            I believed, therefore, I have spoken; I was exceedingly humbled. I said in my amazement, “Every man is a liar.” What shall I render to the Lord for everything which He has done unto me? I shall take the cup of salvation, and call upon the name of the Lord. I will pay my vows to the Lord, in the presence of all His people.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            آمنتُ لذلِكَ تكلَّمتُ. وأنا اتَّضعتُ جِداً. أنا قُلتُ في حَيرَتي: إنَّ كلَّ الناسِ كاذِبونَ. بماذا أُكافئُ الربَّ عن كلِّ ما أعطانِيهِ؟ كأسَ الخلاصِ آخذُ وباسمِ الربِّ أدعو. أُوفي نُذوري للربِّ قُدامَ كلِّ شعبِهِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Precious in the sight of the Lord is the death of His saints. O Lord, I am Your servant; I am Your servant, and the son of Your handmaid. You have broken my bonds; I will sacrifice to You the sacrifice of praise, and will call upon the name of the Lord. I will pay my vows to the Lord in the presence of all His people, in the courts of the Lord's house, in the midst of Jerusalem. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            كريمٌ أمامَ الربِّ موتُ قدِّيسيهِ. ياربُّ أنا عبدُكَ، أنا عبدُكَ وابنُ أمتِكَ. قطّعتَ قُيودي. فلكَ أذبحُ ذبيحةَ التسبيحِ، وباسمِ الربِّ أدعو. أُوفي للربِّ نُذوري في ديارِ بيتِ الربِّ، قُدَّامَ كلِّ شعبِهِ، في وسطِ أورُشَلِيمَ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         The following Psalms from the Eleventh Hour are prayed:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 120 - I lifted up my eyes...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والعشرونَ - رفعتُ عينيَّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            I lifted up my eyes to the mountains, from where my help shall come. My help shall come from the Lord, who made the heaven and the earth. He will not let your foot be moved, and your keeper will not slumber. Behold, He who keeps Israel shall not slumber nor sleep. The Lord shall keep you; the Lord shall cast a shelter upon your right hand. The sun shall not burn you by day, neither the moon by night. The Lord shall preserve you from every evil; the Lord shall keep your soul. The Lord shall keep your coming in and your going out, from this time and forever. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            رفعتُ عينيَّ إلى الجبالِ، مِنْ حيثُ يأتي عَوني. معونتي مِنْ عِندِ الربِّ الذي صنعَ السماءَ والأرضَ. لا يُسلِّمُ رِجلَكَ للزللِ، فما ينعسُ حافِظُكَ. هوذا لا ينعسُ ولا ينامُ حارِسُ إسرائيلَ. الربُّ يحفظُكَ. الربُّ يُظلِّلُ على يدِكَ اليُمنى، فلا تحرِقُكَ الشمسُ بالنهارِ ولا القمرُ بالليلِ. الربُّ يحفظُكَ مِنْ كلِّ سُوءٍ. الربُّ يحفظُ نفسَكَ. الربُّ يحفظُ دُخولَكَ وخُروجَكَ، مِنَ الآنَ وإلى الأبدِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 128 - Many times they have warred...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والثامنُ والعشرونَ - مِراراً كثيرةً حارَبوني...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Many times they have warred against me from my youth, let Israel now say. Many times they have warred against me from my youth, and yet they have not prevailed against me. The sinners scourged me on my back, and prolonged their iniquity. The Lord is righteous; He has broken the necks of sinners. Let all who hate Zion be put to shame and turned back. Let them be as the grass of the housetops, which withers before it is plucked up, with which the reaper does not fill his hand, nor he who gathers up sheaves, his bosom. Neither do they who pass by say, "The blessing of the Lord be upon you, we have blessed you in the name of the Lord." ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            مِراراً كثيرةً حارَبوني مُنذُ صِباي  ليقُلْ إسرائيلُ  مِراراً كثيرةً قاتَلوني مُنذُ شبابي، وإنَّهُمَ لمْ يقدِروا عليَّ. على ظهري جلدَني الخُطاةُ وأطالوا إثمَهُم. الربُّ صدِّيقٌّ هو، يقطعُ أعناقَ الخُطاةِ. فليُخزَ وليرتدّْ إلى الوراءِ كلُّ الذينَ يُبغِضونَ صِهيَونَ، وليكونوا مِثلَ عُشبِ السطوحِ الذي ييبَسُ قبلَ أن يُقطَعَ، الذي لمْ يملأ الحاصِدُ مِنهُ يدَهُ، ولا الذي يجمعُ الغُمورُ حِضنَهُ. ولمْ يقُلْ المُجتازونَ إنَّ بركةَ الربِّ علَيكُم. باركناكُم باسمِ الربِّ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         The following Psalms from the Twelfth Hour are prayed:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 129 - Out of the depths...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والتاسعُ والعشرونَ - مِنَ الأعماقِ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Out of the depths I have cried to You, O Lord. O Lord, hear my voice; let Your ears be attentive to the voice of my supplication. If You, O Lord, should mark iniquities, O Lord, who shall stand? For through You is forgiveness. For Your name's sake I have waited for You, O Lord. My soul has waited for Your law. My soul has hoped in the Lord, from the morning watch till night. From the morning watch, let Israel hope in the Lord. For with the Lord is mercy, and great is His redemption; and He shall redeem Israel from all his iniquities. ALLELUIA
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            مِنَ الأعماقِ صرختُ إليكَ يا ربُّ، يا ربُّ استمِعْ صوتي. لِتكنْ أُذُناكَ مُصغِيَتَينِ إلى صوتِ تضرُّعي. إنْ كنتَ للآثامِ راصِداً يا ربُّ، يا ربُّ مَنْ يثبُتُ لأنَّ مِنْ عِندِكَ المغفِرةَ. مِنْ أجلِ اسمِكَ صبَرْتُ لكَ يا ربُّ، صبَرَتْ نفسي لناموسِكَ. انتظرَتْ نفسي الربَّ مِنْ مَحْرَسِ الصُبحِ إلى الليلِ. مِنْ مَحْرَسِ الصُبحِ فلينتظِرْ إسرائيلُ الربَّ. لأنَّ الرحمةَ مِنْ عندِ الربِّ. عظيمٌ هو خلاصُهُ وهو يفتدي إسرائيلَ مِنْ كلِّ آثامِهِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 130 - O Lord, my heart was not exalted...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والثلاثونَ - يا ربُّ لمْ يرتفِعْ قلبي...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord, my heart was not exalted, neither have my eyes been haughtily raised; neither have I walked in great matters, nor in wonders greater than me. If I have not humbled myself, but raised my soul, as a weaned child with his mother, so is the recompense upon my soul. Let Israel hope in the Lord, from now and forever. ALLELUIA
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يا ربُّ لمْ يرتفِعْ قلبي، ولمْ تسْتعْلِ عَينايَ، ولمْ أسلُكْ في العظائمِ ولا في العجائبِ التي هي أعلى مِنِّي. فإنْ كنتُ لمْ أتضِعْ لكِنْ رفعتُ صَوتي مِثلُ الفطيمِ مِنَ اللبنِ على أمِّهِ. كذلِكَ المُجازاةُ على نفسي. فليتكِلْ إسرائيلُ على الربِّ مِنَ الآنَ وإلى الأبدِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 131 - Lord, remember David...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والحادي والثلاثونَ - اذكُرْ يا ربُّ داودَ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Lord, remember David and all his meekness; how he swore to the Lord, and vowed to the God of Jacob, saying, “I will not go into the dwelling of my house, or go up to the bed of my couch; I will not give sleep to my eyes, nor slumber to my eyelids, nor rest to my temples, until I find a place for the Lord, and a dwelling place for the God of Jacob.” Behold, we heard of it in Ephratha; we found it in the fields of the wood. Let us enter into His dwelling, and worship at the place where His feet stood.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اذكُرْ يا ربُّ داودَ وكلَّ دِعَتِهِ. كيفَ أقسَمَ للربِّ ونذرَ لإلهِ يعقوبَ: إنِّي لا أدخُلُ إلى مسكنِ بيتي، ولا أصعدُ على سريرِ فِراشي، ولا أُعطي لعَينيَّ نوماً، ولا لأجفاني نُعاساً، ولا راحةً لصِدغَيَّ، إلى أنْ أجدَ موضِعاً للربِّ ومسكناً لإلهِ يعقوبَ. ها قدْ سَمِعنا بهِ في أفراتةَ ووجدناهُ في موضِعِ الغابةِ. فلندخُلْ إلى مساكنِهِ ونسجُدْ في الموضِعِ الذي فيهِ استقرَّتْ قدَماهُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Arise, O Lord, into Your rest, You, and the ark of Your holy place. Your priests shall clothe themselves with righteousness, and Your righteous shall exult. For the sake of Your servant David, do not turn away Your face from Your anointed.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            قُمْ يا ربُّ إلى راحتِكَ أنتَ وتابوتُ موضِعِ قُدسِكَ. كهنتُكَ يلبَسونَ البِرَّ وأبرارُكَ يبتهِجونَ. مِنْ أجلِ داودَ عبدِكَ لا ترُدَّ وجهَكَ عنْ مسيحِكَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord has sworn in truth to David, and He will not turn from it, “Of the fruit of your loins I will set upon your throne. If your children keep My covenant and My testimonies which I will teach them, their children also will sit upon your throne forever.”
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            حلفَ الربُّ لداودَ حقاً ولا يخلِفُ: لأجعَلنَّ مِنْ ثمرةِ بطنِكَ على كُرسيِّكَ. إنْ حفِظَ بنوكَ عهْدي وشهاداتي التي أُعلِّمُهُم إيَّاها، فبنوهُم أيضاً يجلِسونَ إلى الأبدِ على كُرسيِّكَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            For the Lord has selected Zion, He has chosen her a dwelling for Himself. “This is My resting place forever. Here I will dwell; for I have desired it. In blessing I shall bless her hunting. Her poor I shall satisfy with bread. Her priests I shall clothe with salvation, and her saints with rejoicing shall rejoice. There I shall raise a horn to David. I have prepared a lamp for My anointed. His enemies I shall clothe with shame, and My holiness shall flourish upon Him.” ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لأنَّ الربَّ اختارَ صِهيَونَ ورضيَها مسْكناً لهُ: هذا هو موضِعُ راحتي إلى أبدِ الأبدِ، ههنا أسكُنُ لأنِّي أردتُهُ. لصيدِها أبارِكُ بركةً، لمساكينِها أُشبِعُ خُبزاً، لكهنتِها أُلبِسُ الخلاصَ وأبرارُها يبتهِجونَ ابتِهاجاً. هناكَ أُقيمُ قرناً لداودَ. هيَّأتُ سِراجاً لمسيحي. لأعدائِهِ أُلبِسُ الخِزيَ وعليهِ يُزهِرُ قُدسي. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 132 - Behold! What is so good...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والثاني والثلاثونَ - هوذا ما أحسنَ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Behold! What is so good, or what so pleasant, as for brothers dwelling together? It is as ointment upon the head, that came down upon the beard, the beard of Aaron that came down to the fringe of his clothing; as the dew of Aermon, that comes down upon the mountain of Zion, for there the Lord commanded the blessing and the life forever. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            هوذا ما أحسنَ وما أحلى أنْ يسكُنَ الإخوةُ معاً. كالطيبِ الكائنِ على الرأسِ الذي ينزِلُ على اللحيةِ، لحيةِ هارونَ النازِلةِ على جيبِ قميصِهِ. ومِثلُ ندى حَرمونَ المُنحدِرِ على جبلِ صِهيَونَ. لأنَّ هناكَ أمرَ الربُّ بالبركةِ والحياةِ إلى الأبدِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 133 - Behold, bless the Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والثالثُ والثلاثونَ - ها بارِكوا الربََّّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Behold, bless the Lord, O you the servants of the Lord, who stand in the house of the Lord, in the courts of the house of our God. In the nights lift up your hands O you saints, and bless the Lord. The Lord shall bless you out of Zion, He who made heaven and earth. ALLELUIA
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ها بارِكوا الربَّ يا عبيدَ الربِّ، القائمينَ في بيتِ الربِّ في ديارِ إلهِنا. في الليالي ارفعوا أيدَيَكُم أيها القِدِّيسونَ وبارِكوا الربَّ. يُبارِكُكُمُ الربُّ مِنْ صِهيَونَ الذي خلقَ السماءَ والأرضَ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 136 - By the rivers of Babylon...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والسادسُ والثلاثونَ - على أنهارِ بابِلَ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat and wept when we remembered Zion. We hung our harps on the willows in the midst of it. For there those who had taken us captive asked of us the words of a song, and those who had carried us away asked a hymn, saying, “Sing us one of the songs of Zion.”
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            على أنهارِ بابِلَ هناكَ جلسْنا، فبكيْنا عِندما تذكَّرْنا صِهيَونَ. على الصِّفصافِ في وسَطِها علَّقنا قيثاراتِنا، لأنَّهُ هناكَ سألَنا الذينَ سبَوْنا أقوالَ التسبيحِ. والذينَ استاقونا إلى هناكَ قالوا: سبِّحوا لنا تسبِحةً مِنْ تسابيحِ صِهيَونَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            How will we sing the Lord's song in a strange land? If I forget you, O Jerusalem, I shall forget my right hand. My tongue shall cling to my throat, if I did not remember you; if I did not prefer Jerusalem as the head of my joy.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            كيفَ نُسبِّحُ تسبِحةَ الربِّ في أرضٍ غريبةٍ؟ إنْ نسِيتُكِ يا أورُشليمُ أنسَ يميني، ويلتصِقُ لِساني بحنَكي إنْ لمْ أذكُرْكِ، إنْ لمْ أُفضِّلْ أورُشليمَ في ابتداءِ فرحي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Remember, O Lord, the children of Edom in the day of Jerusalem, who said, “Tear it down, tear it down, even to its foundations.” Wretched daughter of Babylon! Blessed is he who will reward you with the reward you have given us. Blessed is he who will seize and bury your infants by the rock. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اذكُرْ يا ربُّ بني أدومَ في يومِ أورُشليمَ القائلينَ: انقُضوا، انقُضوا حتَّى الأساسَ مِنْها. يا بِنتَ بابِلَ الشقيَّةَ طوبى لمَنْ يُكافِئُكِ مُكافأتِكِ التي جازيتِنا. طوبى لمَنْ يُمسِكُ أطفالَكِ ويدفِنُهُم عندَ الصخرةِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 140 - O Lord, I have cried to You...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والأربعونَ - يا ربُّ إليكَ صرختُ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord, I have cried to You; hear me; attend to the voice of my supplication when I cry to You. Let my prayer be set forth before You as incense, and the lifting up of my hands as an evening sacrifice. O Lord, set a watch on my mouth and a strong door for my lips. Do not incline my heart to words of evil, to employ excuses for sins with men who work iniquity, and I shall not agree with their choices. The righteous shall chasten me with mercy, and reprove me, but do not let the oil of the sinner anoint my head, for yet my prayer also is in their pleasures.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يا ربُّ إليكَ صرختُ فاستمِعْ لي. أنصِتْ إلى صوتِ تضرُّعي، إذا ما صرخْتُ إليكَ. لِتستقِمْ صلاتي كالبَخورِ قُدَّامَكَ. وليكنْ رفعُ يديَّ كذبيحةٍ مَسائيَّةٍ. ضعْ يا ربُّ حافِظاً لفمي، وباباً حصيناً لشفتيَّ. ولا تُمِلْ قلبي إلى كلامِ الشرِّ، فيتعلَّلُ بعِللٍ في الخطايا معَ أُناسٍ فاعلي الإثمِ، ولا أتفِقُ معَ مُختاريهِم. فليؤدِبْني الصدِّيقُ بِرحمةٍ ويوبِّخْني. أمَّا زيتُ الخاطئِ فلا يدهِنْ رأسي، لأنَّ صلاتي أيضاً بِمسرَّةٍ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Their mighty ones have been swallowed up near the rock; they shall hear my words, for they are delightful. As a lump of earth, they are broken upon the ground; their bones have been scattered at Hades. For my eyes are to You, O Lord; O Lord, I have hoped in You; do not take away my soul. Keep me from the snare which they have set for me, and from the stumbling blocks of those who work iniquity. Sinners shall fall by their own net; I am alone until iniquity passes by. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            قدْ ابتُلِعَ أقوياؤهُم عِندَ الصخرةِ، يسمعونَ كلِماتي لأنَّهُم استلذُّوا. مِثلُ شحمِ الأرضِ انشقُّوا على الأرضِ. تبدَّدتْ عِظامُهُم عِندَ الجحيمِ، لأنَّ عُيونَنا إليكَ يا ربُّ، يا ربُّ عليكَ توكَّلتُ فلا تقتُلْ نفسي. احفظْني مِنَ الفخِّ الذي قدْ نصبوهُ لي، ومِنْ شُكوكِ فاعلي الإثمِ. يسقُطُ الخُطاةُ في شبكتِهِم، وأكونُ أنا وحدي حتَّى يجوزَ الإثمُ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 145 - Praise the Lord, O my soul...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والخامسُ والأربعونَ - سبِّحي يا نفسي الربَّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Praise the Lord, O my soul. I will praise the Lord in my life. I will sing praises to my God as long as I exist. Do not trust in the princes, nor in the children of men, in whom there is no salvation. Their spirit shall go forth, and they shall return to their earth. In that day all their thoughts shall perish.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            سبِّحي يا نفسي الربَّ، أُسبِّحُ الربَّ في حياتي وأرتِّلُ لإلهي ما دُمتُ موجوداً. لا تتَّكِلوا على الرؤساءِ ولا على بني البشرِ الذينَ ليسَ عِندَهُم خلاصٌ. تخرُجُ رُوحُهُم فيعودونَ إلى تُرابِهِم. في ذلِكَ اليومِ تهلَكُ كافَّةُ أفكارِهِم.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Blessed is he whose helper is the God of Jacob,  whose hope is in the Lord his God, who made heaven and earth, the sea and all things in them, who keeps truth forever, who executes judgment for the oppressed, who gives food to the hungry.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            طوبى لمَنْ إلهُ يعقوبَ مُعينُهُ. واتِّكالُهُ على الربِّ إلهِهِ، الذي صنعَ السماءَ والأرضَ والبحرَ وكلَّ ما فيها. الحافِظِ العدلَ إلى الدهرِ، الصانِعِ الحُكمَ للمظلومينَ، المُعطي الطعامَ للجياعِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord looses the bound; the Lord sets up the broken down. The Lord gives wisdom to the blind; the Lord loves the righteous. The Lord preserves the strangers; He accepts the orphan and widow, but He will destroy the way of sinners. The Lord shall reign forever, and your God, O Zion, from generation to generation. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الربُّ يحِلُّ المربوطينَ، الربُّ يُقيمُ الساقِطينَ. الربُّ يُحَكِّمُ العُميانَ. الربُّ يُحبُّ الصدِّيقينَ. الربُّ يحفظُ الغُرباءَ، ويعضُدُ اليتيمَ والأرملةَ. ويُبيدُ طُرُقَ الخُطاةِ. يملِكُ الربُّ إلى الدهرِ، وإلهُكِ يا صِهيوَنُ مِنْ جيلٍ إلى جيلٍ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         The following Psalms from the Midnight Prayer are said:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 118 (20) - Look upon my humiliation...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والثامِنَ عشرَ (٢٠) - انظُرْ إلى مذلَّتي...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Look upon my humiliation, and save me, for I have not forgotten Your law. Plead my cause, and redeem me; revive me for the sake of Your word. Salvation is far from sinners, for they have not searched out Your ordinances. Your mercies, O Lord, are many; revive me according to Your judgments. Many are they who persecute me and distress me, but I did not turn away from Your testimonies. I beheld foolish men, and I suffered, for they did not keep Your words. Behold, O Lord, I have loved Your commandments; revive me in Your mercy. The beginning of Your words is truth, and all judgments of Your righteousness are forever.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            انظُرْ إلى مذلَّتي وأنقذني، فإنِّي لمْ أنسَ ناموسَكَ. احكُمْ لي في دعْوايَ ونجِّني. مِنْ أجلِ كلامِكَ أحيِني. بعيدٌ هو الخلاصُ عنْ الخُطاةِ، لأنَّهم لمْ يطلُبوا حُقوقَكَ. رأفتُكَ كثيرةٌ جِداً يا ربُّ، حَسْبَ أحكامِكَ أحيِني. كثيرونَ هُمُ الذينَ يضطَهِدونَني ويُحزِنونَني، وعنْ شَهاداتِكَ لمْ أجنَحْ. رأيتُ الذينَ لا يفهمونَ فاكتأبتُ، لأنَّهُم لأقوالِكَ لمْ يحفظوا. انظُرْ يا ربُّ، فإنِّي أحببتُ وصاياكَ. بِرحمتِكَ يا ربُّ أحيِني. بدءُ كلامِكَ حقٌ، وإلى الأبدِ كلُّ أحكامِ عدلِكَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲇⲟⲝⲁ ⲥⲓ ⲫⲓⲗⲁⲛⲑ̀ⲣⲱⲡⲉ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory to You, O Lover of Mankind.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجدُ لَكَ يا مُحِبَّ البَشَرِ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 118 (21) - Princes persecuted me...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والثامِنَ عشرَ (٢١) - الرؤساءُ اضطَهَدوني...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Princes persecuted me without a cause; my heart was afraid of Your words. I will exult because of Your words, as one who has found a great treasure. I hated and abhorred unrighteousness, but I loved Your law. Seven times a day I have praised You because of the judgments of Your righteousness. Let great peace be for those who love Your law, and there is no stumbling in them. I waited for Your salvation, O Lord, and have loved Your commandments. My soul has kept Your testimonies, and loved them exceedingly. I have kept Your commandments and Your testimonies, and all my ways are before You, O Lord.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الرؤساءُ اضطَهَدوني بِلا سببٍ. مِنْ أقوالِكَ جزِعَ قلبي. أبتهِجُ أنا بكلامِكَ كمَنْ وجدَ غنائمَ كثيرةً. أبغضتُ الظُلمَ ورذلتُهُ، أمَّا ناموسَكَ فأحببتُهُ. سبْعَ مرَّاتٍ في النهارِ سبَّحتُكَ على أحكامِ عدلِكَ. فليكُن سلامٌ عظيمٌ للذينَ يُحِبُّونَ اسمَكَ، وليسَ لهُم شَكٌ. توقَّعتُ خلاصَكَ يا ربُّ، ووصاياكَ أحببتُها. حفِظَتْ نفسي شهاداتِكَ، وأحببتُها جِداً. حفِظتُ وصاياكَ وشَهاداتِكَ، وكلُّ طُرُقي أمامَكَ يا ربُّ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲇⲟⲝⲁ ⲥⲓ ⲫⲓⲗⲁⲛⲑ̀ⲣⲱⲡⲉ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory to You, O Lover of Mankind.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجدُ لَكَ يا مُحِبَّ البَشَرِ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">      
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 118 (22) - Let my supplication come...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والثامِنَ عشرَ (٢٢) - فليَدنُ توسُّلي قُدَّامَكَ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Let my supplication come near before You, O Lord; give me understanding according to Your word. Let my petition come before You, revive me according to Your word. Let my lips flow with praise, when You have taught me Your ordinances. Let my tongue speak of Your words, for all Your commandments are righteous. Let Your hand be for saving me, for I have desired Your commandments. I have longed for Your salvation, O Lord, and Your law is my meditation. My soul shall live and praise You, and Your judgments shall help me. I have gone astray like a lost sheep; seek Your servant, for I have not forgotten Your commandments.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            فليَدنُ توسُّلي قُدَّامَكَ يا ربُّ، كقولِكَ فهِّمْني. فلتدخُلْ طِلبَتي إلى حضْرتِكَ يا ربُّ، ككلِمتِكَ أحيِني. تفيضُ شفَتايَ السُبحَ، إذا ما علَّمتَني حُقوقَكَ. لِساني ينطِقُ بأقوالِكَ، لأنَّ جميعَ وصاياكَ عادِلةٌ. لتكُنْ يدُكَ لِخلاصي، لأنَّني اشتهَيتُ وصاياكَ. اشتقتُ إلى خلاصِكَ يا ربُّ، وناموسُكَ هو تِلاوتي. تحيا نفسي وتُسبِّحُكَ، وأحكامُكَ تُعينُني. ضلَلتُ مِثلُ الخروفِ الضالِّ، فاطلُبْ عبدَكَ، فإنِّي لِوصاياكَ لمْ أنسَ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Role id="Introduction">
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Holy, holy, holy. A reading from the Holy Gospel according to our teacher Saint John. May his blessings be with us all. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            قدوسٌ، قدوسٌ، قدوسٌ، فصلٌ مِنْ بِشارةِ الإنجيلِ لمُعلِّمِنا مارِ يوحنَّا البشيرِ بركتِهِ على جميعِنا. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Role>
   
   <ns0:Role id="Reader">
      <ns0:Section expanded="true">
         <ns0:Title>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Gospel (John 6:15-23)
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               الإنجيل لمُعلِّمِنا يوحنا ص 6: 15-23
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Title>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               When Jesus therefore perceived that they would come and take Him by force to make Him a king, He departed again into a mountain by Himself alone. 
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               ولمَّا رَأى يَسوعُ أنَّهُم مُهْتَمُّونَ بأنْ يَأتوا ليَختَطِفوهُ، ويَجعَلوهُ مَلِكاً، انْصَرَفَ إلى الجَبَلِ وَحدَهُ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
               
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               And when evening came, His disciples went down to the sea, and entered into a boat, and went over the sea toward Capernaum. And it was now dark, and Jesus had not come to them. And the sea arose by reason of a great wind that blew.  So when they had rowed about three or four miles, they saw Jesus walking on the sea, and drawing near to the boat, and they were afraid. But He said to them, "It is I; do not be afraid." Then they willingly received Him into the boat: and immediately the boat was at the land where they were going.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               فَلَمَّا كانَ المَسَاءُ، نَزَلَ تَلامِيذُهُ إلى البَحْرِ، وركِبوا السَّفِينَةَ ذاهبينَ إلى عَبْرِ البَحرِ، إلى كَفرِنَاحُومَ. وكانَ الظَّلاَمُ قَدْ حَلَّ، ولمْ يَكُنْ يَسوعُ قَدْ جاءَ إلَيْهِمْ بعدُ. وكانَ البَحْرُ هائجاً، وريحٌ شَديدةٌ تَهُبُّ. فلَمَّا ابتَعدوا نَحوَ خَمْسٍ وعِشرِينَ غَلْوَةً أو ثَلاثِينَ، نَظَرُوا يَسوعَ مَاشِياً على البَحْرِ، مُقتَرِباً إلى السَّفِينَةِ فَخَافُوا. فقالَ لهُمْ: أنَا هُوَ لا تَخَافُوا. وكانوا يُريدونَ أنْ يَحمِلوهُ مَعَهُم في السَّفِينَةِ. ولِلوَقتِ جَاءَتْ السَّفِينَةُ إلى شَاطِئِ الأرضِ، التي كَانوا ذَاهِبينَ إليْهَا.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
               
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               On the following day, the people who stood on the other side of the sea saw that there was no other boat there, except that one which His disciples had entered, and that Jesus had not entered the boat with his disciples, but that His disciples had gone away alone. However, there came other boats from Tiberias near the place where they ate bread, after the Lord had given thanks.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وفي الغَدِ رَأى الجَمْعُ الذي كانَ واقِفاً عِندَ عَبْرِ البَحْرِ، أنَّهُ لَمْ تَكُنْ هُنَاكَ سَفِينَةٌ أُخْرَى، سِوَى وَاحِدةٍ، وَهِيَ تِلْكَ الَّتِي دَخَلَهَا تلاَمِيذُهُ، وأنَّ يَسوعَ لَمْ يَركبْ السَّفِينَةَ مَع تَلامِيذِهِ، بَلْ مَضَى تَلامِيذُهُ وحْدَهُمْ. وجَاءَتْ سُفُنٌ أُخْرَى مِنْ طَبَرِيَّةَ، عِندَ المَوضِعِ حَيثُ أَكَلوا الخُبزَ الذي شَكَرَ عَلَيهِ الربُّ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Section>
   </ns0:Role>
   
   <ns0:Role id="Priest">
       <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲇⲟⲝⲁ ⲥⲓ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ ⲏ̀ⲙⲱⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Glory be to God forever. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            والمجْدُ للهِ دَائماً
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>      
      
      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         May the sayings of God be fulfilled in peace.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليكمُلْ قولُ اللهِ بسلامٍ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="NativityPeriod | NativityParamoun | Circumcision">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               From the Paramoun of the Nativity to the Feast of the Circumcision:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲩⲙⲁⲥⲕ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You were born and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ وُلِدتَ وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="TheophanyPeriod | TheophanyParamoun">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               From Paramoun of the Theophany until the 12th of Tobe:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲕϭⲓⲱⲙⲥ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You were baptized and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ أعتمدت وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="PaschaWeek | Pascha | FeastOfTheCross | (FuneralTune ^ FuneralPrayer) | GeneralFuneralPrayer">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               On the two Feasts of the Cross, during Holy Pascha Week, and during funerals:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲩⲁϣⲕ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You were crucified and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ صلبت وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="!ThirdProstration ^ (Joyful29thOfTheMonthRaw | PentecostPeriod | (Sundays ^ ApostlesFastToLastDayOfHathor))">
         <ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">         
         On joyful days (see note in About Menu for details):
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
<ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲕⲧⲱⲛⲕ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You have risen and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ قمت وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="Other">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               On standard days of the year and on fasting days:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲕⲓ̀ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You have come and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنَّكَ أتيتَ وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group> 
</ns0:Role>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">Litanies</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">طلبةٌ</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
         
      <ns0:Role id="Reader">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               1. Lord, You know the alertness of my enemies; and as for my weakness, You are aware of it, my Creator.  Therefore, I, hereby, place my soul into Your hands.  So cover me with the wings of Your goodness, lest I might sleep till death. Enlighten my eyes by the greatness of Your sayings, and raise me up at all times for Your glorification, for You alone are Good and Lover of Mankind.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               1. يا ربُّ أنتَ تَعْرِفُ يَقَظةَ أعْدائِي، وضَعْفُ طَبيعَتي أنتَ تَعْلَمُهُ، يا خالِقي. لأنِّي هوذا أضَعُ رُوحِي في يَدَيْكَ، فاستُرْنِي بأجْنحَةِ صَلاحِكَ، لِئَلَّا أنَامَ إلى الوَفاةِ. أضِئْ عَينَيَّ بعَظَمَةِ أقوالِكَ، وانهِضْنِي في كُلِّ حينٍ لِتمجيدِكَ، لأنَّكَ صَالِحٌ وَحدَكَ، ومُحِبُّ البَشرِ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Role>
            
      <ns0:Role id="People">
      <ns0:Text forceLanguage="Coptic">
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲇⲟⲝⲁ Ⲡⲁⲧⲣⲓ ⲕⲉ Ⲩⲓⲱ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲱ Ⲡⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁⲧⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجدُ للآبِ والابنِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Role>
<ns0:Role id="Reader">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               2. Lord, Your judgment is dreadful; when men shall be rushed, the angels shall stand, the books shall be opened, the deeds shall be revealed, and the thoughts examined.  What a judgment mine will be, I who am entangled by sin?!  Who would quench the flames of fire about me?!  Who would enlighten my darkness, other than You, O Lord?! Have mercy on me, for You are compassionate to mankind.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               2. يا ربُّ إنَّ دَيْنونَتَكَ لمرهُوبَةٌ. إذ تُحشَرُ النَّاسُ، وتَقِفُ الملائِكةُ، وتُفْتَحُ الأسْفارُ، وتنكشِفُ الأعمالُ، وتُفحَصُ الأفكارُ. أيَّةُ إدانَةٍ تَكونُ إدانَتِي أنا المَضبُوطُ بالخَطايَا. مَنْ يُطفِئُ لهِيبَ النَّارِ عَنِّي؟! مَنْ يُضِيءُ ظُلمَتِي، إنْ لمْ تَرحَمْنِي أنتَ يا ربُّ؟ لأنَّكَ مُتعَطِّفٌ على البَشَرِ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Role>
            
      <ns0:Role id="People">
      <ns0:Text forceLanguage="Coptic">
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲕⲉ ⲛⲩⲛ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲓ̀ ⲕⲉ ⲓⲥ ⲧⲟⲩⲥ ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲁⲥ ⲧⲱⲛ ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲱⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.         
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.      
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Role>
<ns0:Role id="Reader">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               3. O Theotokos, because we have put our trust in you, we shall not be put to shame, but shall be saved.  And because we have attained your help and intercession, O holy and perfect one, we shall not fear, but shall drive out our enemies and shall disperse them.  And, in everything, we take your great help to protect us as if with a shield.  We ask and entreat you, crying, O Theotokos, to save us by your intercessions, and raise us up from the dark sleep, in order to powerfully glorify God who took flesh from you.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               3. يا والِدةَ الإلَهِ، إذ قد حوَينَا الثقةَ بكِ، فلا نَخزَى بَلْ نَخلُصُ. وإذ قد اقتَنَينَا مَعونَتَكِ وشَفَاعَاتِكِ أيَّتُهَا الطَّاهِرةُ الكامِلةُ فلا نَخَافُ، بَلْ نَطرُدُ أعداءَنَا فَنُبدِّدُهُم. ونَتَّخِذُ لنا سِترَ مَعونَتِكِ القَويَّةِ في كُلِّ شيءٍ، نَظِيرَ التُّرسِ. ونَسألُ ونَتَضرَّعُ إليكِ هاتِفينَ، يا والِدَةَ الإلَهِ. لِكَيْ تُخَلِّصِينا بِشَفاعَاتِكِ. وتُنهِضينَا مِنَ النَّومِ المُظلِمِ إلى التَمجِيدِ، بِقُوَّةِ الإلهِ المُتجسِّدِ مِنْكِ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Role>
   </ns0:Section>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Trisagion</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">الثلاث تقديسات</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ...</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲓⲥⲭⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲁ̀ⲑⲁⲛⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲟ̀ ⲉⲕ ⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲩ ⲅⲉⲛⲛⲉⲑⲏⲥ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, who was born of the Virgin, have mercy upon us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         قُدّوسٌ اللَّهُ، قُدّوسٌ القَويُّ، قُدّوسٌ الحَيُّ الَّذي لا يَموتُ، الَّذي وُلِدَ مِنَ العَذْراءِ ارحَمْنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲓⲥⲭⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲁ̀ⲑⲁⲛⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲟ̀ ⲥ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲣⲱⲑⲓⲥ ⲇⲓ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ: ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, who was crucified for us, have mercy upon us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         قُدّوسٌ اللَّهُ، قُدّوسٌ القَويُّ، قُدّوسٌ الحَيُّ الَّذي لا يَموتُ، الَّذي صُلِبَ عنّا ارحَمْنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲓⲥⲭⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲁ̀ⲑⲁⲛⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲟ̀ ⲁ̀ⲛⲁⲥⲧⲁⲥ ⲉⲕ ⲧⲱⲛ ⲛⲉⲕⲣⲱⲛ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲛⲉⲗⲑⲱⲛ ⲓⲥ ⲧⲟⲩⲥ ⲟⲩⲣⲁⲛⲟⲥ: ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, who rose from the dead and ascended into the heavens, have mercy upon us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         قُدّوسٌ اللَّهُ، قُدّوسٌ القَويُّ، قُدّوسٌ الحَيُّ الَّذي لا يَموتُ، الَّذي قامَ مِنَ الأمْواتِ، وصَعِدَ إلى السَّماواتِ ارحَمْنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲇⲟⲝⲁ Ⲡⲁⲧⲣⲓ ⲕⲉ Ⲩⲓⲱ: ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲱ Ⲡⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁⲧⲓ: ⲕⲉ ⲛⲩⲛ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲓ̀ ⲕⲉ ⲓⲥⲧⲟⲩⲥ: ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲁⲥ ⲧⲱⲛ ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲱⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit. Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجْدُ للآبِ والابن والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، الآنَ وكلَّ أَوانٍ وإلى دَهْرِ الدّهورِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>   
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲁ ⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ: ⲡⲁⲛⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲁ ⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ: ϯⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا، أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا، أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲡⲁⲣⲁⲡⲧⲱⲙⲁ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Lord, forgive us our sins. O Lord, forgive us our iniquities. O Lord, forgive us our trespasses.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا خَطايانا، ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا آثامَنا، ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا زَلاّتِنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ϫⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲓⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉⲧϣⲱⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲗⲁⲟⲥ: ⲙⲁⲧⲁⲗϭⲱⲟⲩ ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅: ⲛⲉⲛⲓⲟϯ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲉⲛⲥ̀ⲛⲏⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲉⲛⲕⲟⲧ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲙⲁⲙ̀ⲧⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲛⲟⲩⲯⲩⲭⲏ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Lord, visit the sick of Your people, heal them for the sake of Your holy name. Our fathers and brethren who have fallen asleep, O Lord, repose their souls.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ياربُّ افْتَقدْ مَرْضَى شَعْبِكَ. اشْفِهمْ مِنْ أجْلِ اسْمِكَ القُدُّوسِ. آباؤُنا وإخْوَتُنا الَّذينَ رَقدوا ياربُّ نَيِّحْ نُفوسَهُم.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲓⲁⲑⲛⲟⲃⲓ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲡⲓⲁⲑⲛⲟⲃⲓ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲁ̀ⲣⲓⲃⲟⲏ̀ⲑⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ ϣⲉⲡ ⲡⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O You who are without sin, Lord, have mercy on us. O You who are without sin, Lord, help us and receive our supplications.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         يا مَنْ هُوَ بِلا خَطيئَةٍ ياربُّ ارحَمْنا. يا الَّذي بِلا خَطيئَةٍ ياربُّ أَعِنّا واقْبَلْ طَلباتِنا إليكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ ⲫⲱⲕ ⲡⲉ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲁ̀ⲙⲁϩⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ: Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲩⲗⲟⲅⲏⲥⲟⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.            
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         For Yours is the glory, the dominion, and triple holiness. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord bless us. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         لأنَّ لَكَ المجْدَ والعِزَّةَ والتَّقْديسَ المثلَّثَ، ياربُّ ارحَمْ، ياربُّ ارْحَمْ، ياربُّ بارِكْ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>   
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Our Father</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">أبانا الذي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲧⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲁ ⲛ̀ϫⲟⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Make us worthy to pray thankfully:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اللهُمَّ اجعلْنا مُستحقينَ أن نقولَ بشكرٍ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ Ⲡⲉⲛⲓⲱⲧ ⲉⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be Thy name.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أبانا الذي في السماواتِ ليتقدسِ اسمُكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲥⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ: ⲡⲉⲧⲉϩⲛⲁⲕ ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥϣⲱⲡⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲕⲁϩⲓ:  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Thy kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليأتِ ملكوتُكَ، لتكُن مشيئتُكَ، كما في السماءِ كذلكَ على الأرضِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲓⲕ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲣⲁⲥϯ ⲙⲏⲓϥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲫⲟⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲣⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Give us this day our daily bread and forgive us our trespasses, as we forgive those who trespass against us and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         خبزَنا الذي للغدِّ أعطِنا اليومَ، واغفِرْ لنا ذنوبَنا كما نغفِرُ نحنُ أيضاً للمُذنبينَ إلينا، ولا تُدخِلنا في تجرِبةٍ لكِنْ نجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ: ϫⲉ ⲑⲱⲕ ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In Christ Jesus our Lord. For Thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, forever. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِّنا. لأنَّ لكَ المُلكَ والقوةَ والمجدَ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Hail to You</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">السّلامُ لَكِ...</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
      
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲛⲉ ⲧⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟ: ⲱ̀ ⲑⲏⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅ ⲉⲑⲙⲉϩ ⲛ̀ⲱ̀ⲟⲩ: ⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲛ̀ⲥⲏⲟⲩ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ϯⲙⲁⲥⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲑ̀ⲙⲁⲩ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Hail to you. We ask you, O saint, full of glory, the ever-virgin, the Theotokos, the Mother of Christ,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         السَّلامُ لَكِ، نَسْألُكِ أيَّتُها القِدّيسَةُ الممْتَلِئةُ مَجْداً، العَذْراءُ كلَّ حينٍ، والِدةُ الإلَهِ، أمُّ المسيحِ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲛⲓⲟⲩⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲉⲩⲭⲏ: ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ϣⲱⲓ ϩⲁ ⲡⲉϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲉⲛⲣⲓⲧ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Lift up our prayers unto your beloved Son, that He may forgive us our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اصْعدي صَلَواتِنا إلى ابْنِكِ الحَبيبِ، ليغْفِرَ لَنا خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲑⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲥⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ: ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Hail to the holy Virgin, who has brought forth unto us the true Light, Christ our God.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         السَّلامُ لِلَّتي وَلَدَتْ لَنا النّورَ الحَقيقيَّ المسيحَ إلَهَنا. العَذْراءُ القدّيسَةُ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁϯϩⲟ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲉⲣⲟⲩⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲉⲛⲯⲩⲭⲏ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Ask the Lord on our behalf, that He may have mercy on our souls, and forgive us our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اسْألي الرَّبَّ عنّا ليَصْنَعَ رَحْمَةً مَعَ نُفوسِنا، ويغفِرَ لَنا خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ Ⲙⲁⲣⲓⲁⲙ: ϯⲑⲉⲟ̀ⲧⲟⲕⲟⲥ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅: ϯⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲧⲁⲧⲏⲥ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲛϩⲟⲧ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡ̀ⲅⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲣⲱⲙⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Virgin Mary, the holy Theotokos, the faithful advocate for all mankind,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أيَّتُها العَذْراءُ مَرْيَمُ والِدةُ الإلهِ، القِدّيسَةُ الشَّفيعَةُ الأمينَةُ لجنْسِ البَشرِيّةِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲡ̀ⲣⲉⲥⲃⲉⲩⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅ ⲫⲏⲉⲧⲁⲣⲉϫ̀ⲫⲟϥ: ϩⲟⲡⲱⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲉⲣϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Intercede on our behalf before Christ whom you bore, that He may grant us the forgiveness of our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اشْفَعي فينا أَمامَ المَسيحِ الَّذي وَلدْتِهِ، لِكَيْ يُنْعِمَ لنا بغُفْرانِ خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲛⲉ ⲱ̀ ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ: ϯⲟⲩⲣⲱ ⲙ̀ⲙⲏⲓ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲗⲏⲑⲓⲛⲏ: ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲡ̀ϣⲟⲩϣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲅⲉⲛⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲣⲉϫ̀ⲫⲟ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲛ̀Ⲉⲙⲙⲁⲛⲟⲩⲏⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Hail to you, O Virgin, / the right and true Queen. / Hail to the pride of our race / who bore to us Immanuel.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         السَّلامُ لكِ أيَّتُها العَذْراءُ الملكةُ الحقيقيَّةُ الحقانِيَّةُ السَّلامُ لفَخرِ جِنسِنا ولدْتِ لنا عِمَّانوئيلَ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲁ̀ⲣⲓⲡⲉⲛⲙⲉⲩⲓ̀: ⲱ̀ ϯⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲧⲁⲧⲏⲥ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲛϩⲟⲧ: ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲉⲛⲟ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲓⲏ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We ask you to remember us, / O our faithful advocate, / before our Lord Jesus Christ / that He may forgive us our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نسألُكِ أن تَذكُرينا أيَّتُها الشفيعةُ المؤتمنةُ أمامَ ربِّنا يسوعَ المسيحِ ليغفِرَ لنا خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">     
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Introduction to the Creed</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">بدء قانون الإيمان</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>      
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϭⲓⲥⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟ ⲑ̀ⲙⲁⲩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: ⲧⲉⲛϯⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲉ ⲱ̀ ⲑⲏⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁⲥⲛⲟⲩϯ: ϫⲉ ⲁ̀ⲣⲉⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲡ̀ⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲕⲟⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲧⲏⲣϥ: ⲁϥⲓ̀ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁϥⲥⲱϯ ⲛ̀ⲛⲉⲛⲯⲩⲭⲏ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We exalt you, the Mother of the true Light. We glorify you, O saint, the Theotokos, for you have brought forth unto us the Savior of the whole world; He came and saved our souls. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نُعظِّمُكِ يا أمَّ النُّورِ الحَقيقيِّ. ونُمجِّدُكِ أيَّتُها العَذْراءُ القِدّيسةُ والِدةُ الإلهِ. لأنَّكِ وَلدْتِ لَنا مُخلِّصَ العالَمِ. أتَى وخَلَّصَ نُفُوسَنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>      
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲟⲩⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲁⲕ ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲏⲃ ⲡⲉⲛⲟⲩⲣⲟ Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅: ⲡ̀ϣⲟⲩϣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲁ̀ⲡⲟⲥⲧⲟⲗⲟⲥ: ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲗⲟⲙ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲙⲁⲣⲧⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲡ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲇⲓⲕⲉⲟⲥ: ⲡ̀ⲧⲁϫⲣⲟ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲉ̀ⲕⲕ̀ⲗⲏⲥⲓⲁ: ⲡ̀ⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲛⲟⲃⲓ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory be to You, our Master, our King, Christ, the pride of the apostles, the crown of the martyrs, the joy of the righteous, the firmness of the churches, the forgiveness of sins.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجْدُ لكَ يا سَيِّدَنا ومَلِكَنا المسيحَ: فَخْرَ الرُّسُلِ، إكْليلَ الشُهداءِ، تَهْليلَ الصِدّيقينَ، ثَباتَ الكَنائسِ، غُفْرانَ الخَطايا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>      
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲧⲉⲛϩⲓⲱⲓϣ ⲛ̀ϯⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ⲉⲥϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲙⲉⲑⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ: ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲥ: ⲧⲉⲛϯⲱⲟⲩ ⲛⲁⲥ. Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ: Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ: Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲩⲗⲟⲅⲏⲥⲟⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We proclaim the Holy Trinity in one Godhead. We worship Him. We glorify Him. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord bless us. Amen.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نُبشِّرُ بالثَّالوثِ القُدُّوسِ: لاهوتٌ واحِدٌ. نَسجُدُ لهُ ونُمجِّدُهُ. ياربُّ ارحَمْ، ياربُّ ارحَمْ، ياربُّ بارِكْ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">      
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">The Orthodox Creed</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">قانون الإيمان المقدس الأرثوذكسي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
         
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛⲛⲁϩϯ ⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ: Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲡⲓⲡⲁⲛⲧⲟⲕⲣⲁⲧⲱⲣ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁϥⲑⲁⲙⲓⲟ ⲛ̀ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡ̀ⲕⲁϩⲓ: ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲩⲛⲁⲩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛ̀ⲥⲉⲛⲁⲩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ ⲁⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We believe in one God, God the Father, the Pantocrator, Creator of heaven and earth, and of all things seen and unseen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نؤمنُ بإلهٍ واحدٍ اللهِ الآبِ ضابطِ الكلِ خالقِ السماءِ والأرضِ. ما يُرَى وما لا يُرَى
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛⲛⲁϩϯ ⲉ̀ⲟⲩϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲡϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲙ̀Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲡⲓⲙⲟⲛⲟⲅⲉⲛⲏⲥ: ⲡⲓⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ϧⲁϫⲱⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲉ̀ⲱⲛ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We believe in one Lord, Jesus Christ, the only-begotten Son of God, begotten of the Father before all ages.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نؤمنُ بربٍ واحدٍ يسوعَ، المسيحِ، ابنِ اللهِ الوحيدِ المولودِ مِنَ الآبِ قبلَ كلِّ الدهورِ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲟⲩⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ: ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: ⲟⲩⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲡⲉ ⲟⲩⲑⲁⲙⲓⲟ ⲁⲛ ⲡⲉ ⲟⲩⲟ̀ⲙⲟⲟⲩⲥⲓⲟⲥ ⲡⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ϣⲱⲡⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲓⲧⲟⲧϥ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Light of Light, true God of true God; begotten, not created; of one essence with the Father; by whom all things were made.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نورٍ مِنْ نورٍ إلهِ حقٍ مِنْ إلهِ حقٍ، مولودٍ غيرِ مخلوقٍ، مساوٍ للآبِ في الجوهرِ الذي بِهِ كانَ كلُّ شيءٍ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲉⲑⲃⲏⲧⲉⲛ ⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲛ ϧⲁ ⲛⲓⲣⲱⲙⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲟⲩϫⲁⲓ: ⲁϥⲓ̀ ⲉ̀ⲡⲉⲥⲏⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ: ⲁϥϭⲓⲥⲁⲣⲝ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲙⲁⲣⲓⲁ ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁϥⲉⲣⲣⲱⲙⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Who for us men and for our salvation came down from heaven, was incarnate of the Holy Spirit and of the Virgin Mary, and became man.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         هذا الذي مِنْ أجلِنا نحنُ البشرَ ومِنْ أجلِ خلاصِنا نزِلَ مِنَ السماءِ وتجسدَ مِنَ الرّوحِ القُدُسِ ومِنْ مريمَ العذراءِ وتأنسَ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="CovenantThursday | JoyousSaturday">
         <ns0:Group>            
            <ns0:Season id="JoyousSaturday">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲣⲱⲛⲓⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟϥ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲟⲛⲧⲓⲟⲥ Ⲡⲓⲗⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲁϥϣⲉⲡⲉⲙⲕⲁϩ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲕⲟⲥϥ. 
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     And He was crucified for us under Pontius Pilate, suffered and was buried;  
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وصُلِبَ عنَّا على عهدِ بيلاطسَ البُنطيِّ، تألّمَ وقُبِرَ
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
         </ns0:Group>
         
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Skip to “Yes, we believe in the Holy Spirit...” 
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="Other">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲣⲱⲛⲓⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟϥ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲟⲛⲧⲓⲟⲥ Ⲡⲓⲗⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲁϥϣⲉⲡⲉⲙⲕⲁϩ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲕⲟⲥϥ. Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁϥⲧⲱⲛϥ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲏⲉⲑⲙⲱⲟⲩⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁϩϣⲟⲙⲧ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ⲛⲓⲅ̀ⲣⲁⲫⲏ. 
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               And He was crucified for us under Pontius Pilate, suffered and was buried, and on the third day He rose from the dead according to the Scriptures. 
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وصُلِبَ عنَّا على عهدِ بيلاطسَ البُنطيِّ، تألّمَ وقُبِرَ وقامَ مِنْ بينِ الأمواتِ في اليومِ الثالثِ كما في الكتبِ
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲁϥϣⲉⲛⲁϥ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ϣⲱⲓ ⲉ̀ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲁϥϩⲉⲙⲥⲓ ⲥⲁⲟⲩⲓⲛⲁⲙ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉϥⲓⲱⲧ. Ⲕⲉ ⲡⲁⲗⲓⲛ ϥ̀ⲛⲏⲟⲩ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲉϥⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ϯϩⲁⲡ ⲉ̀ⲛⲏⲉⲧⲟⲛϧ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉⲑⲙⲱⲟⲩⲧ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲧⲉϥⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲟⲩⲁⲑⲙⲟⲩⲛⲕ ⲧⲉ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Ascended into the heavens; He sits at the right hand of His Father, and He is coming again in His glory to judge the living and the dead, whose kingdom shall have no end.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وصَعِدَ إلى السماواتِ وجلسَ عن يمينِ أبيهِ وأيضاً يأتي في مجدِهِ ليُدينَ الأحياءَ والأمواتَ الذي ليسَ لمُلكِهِ انقضاءٌ
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲥⲉ ⲧⲉⲛⲛⲁϩϯ ⲉ̀Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲛ̀ⲣⲉϥϯ ⲙ̀ⲡ̀ⲱⲛϧ: ⲫⲏⲉⲑⲛⲏⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲫ̀ⲓⲱⲧ: ⲥⲉⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟϥ ⲥⲉϯ ⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲁϥ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡϣⲏⲣⲓ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁϥⲥⲁϫⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲫⲏⲧⲏⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Yes, we believe in the Holy Spirit, the Lord, the Giver of Life, who proceeds from the Father, who with the Father and the Son, is worshiped and glorified, who spoke by the prophets.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نَعَم نؤمنُ بالرّوحِ القُدُسِ الربِّ المحيي المنبثقِ مِنَ الآبِ، نسجدُ لهُ ونمجدُهُ معَ الآبِ والابنِ الناطقِ في الأنبياءِ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲉⲟⲩⲓ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲁ ⲛ̀ⲕⲁⲑⲟⲗⲓⲕⲏ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲡⲟⲥⲧⲟⲗⲓⲕⲏ ⲛ̀ⲉⲕⲕ̀ⲗⲏⲥⲓⲁ̀. Ⲧⲉⲛⲉⲣⲟ̀ⲙⲟⲗⲟⲅⲓⲛ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲙⲥ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲛⲟⲃⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         And in one holy, catholic (universal), and apostolic Church. We confess one baptism, for the remission of sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وبكنيسةٍ واحدةٍ مُقدسَةٍ جامعةٍ رسوليةٍ. ونعترفُ بمعموديةٍ واحدةٍ لمغفِرةِ الخطايا
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>         
      <ns0:Season id="(FuneralTune ^ FuneralPrayer) | GeneralFuneralPrayer">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               The last verse is chanted in the “Golgotha” tune:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="Other">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               The people chant the last sentence in a loud voice.
            </ns0:Language>         
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               ثم يقول الشعب جهراً هذه الجملة الأخيرة مِنْ قانون الإيمان، وهي:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϫⲟⲩϣⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϧⲁⲧ̀ϩⲏ ⲛ̀ϯⲁ̀ⲛⲁⲥⲧⲁⲥⲓⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲣⲉϥⲙⲱⲟⲩⲧ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱⲛϧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲓⲉ̀ⲱⲛ ⲉⲑⲛⲏⲟⲩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We look for the resurrection of the dead, and the life of the age to come. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وننتظرُ قيامةَ الأمواتِ، وحياةَ الدهرِ الآتي. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Role id="Priest">
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord hear us and have mercy on us and forgive us our sins. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ياربُّ اسمَعْنا وارحَمْنا واغفِرْ لنا خطايانا. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Role>
<ns0:Text forceLanguage="Coptic">
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ (ⲙ̅ⲁ̅)
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Lord have mercy (41)          
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ياربُّ ارحَمْ (41)
      </ns0:Language>   
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">Holy, Holy, Holy</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Holy, holy, holy, Lord of Sabaoth. Heaven and earth are full of Your glory and honor. Have mercy on us, O God the Father, the Pantocrator. O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Lord, God of hosts, be with us. For we have no helper in our hardships and tribulations but You. Absolve, forgive, and remit, O God, our transgressions; those which we have committed willingly and those which we have committed unwillingly, those which we have committed knowingly and those which we have committed unknowingly, the hidden and the manifest, O Lord forgive us, for the sake of Your holy name which is called upon us. Let it be according to Your mercy, O Lord, and not according to our sins.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ، ربُّ الصباؤوتِ. السماءُ والأرضُ مملوءتانِ مِنْ مجدِكَ وكرامتِكَ. ارحَمْنا يا اللهُ الآبُ ضابطُ الكلِّ. أيها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا. أيها الربُّ إلهُ القواتِ كُن معنا، لأنَّهُ ليسَ لنا مُعينٌ في شدائدِنا وضيقاتِنا سِواكَ. حلِّ واغفِرْ واصفحْ لنا يا اللهُ عَن سيئاتِنا، التي صنعناها بإرادتِنا والتي صنعناها بغيرِ إرادتِنا، التي فعلناها بمعرفةٍ والتي فعلناها بغيرِ معرفةٍ، الخفيةِ والظاهرةِ. ياربُّ اغفِرْها لنا، مِنْ أجلِ اسمِكَ القُدُّوسِ الذي دُعِيَ علينا. كرحمتِكَ ياربُّ وليسَ كخطايانا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Our Father</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">أبانا الذي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲧⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲁ ⲛ̀ϫⲟⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Make us worthy to pray thankfully:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اللهُمَّ اجعلْنا مُستحقينَ أن نقولَ بشكرٍ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ Ⲡⲉⲛⲓⲱⲧ ⲉⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be Thy name.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أبانا الذي في السماواتِ ليتقدسِ اسمُكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲥⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ: ⲡⲉⲧⲉϩⲛⲁⲕ ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥϣⲱⲡⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲕⲁϩⲓ:  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Thy kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليأتِ ملكوتُكَ، لتكُن مشيئتُكَ، كما في السماءِ كذلكَ على الأرضِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲓⲕ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲣⲁⲥϯ ⲙⲏⲓϥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲫⲟⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲣⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Give us this day our daily bread and forgive us our trespasses, as we forgive those who trespass against us and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         خبزَنا الذي للغدِّ أعطِنا اليومَ، واغفِرْ لنا ذنوبَنا كما نغفِرُ نحنُ أيضاً للمُذنبينَ إلينا، ولا تُدخِلنا في تجرِبةٍ لكِنْ نجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ: ϫⲉ ⲑⲱⲕ ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In Christ Jesus our Lord. For Thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, forever. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِّنا. لأنَّ لكَ المُلكَ والقوةَ والمجدَ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">      
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Absolution
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            التحليلُ
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord and Master, Jesus Christ our God, grant us rest in our sleep, repose of our bodies, and purity of our souls, and protect us from the darkness of devastating sin. May the pangs of pain subside, and the heat of the flesh calm down, and the turmoil of the body come to an end. Grant us an alert mind, a humble thought, a life full of virtue, and a pure and undefiled bed.  Raise us up for the night and morning praises, steadfast in Your commandments, keeping in ourselves, at all times, the thought of Your judgments. Grant us to praise You the whole night, blessing Your holy name full of glory and splendor, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, the Life-Giver, now and at all times and unto the ages of all ages.  Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أيُّها السَّيِّدُ الربُّ يَسوعُ المَسيحُ إلهُنَا، أعطِنَا رَاحَةً في نَومِنَا، ونِياحاً في أجْسَادِنا، وطَهارَةً في أنْفُسِنا. واحفَظْنا مِنْ ظُلمَةِ الخَطيئةِ المُدْلَهِمَّةِ. ولْتَسْكُنْ حَرَكاتُ الآلامِ، ولْتَنطفِئْ حرَارَةُ الجَسدِ. وابطِلْ شَغَبَ الجِسْمِ. وامنَحْنا عَقلاً مُستَيقِظاً، وفِكْراً مُتواضِعاً، وسِيرةً مَملوءَةً فَضيلَةً، وفِراشاً غَيرَ دَنِسٍ، ومَضْجَعاً نَقِيَّاً. وانْهِضْنَا لتَسبِيحِ اللَّيلِ، وبَاكِرِ، ثَابِتينَ في وصَايَاكَ، وحافِظِينَ في ذواتِنا على الدَّوامِ ذِكْرَ أحْكَامِكَ. وَهَبْ لنا تَمجيداً في اللَّيلِ أجمعِ. لِنُبَارِكَ اسمَكَ القُدُّوسَ المَملُوءَ مَجداً وبَهاءً، مَعَ أبيكَ الصَّالِحِ، والرُّوح القُدُسِ المُحيِي، الآنَ وكُلَّ أوانٍ، وإلى دَهرِ الدُّهُورِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
         
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">Conclusion of Every Hour</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">طلبةٌ تقالُ آخرَ كلِّ ساعةٍٍ</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Have mercy on us, O God, and have mercy on us, who at all times and in every hour, in heaven and on earth, is worshipped and glorified; Christ our God, the good, the long suffering, the abundant in mercy, and the great in compassion, who loves the righteous and has mercy on the sinners of whom I am chief, who does not wish the death of the sinner but rather that he returns and lives, who calls all to salvation for the promise of the good things to come.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ارحَمْنا يا اللهُ ثمَّ ارحَمْنا، يا مَنْ في كلِّ وقتٍ وكلِّ ساعةٍ، في السماءِ وعلى الأرضِ، مسجودٌ لهُ ومُمجَّدٌ. المسيحُ إلهُنا الصالحُ، الطويلُ الرّوحِ، الكثيرُ الرحمةِ، الجزيلُ التحننِ، الذي يحبُّ الصديقينَ ويرحمُ الخطاةَ الذينَ أوَّلُهُم أنا. الذي لا يشاءُ موتَ الخاطئِ مثلَ ما يرجعُ ويحيا. الدَّاعي الكلَّ إلى الخلاصِ لأجلِ الموعدِ بالخيراتِ المُنتظَرةِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Lord receive from us our prayers in this hour and in every hour. Ease our life and guide us to fulfill Your commandments. Sanctify our spirits. Cleanse our bodies. Conduct our thoughts. Purify our intentions. Heal our diseases. Forgive our sins. Deliver us from every evil grief and distress of heart. Surround us by Your holy angels, that, by their camp, we may be guarded and guided, and attain the unity of faith, and the knowledge of Your imperceptible and infinite glory. For You are blessed forever. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ياربُّ اقبَلْ مِنَّا في هذهِ الساعةِ وكلِّ ساعةٍ طلباتِنا. سهِّلْ حياتَنا، وارشِدْنا إلى العملِ بوصاياكَ. قدِّسْ أرواحَنا. طهِّرْ أجسامَنا. قوِّمْ أفكارَنا. نَقِّ نياتِنا. اشفِ أمراضَنا واغفِرْ خطايانا. ونجِّنا مِنْ كلِّ حزنٍ رديءٍ ووجعِ قلبٍ. أحِطنا بملائكتِكَ القديسينَ، لكي نكونَ بمعسكرِهِم محفوظينَ ومُرشَدينَ، لنصِلَ إلى اتِّحادِ الإيمانِ وإلى معرفةِ مجدِكَ غيرِ المحسوسِ وغيرِ المحدودِ، فإنَّكَ مُبارَكٌ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
</ns0:Document>