<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<ns0:Document xmlns:ns0="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" Agpeya="true">
   <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">The Twelfth Hour (Compline)</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">صلاةُ النَومِ</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         6:00 PM: To commemorate the laying of our Lord Jesus Christ in the tomb.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         تُقابِلُ السادِسةَ مساءً بالتوقيتِ الفرنجي. رُتِّبَتْ بمُناسبةِ دفنِ سيِّدِنا في القبرِ وانتهاءِ نهارِ اليومِ. نطلُبُ فيها خلاصاً مِنَ الدينونةِ الرهيبةِ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
            
   <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Introduction of Every Hour</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">مُقدِمةُ كلِّ ساعةٍ</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
    
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ ⲫ̀ⲣⲁⲛ ⲙ̀Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In the name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, one God. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         باسمِ الآبِ والابنِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ الإلهِ الواحدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         <ns0:span class="Coptic">Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ</ns0:span>. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord bless us. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         <ns0:span class="Coptic">Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ.</ns0:span>  ياربُّ ارحَمْ. ياربُّ ارحَمْ. ياربُّ بارِكْ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit. Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجدُ للآبِ والابنِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Our Father</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">أبانا الذي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲧⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲁ ⲛ̀ϫⲟⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Make us worthy to pray thankfully:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اللهُمَّ اجعلْنا مُستحقينَ أن نقولَ بشكرٍ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ Ⲡⲉⲛⲓⲱⲧ ⲉⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be Thy name.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أبانا الذي في السماواتِ ليتقدسِ اسمُكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲥⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ: ⲡⲉⲧⲉϩⲛⲁⲕ ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥϣⲱⲡⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲕⲁϩⲓ:  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Thy kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليأتِ ملكوتُكَ، لتكُن مشيئتُكَ، كما في السماءِ كذلكَ على الأرضِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲓⲕ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲣⲁⲥϯ ⲙⲏⲓϥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲫⲟⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲣⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Give us this day our daily bread and forgive us our trespasses, as we forgive those who trespass against us and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         خبزَنا الذي للغدِّ أعطِنا اليومَ، واغفِرْ لنا ذنوبَنا كما نغفِرُ نحنُ أيضاً للمُذنبينَ إلينا، ولا تُدخِلنا في تجرِبةٍ لكِنْ نجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ: ϫⲉ ⲑⲱⲕ ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In Christ Jesus our Lord. For Thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, forever. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِّنا. لأنَّ لكَ المُلكَ والقوةَ والمجدَ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">The Prayer of Thanksgiving</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">صلاةُ الشكر</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>

      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲛϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲟⲧϥ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲉϥⲉⲣⲡⲉⲑⲛⲁⲛⲉϥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲏⲧ: Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲛⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Let us give thanks to the beneficent and merciful God, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         فلنشكرْ صانعَ الخيراتِ، الرحومَ اللهَ أبا ربِّنا وإلَهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>   
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ ⲁϥⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲕⲉⲡⲁⲍⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲁϥⲉⲣⲃⲟⲏ̀ⲑⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁϥⲁ̀ⲣⲉϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁϥϣⲟⲡⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟϥ ⲁϥϯⲁ̀ⲥⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁϥϯⲧⲟⲧⲉⲛ ⲁϥⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲓⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩ ⲑⲁⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         For He has covered us, helped us, guarded us, accepted us to Himself, spared us, supported us, and has brought us to this hour.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         لأنهُ سترَنا وأعانَنا وحفظَنا وقبلَنا إليهِ وأشفقَ علَينا وعضدَنا وأتى بِنا إلى هذهِ الساعةِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲛⲑⲟϥ ⲟⲛ ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟϥ ϩⲟⲡⲱⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲁ̀ⲣⲉϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲁⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲛϧ: ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲓⲣⲏⲛⲏ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲓⲡⲁⲛⲧⲟⲕⲣⲁⲧⲱⲣ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Let us also ask Him, the Lord our God, the Pantocrator, to guard us in all peace this holy day and all the days of our life.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         هو أيضاً فلنسألْهُ أن يحفظَنا في هذا اليومِ المُقدسِ، وكلِّ أيامِ حياتِنا بكلِّ سلامٍ، الضابطَ الكلِّ الربَّ إلهَنا.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲛⲏⲃ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲡⲓⲡⲁⲛⲧⲟⲕⲣⲁⲧⲱⲣ: Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲛⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Master, Lord, God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أيها السيدُ الربُّ الإلهُ ضابطُ الكلِّ، أبو ربِّنا وإلَهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>   
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲟⲧⲕ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         we thank You for everything, concerning everything, and in everything.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نشكرُكَ على كلِّ حالٍ، ومِنْ أجلِ كلِّ حالٍ، وفي كلِّ حالٍ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ ⲁⲕⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲕⲉⲡⲁⲍⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲁⲕⲉⲣⲃⲟⲏ̀ⲑⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁⲕⲁ̀ⲣⲉϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁⲕϣⲟⲡⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ: ⲁⲕϯⲁ̀ⲥⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁⲕϯⲧⲟⲧⲉⲛ ⲁⲕⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲓⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩ ⲑⲁⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         For You have covered us, helped us, guarded us, accepted us to Yourself, spared us, supported us, and have brought us to this hour.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         لأنكَ سترتَنا وأعنتَنا وحفظتَنا، وقبلتَنا إليكَ، وأشفقتَ علينا وعضَّدتَنا وأتيتَ بنا إلى هذهِ الساعةِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲧⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲧⲉⲛⲧⲱⲃϩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ ⲡⲓⲙⲁⲓⲣⲱⲙⲓ: ⲙⲏⲓⲥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉⲑⲣⲉⲛϫⲱⲕ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲙ̀ⲡⲁⲓⲕⲉⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲫⲁⲓ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲛϧ: ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲓⲣⲏⲛⲏ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲧⲉⲕϩⲟϯ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Therefore, we ask and entreat Your goodness, O Lover of Mankind, grant us to complete this holy day and all the days of our life in all peace with Your fear.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         مِنْ أجلِ هذا نسألُ ونطلبُ مِنْ صلاحِكَ يا محبَّ البشرِ، امنحنا أن نكمِّلَ هذا اليومَ المُقدسَ، وكلَّ أيامِ حياتِنا بكلِّ سلامٍ معَ خوفِكَ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲑⲟⲛⲟⲥ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ⲉ̀ⲛⲉⲣⲅⲓⲁ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡ̀ⲥⲁⲧⲁⲛⲁⲥ: ⲡ̀ⲥⲟϭⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ϩⲁⲛⲣⲱⲙⲓ ⲉⲩϩⲱⲟⲩ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡ̀ⲧⲱⲛϥ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ϣⲱⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ϩⲁⲛϫⲁϫⲓ ⲛⲏⲉⲧϩⲏⲡ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉⲑⲟⲩⲱⲛϩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         All envy, all temptation, all the work of Satan, the counsel of wicked men and the rising up of enemies, hidden and manifest,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         كلُّ حسدٍ وكلُّ تجربةٍ وكلُّ فعلِ الشيطانِ، ومؤامرةُ الناسِ الأشرارِ، وقيامُ الأعداءِ الخفيينَ والظاهرينَ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="!Agpeya">
         <ns0:Comment>         
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               The priest bows his head toward the East and signs himself with the sign of the cross, saying:
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               يطامن الكاهن رأسه إلى الشرق ويرشم ذاته بمثال الصليب قائلاً:
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Comment>         
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲁ̀ⲗⲓⲧⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁⲣⲟⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         take them away from us
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         انزعْها عنَّا.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="!Agpeya">
         <ns0:Comment>         
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Then he turns toward the west from his right and makes the sign of the cross over the people, saying the following. If the Pope, a metropolitan, or a bishop is present, he makes the sign of the cross over the people and says the following instead of the priest.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               ثم يلتفت إلى الغرب عن يمينه ويرشم الشعب قائلاً:[إذا كان الأب البابا أو المطران أو الأسقف حاضراً فهو الذي يرشم الشعب ويقول ذلك.]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲉⲕⲗⲁⲟⲥ ⲧⲏⲣϥ
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         and from all Your people,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وعن سائرِ شعبِكَ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="Baptism | Unction | LiturgyOfTheWaters | Engagement | Crowning | FuneralPrayer | GeneralFuneralPrayer | Ordination">
         <ns0:Group>
            <ns0:Season id="ConsecrationOfWaters | BathingPrayer | LiturgyOfTheWaters">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲕⲟⲗⲩⲙⲃⲏⲑⲣⲁ ⲑⲁⲓ
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this basin,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذه الفسقيةِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="AbsolutionOfWoman">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲥ̀ϩⲓⲙⲓ ⲑⲁⲓ:
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this woman,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذه المرأةِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Unction">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉⲧϣⲱⲛⲓ 
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this infirm person,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذا المريضِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Engagement">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉⲧⲁϥⲱⲡ ⲛ̀ⲥⲁ ⲑⲁⲓ
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this betrothed couple,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذين الخطيبين
                  </ns0:Language>
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Crowning">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲛⲁⲓⲡⲁⲧϣⲉⲗⲉⲧ ⲛⲁⲓ
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this bridegroom and bride,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذين العروسين.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="(FuneralPrayer ^ !FuneralMemorial) | GeneralFuneralPrayer">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲯⲩⲭⲏ ⲑⲁⲓ 
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this soul,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذه النفسِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Ordination">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this Your servant,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن عبدك هذا.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
         </ns0:Group>
         
         <ns0:Group>
            <ns0:Season id="!Agpeya">
               <ns0:Comment>         
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     Then he turns towards the East, making the sign of the cross, saying:
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     ثم يلتفت إلى الشرق قائلا:
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Comment>
            </ns0:Season>
         </ns0:Group>
      </ns0:Season>

      <ns0:Season id="HomeBlessing">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲁⲓⲏⲓ ⲫⲁⲓ
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               and from this house,
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وعن هذا البيتِ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>

      <ns0:Season id="!OfferingOfLamb ^ !Agpeya ^ !Ordination">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲉⲕⲕ̀ⲗⲏⲥⲓⲁ̀ ⲑⲁⲓ
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               and from this church,
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وعن هذه الكنيسةِ.
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
         
         <ns0:Comment>         
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Then he turns toward the East, making the sign of the cross on the altar, saying:
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               ثم يلتفت إلى الشرق ويرشم على المذبح قائلاً:
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="OfferingOfLamb">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲧ̀ⲣⲁⲡⲉⲍⲁ ⲑⲁⲓ
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               and from this table,
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وعن هذه المائدة،
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲁⲓⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲕ ⲫⲁⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         and from this Your holy place.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وعن موضعِكَ المُقدسِ هذا.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲛⲏ ⲇⲉ ⲉⲑⲛⲁⲛⲉⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉⲧⲉⲣⲛⲟϥⲣⲓ ⲥⲁϩⲛⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲱⲟⲩ ⲛⲁⲛ: ϫⲉ ⲛ̀ⲑⲟⲕ ⲡⲉ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲕϯ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲉⲣϣⲓϣⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲉ̀ϩⲱⲙⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ⲛⲓϩⲟϥ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓϭ̀ⲗⲏ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲧⲏⲣⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲓϫⲁϫⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         But those things which are good and profitable do provide for us, for it is You who have given us the authority to tread on serpents and scorpions, and upon all the power of the enemy.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أمَّا الصالحاتُ والنافعاتُ فارزقنا إياها لأنكَ أنتَ الذي أعطيتَنا السلطانَ أن ندوسَ على الحياتِ والعقاربَ وعلى كلِّ قوةِ العدوِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ: ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ولا تُدْخِلْنا في تجربةٍ لكن نَجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲓϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓⲙⲉⲧϣⲉⲛϩⲏⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲙⲁⲓⲣⲱⲙⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲙⲟⲛⲟⲅⲉⲛⲏⲥ ⲛ̀Ϣⲏⲣⲓ: Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲛⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Through the grace, compassion, and love-of-mankind of Your only-begotten Son, our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالنعمةِ والرأفاتِ ومحبةِ البشرِ اللواتي لابنِكَ الوحيدِ، ربِّنا وإلهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲓⲧⲟⲧϥ ⲉ̀ⲣⲉ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲧⲁⲓⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲁ̀ⲙⲁϩⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲕⲩⲛⲏⲥⲓⲥ: ⲉⲣⲡ̀ⲣⲉⲡⲓ ⲛⲁⲕ ⲛⲉⲙⲁϥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲛ̀ⲣⲉϥⲧⲁⲛϧⲟ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ⲟ̀ⲙⲟⲟⲩⲥⲓⲟⲥ ⲛⲉⲙⲁⲕ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         through whom the glory, honor, dominion, and worship are due unto You, with Him and the Holy Spirit, the Giver of Life, who is of one essence with You,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         هذا الذي مِنْ قبَلِه، المجدُ والكرامةُ والعزة والسجودُ، تليقُ بكَ معَهُ، ومعَ الرّوحِ القُدُسِ المُحيي المساوي لكَ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϯⲛⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛ̀ⲥⲏⲟⲩ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         now and at all times and unto the age of all ages. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ كلِّها. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 50
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ الخمسونَ
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲏⲓ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ⲡⲉⲕⲛⲓϣϯ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲓ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ⲡ̀ⲁ̀ϣⲁⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧϣⲉⲛϩⲏⲧ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲥⲱⲗϫ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲁ̀ⲙⲟⲛⲓⲁ̀: ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲣⲁϧⲧ ⲛ̀ϩⲟⲩⲟ̀ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲁⲛⲟⲃⲓ: ϫⲉ ⲧⲁⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ̀ ⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲕ ϯⲥⲱⲟⲩⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲥ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲁⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡⲁⲙ̀ⲑⲟ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗⲛ̀ⲥⲏⲟⲩ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Have mercy upon me, O God, according to Your great mercy; and according to the multitude of Your compassions blot out my iniquity. Wash me thoroughly from my iniquity, and cleanse me from my sin. For I am conscious of my iniquity; and my sin is at all times before me.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ارحَمْنِي يا اللهُ كَعَظيمِ رَحْمتِكَ، ومِثْلِ كَثْرةِ رَأفتِكَ امْحُ إثْمِي واغْسلْنِي كَثيراً مِنْ إثْمِي، ومِنْ خَطيئَتِي طهِّرْنِي. لأنِّي أنا عارِفٌ بإثْمِي، وخَطيئَتِي أمَامِي في كلِّ حينٍ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲛⲑⲟⲕ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁⲩⲁⲧⲕ ⲁⲓⲉⲣⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ ⲁⲓⲁⲓϥ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕⲙ̀ⲑⲟ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ϩⲟⲡⲱⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲁⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲕⲥⲁϫⲓ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲕ ϭⲣⲟ ⲉⲕⲛⲁϭⲓϩⲁⲡ. Hⲏⲡⲡⲉ ⲅⲁⲣ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ̀ ⲁⲩⲉⲣⲃⲟⲕⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲓ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲁ̀ ⲧⲁⲙⲁⲩ ϭⲓϣϣⲱⲟⲩ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲓ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Against You only I have sinned, and done evil before You, that You might be just in Your sayings, and might overcome when You are judged. For, behold, I was conceived in iniquities, and in sins my mother conceived me.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لَكَ وحْدَكَ أخْطأْتُ، والشَّرَّ قدامَكَ صَنعْتُ، لِكيْ تَتَبرَّرَ في أقْوالِكَ، وتَغْلبَ إذَا حوكِمْتَ. لأنِّي هَأنَذَا بالإثْمِ حُبِلَ بِي، وبالَخَطايَا ولدَتْني أمِّي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Hⲏⲡⲡⲉ ⲅⲁⲣ ⲁⲕⲙⲉⲛⲣⲉ ⲑ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: ⲛⲏⲉⲧϩⲏⲡ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛ̀ⲥⲉⲟⲩⲱⲛϩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲁⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲥⲟⲫⲓⲁ ⲁⲕⲧⲁⲙⲟⲓ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ. Ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲛⲟⲩϫϧ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕϣⲉⲛϩⲩⲥⲱⲡⲟⲛ: ⲉⲓⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲣⲁϧⲧ ⲉⲓⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲃⲁϣ ⲉ̀ϩⲟⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲭⲓⲱⲛ: ⲉⲕⲉⲑ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲱⲧⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲟⲩⲟⲩⲛⲟϥ: ⲉⲩⲉ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲛⲓⲕⲁⲥ ⲉⲧⲑⲉⲃⲓⲏⲟⲩⲧ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            For, behold, You have loved the truth; You have manifested to me the hidden and unrevealed things of Your wisdom. You shall sprinkle me with Your hyssop, and I shall be purified. You shall wash me, and I shall be made whiter than snow. You shall make me to hear gladness and joy; the humbled bones shall rejoice.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لأنَّكَ هَكَذا قَدْ أحْبَبتَ الحقَّ، إذْ أوْضَحتَ لِي غَوامِضَ حِكْمتِكَ ومَسْتُورَاتِها. تَنضَحُ عَليَّ بِزُوفَاكَ فأُطَهَّرُ، تَغْسلُنِي فَأبْيضُّ أكْثَرَ مِنَ الثَّلجِ. تُسْمعُنِي سُرُوراً وفَرحاً، فتَبْتهجُ عِظامِي المتواضِعةُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲙⲁⲧⲁⲥⲑⲟ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕϩⲟ ⲥⲁⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲛⲟⲃⲓ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛⲁⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ̀ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲥⲟⲗϫⲟⲩ. Ⲟⲩϩⲏⲧ ⲉϥⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲥⲟⲛⲧϥ ⲛ̀ϧⲏⲧ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ: ⲟⲩⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉϥⲥⲟⲩⲧⲱⲛ ⲁ̀ⲣⲓⲧϥ ⲙ̀ⲃⲉⲣⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲏⲉⲧⲥⲁϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲃⲉⲣⲃⲱⲣⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲉⲕϩⲟ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲕⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲟⲗϥ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁⲣⲟⲓ. Ⲙⲟⲓ ⲛⲏⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲟⲩϫⲁⲓ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲛ̀ϩⲏⲅⲉⲙⲱⲛⲓⲕⲟⲛ ⲙⲁⲧⲁϫⲣⲟⲓ: ⲉⲓⲉ̀ⲧ̀ⲥⲁⲃⲉ ⲛⲓⲁⲛⲟⲙⲟⲥ ϩⲓ ⲛⲉⲕⲙⲱⲓⲧ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛⲓⲁⲥⲉⲃⲏⲥ ⲉⲩⲉ̀ⲕⲟⲧⲟⲩ ϩⲁⲣⲟⲕ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Turn away Your face from my sins, and blot out all my iniquities. Create in me a clean heart, O God; and renew a right spirit in my inward parts. Do not cast me away from Your face; and do not remove Your Holy Spirit from me. Give me the joy of Your salvation, and uphold me with a directing spirit. Then I shall teach the transgressors Your ways; and the ungodly men shall turn to You.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اصْرِفْ وجْهَكَ عَنْ خَطايَايَ وامْحُ كلَّ آثَامِي. قَلباً نَقياً اخْلقْ فيَّ يا اللهُ، ورُوحاً مُسْتَقيماً جدِّدهُ في أحْشَائِي. لا تَطْرحْنِي مِنْ قُدَّامِ وجْهِكَ، ورُوحُكَ القُدُّوسُ لا تَنْزعْهُ مِنِّي. امْنَحْنِي بَهْجةَ خَلاصِكَ، وبرُوحٍ رئاسيٍ اعْضُدْنِي فأُعلِّمُ الأثَمَةَ طُرُقَكَ، والمنَافِقونَ إليكَ يَرجِعونَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛⲥ̀ⲛⲟϥ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ: Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲧⲁⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣⲓⲁ: ⲉϥⲉ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲁⲗⲁⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧⲉⲕⲇⲓⲕⲉⲟⲥⲩⲛⲏ. Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲥ̀ⲫⲟⲧⲟⲩ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲉ ⲣⲱⲓ ϫⲱ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕⲥ̀ⲙⲟⲩ: ϫⲉ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉ ⲁⲕⲟⲩⲱϣ ϣⲟⲩϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ: ⲛⲁⲓⲛⲁϯ ⲟⲛ ⲡⲉ: ϩⲁⲛϭⲗⲓⲗ ⲛ̀ϫⲟϥϫⲉϥ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕϯⲙⲁϯ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲟⲩ. Ⲡⲓϣⲟⲩϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉϥⲧⲉⲛⲛⲏⲟⲩⲧ ⲡⲉ: ⲟⲩϩⲏⲧ ⲉϥⲧⲉⲛⲛⲏⲟⲩⲧ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲉϥⲉ̀ⲑⲉⲃⲓⲏⲟⲩⲧ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲛ̀ⲛⲉ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ϣⲟϣϥ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Deliver me from blood, O God, the God of my salvation, and my tongue shall rejoice in Your righteousness. O Lord, You shall open my lips, and my mouth shall declare Your praise. For if You desired sacrifice, I would have given it; You do not take pleasure in burnt offerings. The sacrifice of God is a broken spirit; a broken and humbled heart God shall not despise.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            نَجِّنِي مِنَ الدِّماءِ يا اللهُ إلَهَ خَلاصِي، فيَبتهِجُ لِسانِي بعَدلِكَ. ياربُّ افْتَحْ شَفتَيَّ، فَيُخبرُ فَمِي بَتَسْبيحِكَ. لأنَّكَ لَوْ آثَرتَ الذَّبيحةَ لَكُنْتُ الآنَ أعْطِي؛ ولَكنَّكَ لا تُسرُّ بالَمُحْرقَاتِ فالذَبيحَةُ للهِ رُوحٌ مُنْسحقٌ. القَلْبُ المنْكسِرُ والمتَواضِعُ لا يُرْذلُهُ اللهُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲁⲣⲓⲡⲉⲑⲛⲁⲛⲉϥ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲉⲕϯⲙⲁϯ ⲉ̀Ⲥⲓⲱⲛ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛⲓⲥⲟⲃⲧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ Ⲓⲉⲣⲟⲩⲥⲁⲗⲏⲙ ⲙⲁⲣⲟⲩⲕⲟⲧⲟⲩ: ⲧⲟⲧⲉ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ϯⲙⲁϯ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛϣⲟⲩϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲉⲑⲙⲏⲓ: ⲟⲩⲁⲛⲁⲫⲟⲣⲁ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲁⲛϭⲗⲓⲗ: ⲧⲟⲧⲉ ⲉⲩⲉ̀ⲓ̀ⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ϩⲁⲛⲙⲁⲥⲓ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ⲱϣⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲉⲕⲙⲁⲛ̀ⲉⲣϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Do good, O Lord, in Your good pleasure to Zion; and let the walls of Jerusalem be built. Then You shall be pleased with sacrifices of righteousness, offering, and burnt sacrifices: then they shall offer calves upon Your altar. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أنْعِمْ ياربُّ بِمَسرتِكَ عَلى صِهْيَونَ ولْتُبنَ أسْوَارُ أورُشَلِيمَ. حِينَئذٍ تُسرُّ بذَبائِحِ العدلِ، قرباناً ومُحْرقَاتٍ. حينَئذٍ يُقرِّبونَ عَلى مَذابِحِكَ العُجُولَ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>     
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Role id="Introduction">
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The blessed prayer of retiring, we offer to Christ our King and our God, beseeching Him to forgive us our sins.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            تسبحة النوم من هذا اليوم المبارك أقدمها للمسيح ملكي والهي وأرجوه أن يغفر لي خطاياي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Role>
         
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         From the Psalms of our teacher David the prophet.  May his blessings be upon us all. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         مِنْ مزاميرِ مُعلِّمِنا داودَ النبي بركاتِهِ علينا. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>    
<ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         The following psalms are reserved to be prayed by the priest:
         <ns0:ul>
            <ns0:li>Psalm 129</ns0:li>
            <ns0:li>Psalm 140</ns0:li>
            <ns0:li>Psalm 147</ns0:li>
         </ns0:ul>
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 129 - Out of the depths...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والتاسعُ والعشرونَ - مِنَ الأعماقِ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Out of the depths I have cried to You, O Lord. O Lord, hear my voice; let Your ears be attentive to the voice of my supplication. If You, O Lord, should mark iniquities, O Lord, who shall stand? For through You is forgiveness. For Your name's sake I have waited for You, O Lord. My soul has waited for Your law. My soul has hoped in the Lord, from the morning watch till night. From the morning watch, let Israel hope in the Lord. For with the Lord is mercy, and great is His redemption; and He shall redeem Israel from all his iniquities. ALLELUIA
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            مِنَ الأعماقِ صرختُ إليكَ يا ربُّ، يا ربُّ استمِعْ صوتي. لِتكنْ أُذُناكَ مُصغِيَتَينِ إلى صوتِ تضرُّعي. إنْ كنتَ للآثامِ راصِداً يا ربُّ، يا ربُّ مَنْ يثبُتُ لأنَّ مِنْ عِندِكَ المغفِرةَ. مِنْ أجلِ اسمِكَ صبَرْتُ لكَ يا ربُّ، صبَرَتْ نفسي لناموسِكَ. انتظرَتْ نفسي الربَّ مِنْ مَحْرَسِ الصُبحِ إلى الليلِ. مِنْ مَحْرَسِ الصُبحِ فلينتظِرْ إسرائيلُ الربَّ. لأنَّ الرحمةَ مِنْ عندِ الربِّ. عظيمٌ هو خلاصُهُ وهو يفتدي إسرائيلَ مِنْ كلِّ آثامِهِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 130 - O Lord, my heart was not exalted...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والثلاثونَ - يا ربُّ لمْ يرتفِعْ قلبي...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord, my heart was not exalted, neither have my eyes been haughtily raised; neither have I walked in great matters, nor in wonders greater than me. If I have not humbled myself, but raised my soul, as a weaned child with his mother, so is the recompense upon my soul. Let Israel hope in the Lord, from now and forever. ALLELUIA
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يا ربُّ لمْ يرتفِعْ قلبي، ولمْ تسْتعْلِ عَينايَ، ولمْ أسلُكْ في العظائمِ ولا في العجائبِ التي هي أعلى مِنِّي. فإنْ كنتُ لمْ أتضِعْ لكِنْ رفعتُ صَوتي مِثلُ الفطيمِ مِنَ اللبنِ على أمِّهِ. كذلِكَ المُجازاةُ على نفسي. فليتكِلْ إسرائيلُ على الربِّ مِنَ الآنَ وإلى الأبدِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 131 - Lord, remember David...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والحادي والثلاثونَ - اذكُرْ يا ربُّ داودَ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Lord, remember David and all his meekness; how he swore to the Lord, and vowed to the God of Jacob, saying, “I will not go into the dwelling of my house, or go up to the bed of my couch; I will not give sleep to my eyes, nor slumber to my eyelids, nor rest to my temples, until I find a place for the Lord, and a dwelling place for the God of Jacob.” Behold, we heard of it in Ephratha; we found it in the fields of the wood. Let us enter into His dwelling, and worship at the place where His feet stood.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اذكُرْ يا ربُّ داودَ وكلَّ دِعَتِهِ. كيفَ أقسَمَ للربِّ ونذرَ لإلهِ يعقوبَ: إنِّي لا أدخُلُ إلى مسكنِ بيتي، ولا أصعدُ على سريرِ فِراشي، ولا أُعطي لعَينيَّ نوماً، ولا لأجفاني نُعاساً، ولا راحةً لصِدغَيَّ، إلى أنْ أجدَ موضِعاً للربِّ ومسكناً لإلهِ يعقوبَ. ها قدْ سَمِعنا بهِ في أفراتةَ ووجدناهُ في موضِعِ الغابةِ. فلندخُلْ إلى مساكنِهِ ونسجُدْ في الموضِعِ الذي فيهِ استقرَّتْ قدَماهُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Arise, O Lord, into Your rest, You, and the ark of Your holy place. Your priests shall clothe themselves with righteousness, and Your righteous shall exult. For the sake of Your servant David, do not turn away Your face from Your anointed.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            قُمْ يا ربُّ إلى راحتِكَ أنتَ وتابوتُ موضِعِ قُدسِكَ. كهنتُكَ يلبَسونَ البِرَّ وأبرارُكَ يبتهِجونَ. مِنْ أجلِ داودَ عبدِكَ لا ترُدَّ وجهَكَ عنْ مسيحِكَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord has sworn in truth to David, and He will not turn from it, “Of the fruit of your loins I will set upon your throne. If your children keep My covenant and My testimonies which I will teach them, their children also will sit upon your throne forever.”
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            حلفَ الربُّ لداودَ حقاً ولا يخلِفُ: لأجعَلنَّ مِنْ ثمرةِ بطنِكَ على كُرسيِّكَ. إنْ حفِظَ بنوكَ عهْدي وشهاداتي التي أُعلِّمُهُم إيَّاها، فبنوهُم أيضاً يجلِسونَ إلى الأبدِ على كُرسيِّكَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            For the Lord has selected Zion, He has chosen her a dwelling for Himself. “This is My resting place forever. Here I will dwell; for I have desired it. In blessing I shall bless her hunting. Her poor I shall satisfy with bread. Her priests I shall clothe with salvation, and her saints with rejoicing shall rejoice. There I shall raise a horn to David. I have prepared a lamp for My anointed. His enemies I shall clothe with shame, and My holiness shall flourish upon Him.” ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لأنَّ الربَّ اختارَ صِهيَونَ ورضيَها مسْكناً لهُ: هذا هو موضِعُ راحتي إلى أبدِ الأبدِ، ههنا أسكُنُ لأنِّي أردتُهُ. لصيدِها أبارِكُ بركةً، لمساكينِها أُشبِعُ خُبزاً، لكهنتِها أُلبِسُ الخلاصَ وأبرارُها يبتهِجونَ ابتِهاجاً. هناكَ أُقيمُ قرناً لداودَ. هيَّأتُ سِراجاً لمسيحي. لأعدائِهِ أُلبِسُ الخِزيَ وعليهِ يُزهِرُ قُدسي. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 132 - Behold! What is so good...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والثاني والثلاثونَ - هوذا ما أحسنَ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Behold! What is so good, or what so pleasant, as for brothers dwelling together? It is as ointment upon the head, that came down upon the beard, the beard of Aaron that came down to the fringe of his clothing; as the dew of Aermon, that comes down upon the mountain of Zion, for there the Lord commanded the blessing and the life forever. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            هوذا ما أحسنَ وما أحلى أنْ يسكُنَ الإخوةُ معاً. كالطيبِ الكائنِ على الرأسِ الذي ينزِلُ على اللحيةِ، لحيةِ هارونَ النازِلةِ على جيبِ قميصِهِ. ومِثلُ ندى حَرمونَ المُنحدِرِ على جبلِ صِهيَونَ. لأنَّ هناكَ أمرَ الربُّ بالبركةِ والحياةِ إلى الأبدِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 133 - Behold, bless the Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والثالثُ والثلاثونَ - ها بارِكوا الربََّّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Behold, bless the Lord, O you the servants of the Lord, who stand in the house of the Lord, in the courts of the house of our God. In the nights lift up your hands O you saints, and bless the Lord. The Lord shall bless you out of Zion, He who made heaven and earth. ALLELUIA
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ها بارِكوا الربَّ يا عبيدَ الربِّ، القائمينَ في بيتِ الربِّ في ديارِ إلهِنا. في الليالي ارفعوا أيدَيَكُم أيها القِدِّيسونَ وبارِكوا الربَّ. يُبارِكُكُمُ الربُّ مِنْ صِهيَونَ الذي خلقَ السماءَ والأرضَ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 136 - By the rivers of Babylon...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والسادسُ والثلاثونَ - على أنهارِ بابِلَ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat and wept when we remembered Zion. We hung our harps on the willows in the midst of it. For there those who had taken us captive asked of us the words of a song, and those who had carried us away asked a hymn, saying, “Sing us one of the songs of Zion.”
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            على أنهارِ بابِلَ هناكَ جلسْنا، فبكيْنا عِندما تذكَّرْنا صِهيَونَ. على الصِّفصافِ في وسَطِها علَّقنا قيثاراتِنا، لأنَّهُ هناكَ سألَنا الذينَ سبَوْنا أقوالَ التسبيحِ. والذينَ استاقونا إلى هناكَ قالوا: سبِّحوا لنا تسبِحةً مِنْ تسابيحِ صِهيَونَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            How will we sing the Lord's song in a strange land? If I forget you, O Jerusalem, I shall forget my right hand. My tongue shall cling to my throat, if I did not remember you; if I did not prefer Jerusalem as the head of my joy.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            كيفَ نُسبِّحُ تسبِحةَ الربِّ في أرضٍ غريبةٍ؟ إنْ نسِيتُكِ يا أورُشليمُ أنسَ يميني، ويلتصِقُ لِساني بحنَكي إنْ لمْ أذكُرْكِ، إنْ لمْ أُفضِّلْ أورُشليمَ في ابتداءِ فرحي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Remember, O Lord, the children of Edom in the day of Jerusalem, who said, “Tear it down, tear it down, even to its foundations.” Wretched daughter of Babylon! Blessed is he who will reward you with the reward you have given us. Blessed is he who will seize and bury your infants by the rock. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اذكُرْ يا ربُّ بني أدومَ في يومِ أورُشليمَ القائلينَ: انقُضوا، انقُضوا حتَّى الأساسَ مِنْها. يا بِنتَ بابِلَ الشقيَّةَ طوبى لمَنْ يُكافِئُكِ مُكافأتِكِ التي جازيتِنا. طوبى لمَنْ يُمسِكُ أطفالَكِ ويدفِنُهُم عندَ الصخرةِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 137 - I will give thanks to You...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والسابعُ والثلاثونَ - أعترِفُ لكَ يا...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            I will give thanks to You, O Lord, with my whole heart, for You have heard all the words of my mouth. Before the angels I will chant to You. I will worship toward Your holy temple, and give thanks to Your name, on account of Your mercy and Your truth, for You have magnified Your holy name above all. The day in which I call upon You, hear me speedily; You shall exceedingly look upon my soul with power. Let all the kings of the earth, O Lord, give thanks to You, for they have heard all the words of Your mouth. And let them sing in the ways of the Lord, for great is the glory of the Lord.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أعترِفُ لكَ يا ربُّ مِنْ كلِّ قلبي لأنَّكَ استمعْتَ كلَّ كلِماتِ فمي. أمامَ الملائكةِ أُرتِّلُ لكَ وأسجُدُ قُدَّامَ هيكلِكَ المُقدَّسِ، وأعترِفُ لاسمِكَ على رحمتِكَ وحقِّكَ، لأنَّكَ قدْ عظَّمتَ اسمَكَ القُدُّوسَ على الكلِّ. اليومَ الذي أدعوكَ فيهِ أجِبْني بسُرعةٍ. تُكثِرُ التطلُّعَ على نفسي بقوةٍ. فليعترِفْ لكَ يا ربُّ كلُّ ملوكِ الأرضِ. لأنَّهُم قدْ سمِعوا سائرَ كلِماتِ فمِكَ وليُسبِّحوا في طُرُقِ الربِّ. لأنَّ مجدَ الربِّ عظيمٌ،
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord is high, and He regards the lowly, and He knows the existing things from afar off. If I walk in the midst of affliction, You shall revive me; You have stretched forth Your hands against the wrath of enemies, and Your right hand has saved me. O Lord, You shall reward on my behalf; Your mercy, O Lord, endures forever, do not overlook the works of Your hands. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لأنَّ الربَّ عالٍ ويُعاينُ المُتواضِعاتِ والكائناتُ يعرِفُها مِنْ بُعدٍ. إنْ سلكْتُ في وسَطِ الشِدَّةِ فإنَّكَ تُحيِني. على رِجزِ الأعداءِ مددتَ يدَكَ وخلَّصَتْني يمينُكَ. الربُّ يُجازي عنِّي، يا ربُّ رحمتُكَ دائمةٌ إلى الأبدِ. أعمالُ يدَيكَ يا ربُّ لا تترُكْها. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 140 - O Lord, I have cried to You...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والأربعونَ - يا ربُّ إليكَ صرختُ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord, I have cried to You; hear me; attend to the voice of my supplication when I cry to You. Let my prayer be set forth before You as incense, and the lifting up of my hands as an evening sacrifice. O Lord, set a watch on my mouth and a strong door for my lips. Do not incline my heart to words of evil, to employ excuses for sins with men who work iniquity, and I shall not agree with their choices. The righteous shall chasten me with mercy, and reprove me, but do not let the oil of the sinner anoint my head, for yet my prayer also is in their pleasures.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يا ربُّ إليكَ صرختُ فاستمِعْ لي. أنصِتْ إلى صوتِ تضرُّعي، إذا ما صرخْتُ إليكَ. لِتستقِمْ صلاتي كالبَخورِ قُدَّامَكَ. وليكنْ رفعُ يديَّ كذبيحةٍ مَسائيَّةٍ. ضعْ يا ربُّ حافِظاً لفمي، وباباً حصيناً لشفتيَّ. ولا تُمِلْ قلبي إلى كلامِ الشرِّ، فيتعلَّلُ بعِللٍ في الخطايا معَ أُناسٍ فاعلي الإثمِ، ولا أتفِقُ معَ مُختاريهِم. فليؤدِبْني الصدِّيقُ بِرحمةٍ ويوبِّخْني. أمَّا زيتُ الخاطئِ فلا يدهِنْ رأسي، لأنَّ صلاتي أيضاً بِمسرَّةٍ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Their mighty ones have been swallowed up near the rock; they shall hear my words, for they are delightful. As a lump of earth, they are broken upon the ground; their bones have been scattered at Hades. For my eyes are to You, O Lord; O Lord, I have hoped in You; do not take away my soul. Keep me from the snare which they have set for me, and from the stumbling blocks of those who work iniquity. Sinners shall fall by their own net; I am alone until iniquity passes by. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            قدْ ابتُلِعَ أقوياؤهُم عِندَ الصخرةِ، يسمعونَ كلِماتي لأنَّهُم استلذُّوا. مِثلُ شحمِ الأرضِ انشقُّوا على الأرضِ. تبدَّدتْ عِظامُهُم عِندَ الجحيمِ، لأنَّ عُيونَنا إليكَ يا ربُّ، يا ربُّ عليكَ توكَّلتُ فلا تقتُلْ نفسي. احفظْني مِنَ الفخِّ الذي قدْ نصبوهُ لي، ومِنْ شُكوكِ فاعلي الإثمِ. يسقُطُ الخُطاةُ في شبكتِهِم، وأكونُ أنا وحدي حتَّى يجوزَ الإثمُ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 141 - With my voice to the Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والحادي والأربعونَ - بِصوتي إلى الربِّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            With my voice to the Lord I cried; with my voice to the Lord I made supplication. I will pour out before Him my supplication. My affliction I will pour out before Him, when my spirit was fainting within me, and You knew my paths. In the way in which I was walking, they hid a snare for me. I looked on my right hand, and beheld, for there was no one who noticed me. Refuge failed me, and there was no one who cared for my soul. I cried unto You, O Lord, and said, “You are my hope, my portion in the land of the living. Attend to my supplication, for I am brought very low; deliver me from those who persecute me, for they are stronger than me. Bring my soul out of prison, that I may give thanks to Your name, O Lord. The righteous wait for me until You reward me.” ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            بِصوتي إلى الربِّ صرختُ، بِصوتي إلى الربِّ تضرَّعتُ. أسكُبُ أمامَهُ توسُّلي. أبُثُّ لديهِ ضيقي، عِندَ فناءِ رُوحي مِنِّي، وأنتَ علِمتَ سُبُلي. في الطريقِ التي أسلُكُ أخفَوا لي فخَّاً، تأمَّلتُ عنْ اليمينِ وأبصرتُ فلمْ يكنْ مَنْ يعرِفُني. ضاعَ المَهربُ مِنِّي وليسَ مَنْ يسألُ عنْ نفسي. فصرختُ إليكَ يا ربُّ وقُلتُ: أنتَ هو رجائي وحظِّي في أرضِ الأحياءِ. أنصِتْ إلى طِلبتي فإنَّني قدْ تذلَّلتُ جِداً. نجِّني مِنَ الذينَ يضطَّهِدونَني لأنَّهُم قدْ اعتزُّوا أكثرَ مِنِّي. أخرِجْ مِنَ الحبسِ نفسي، لكي أشكُرَ اسمَكَ يا ربُّ. إيَّايَ ينتظِرُ الصدِّيقونَ حتَّى تُجازيني. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 145 - Praise the Lord, O my soul...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والخامسُ والأربعونَ - سبِّحي يا نفسي الربَّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Praise the Lord, O my soul. I will praise the Lord in my life. I will sing praises to my God as long as I exist. Do not trust in the princes, nor in the children of men, in whom there is no salvation. Their spirit shall go forth, and they shall return to their earth. In that day all their thoughts shall perish.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            سبِّحي يا نفسي الربَّ، أُسبِّحُ الربَّ في حياتي وأرتِّلُ لإلهي ما دُمتُ موجوداً. لا تتَّكِلوا على الرؤساءِ ولا على بني البشرِ الذينَ ليسَ عِندَهُم خلاصٌ. تخرُجُ رُوحُهُم فيعودونَ إلى تُرابِهِم. في ذلِكَ اليومِ تهلَكُ كافَّةُ أفكارِهِم.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Blessed is he whose helper is the God of Jacob,  whose hope is in the Lord his God, who made heaven and earth, the sea and all things in them, who keeps truth forever, who executes judgment for the oppressed, who gives food to the hungry.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            طوبى لمَنْ إلهُ يعقوبَ مُعينُهُ. واتِّكالُهُ على الربِّ إلهِهِ، الذي صنعَ السماءَ والأرضَ والبحرَ وكلَّ ما فيها. الحافِظِ العدلَ إلى الدهرِ، الصانِعِ الحُكمَ للمظلومينَ، المُعطي الطعامَ للجياعِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord looses the bound; the Lord sets up the broken down. The Lord gives wisdom to the blind; the Lord loves the righteous. The Lord preserves the strangers; He accepts the orphan and widow, but He will destroy the way of sinners. The Lord shall reign forever, and your God, O Zion, from generation to generation. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الربُّ يحِلُّ المربوطينَ، الربُّ يُقيمُ الساقِطينَ. الربُّ يُحَكِّمُ العُميانَ. الربُّ يُحبُّ الصدِّيقينَ. الربُّ يحفظُ الغُرباءَ، ويعضُدُ اليتيمَ والأرملةَ. ويُبيدُ طُرُقَ الخُطاةِ. يملِكُ الربُّ إلى الدهرِ، وإلهُكِ يا صِهيوَنُ مِنْ جيلٍ إلى جيلٍ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 146 - Praise the Lord, for a psalm...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والسادسُ والأربعونَ - سبِّحوا الربَّ فإنَّ المزمورَ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Praise the Lord, for a psalm is good; let praise be sweet unto our God. The Lord builds up Jerusalem, and He will gather together the dispersed of Israel. He heals the broken-hearted, and binds up all their fractures. He numbers the multitudes of stars, and calls them all by names. Great is the Lord, and great is His strength; His understanding is infinite. The Lord lifts up the meek, but brings sinners down to the ground.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            سبِّحوا الربَّ فإنَّ المزمورَ جيِّدٌ، ولإلهِنا يلُذُّ التسبيحُ. الربُّ يبني أورُشليمَ. الربُّ يجمعُ مُتفرِّقي إسرائيلَ. الربُّ يشفي المُنكسِري القُلوبِ، ويجبُرُ جميعَ كسرِهِم. المُحصي كثرةَ الكواكِبِ، ولكافَّتِها يُعطي أسماءً. عظيمٌ هو الربُّ وعظيمةٌ هي قوَّتُهُ. ولا إحصاءَ لفهمِهِ. الربُّ يرفعُ الودعاءَ ويُذِلُّ الخُطاةَ إلى الأرضِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Begin the song to the Lord with thanksgiving; sing praises to our God on the harp, He who covers the heaven with clouds, who prepares rain for the earth, who causes grass to spring up on the mountains, and green herb for the service of men, who gives food to the cattle, and to the young ravens that call upon Him. He will not take pleasure in the strength of a horse, nor will He be well-pleased with the legs of man. The Lord will take pleasure in those who fear Him, and in those who hope in His mercy. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ابتدئوا للربِّ بالاعترافِ، رتِّلوا لإلهِنا بالقيثارةِ. الذي يُجلِّلُ السماءَ بالغَمامِ، الذي يُهيئُ للأرضِ المطرَ، الذي يُنبِتُ العُشبَ على الجِبالِ، والخُضرةَ لخِدمةِ البشرِ، ويُعطي البهائمَ طعامَها، ولِفراخِ الغِربانِ التي تدعوهُ. لا يُؤْثِرُ قوَّةَ الفرَسِ ولا يُسرُّ بِساقيِّ الرجُلِ، بلْ يُسَرُّ الربُّ بخائفيهِ وبالراجينَ رحمتَهُ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 147 - Praise the Lord, O Jerusalem...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والسابعُ والأربعونَ - سبِّحي الربَّ يا أورُشليمُ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Praise the Lord, O Jerusalem; praise your God, O Zion, for He has strengthened the bars of your gates. He has blessed your children within you. He makes your borders peaceful, and fills you with the fatness of wheat. He sends His word to the earth; His word runs swiftly. He gives snow like wool; He scatters the mist like ashes. He casts out His ice like morsels; who will be able to stand before His frost? He will send out His word, and melt them. His wind will blow, and the waters shall flow. He declares His word to Jacob, His ordinances and judgments to Israel. He has not done so with every nation, and He has not revealed to them His judgments. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            سبِّحي الربَّ يا أورُشليمُ، سبِّحي إلهَكِ يا صِهيَونُ. لأنَّهُ قدْ قوَّى مغاليقَ أبوابِكِ وبارَكَ بنيكِ فيكِ. الذي جعلَ تُخومَكِ في سلامٍ، ويملأُكِ مِنْ شحمِ الحِنطةِ. الذي يُرسِلُ كلِمتَهُ إلى الأرضِ فيُسرِعُ قولُهُ عاجِلاً جِداً. المُعطي الثلجَ كالصوفِ، المُذَرِّي الضبابَ كالرمادِ، ويُلقي الجليدَ مِثلَ الفُتاتِ. قُدامَ وجهِ برْدِهِ مَنْ يقومُ؟ يُرسِلُ كلِمتَهُ فتُذيبُهُ. تهُبُّ ريحُهُ فتَسيلُ المِياهُ. المُخبِرُ كلِمتَهُ ليعقوبَ وفرائضَهُ وأحكامَهُ لإسرائيلَ. لمْ يصنعْ هكذا بكلِّ الأممِ، وأحكامُهُ لمْ يوضِّحْها لهُم. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Role id="Introduction">
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Holy, holy, holy. A reading  from the Holy Gospel according to our teacher Saint Luke. May his blessings be with us all. Amen. 
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            قدوسٌ، قدوسٌ، قدوسٌ، فصلٌ مِنْ بِشارةِ الإنجيلِ لمُعلِّمِنا مارِ لوقا البشيرِ بركتِهِ على جميعِنا. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Role>
   
   <ns0:Role id="Reader">
      <ns0:Section expanded="true">  
         <ns0:Title>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Gospel (Luke 2:25-32)
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               الإنجيل لمعلمنا لوقا ص 2: 25-32
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Title>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               And behold, there was a man in Jerusalem, whose name was Simeon; and this man was just and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel; and the Holy Spirit was upon him. And it had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit that he would not see death before he had seen Christ the Lord. So he came by the Spirit into the temple. And when the parents brought in the Child Jesus, to do for Him according to the custom of the law, he took Him up in his arms and blessed God, and said, “Lord, now You are letting Your servant depart in peace, according to Your word; for my eyes have seen Your salvation, which You have prepared before the face of all peoples, a light for the revelation to the Gentiles, and the glory of Your people Israel.”
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وإذا إنسانٌ كانَ بأورُشليمَ اسمُهُ سِمعانُ، وهذا الإنسانُ كانَ باراً تقيَّاً مُتوقِعاً تعزيةَ إسرائيلَ، والرُّوحُ القُدُسُ كانَ عليهِ. وكانَ قدْ أُعلِمَ بوحيٍ مِنَ الرُّوحِ القُدُسِ أنَّهُ لا يرى الموتَ قبلَ أنْ يُعاينَ المسيحَ الربَّ. فأقبلَ بالرُّوحِ إلى الهيكلِ. ولمَّا دخلَ بالطفلِ يسوعَ أبواهُ ليصنعا عنهُ كما يجِبُ في الناموسِ، حملَهُ سِمعانُ على ذِراعَيهِ وبارَكَ اللهَ قائلاً: الآنَ يا سيِّدي تُطلِقُ عبدَكَ بِسلامٍ حسبَ قولِكَ، لأنَّ عينيَّ قدْ أبصرتا خلاصَكَ الذي أعددتَهُ قُدَّامَ جميعِ الشعوبِ. نوراً تجلَّى للأُممِ، ومجداً لشعبِكَ إسرائيلَ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Section>
   </ns0:Role>
   
   <ns0:Role id="Priest">
       <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲇⲟⲝⲁ ⲥⲓ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ ⲏ̀ⲙⲱⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Glory be to God forever. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            والمجْدُ للهِ دَائماً
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>      
      
      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         May the sayings of God be fulfilled in peace.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليكمُلْ قولُ اللهِ بسلامٍ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="NativityPeriod | NativityParamoun | Circumcision">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               From the Paramoun of the Nativity to the Feast of the Circumcision:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲩⲙⲁⲥⲕ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You were born and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ وُلِدتَ وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="TheophanyPeriod | TheophanyParamoun">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               From Paramoun of the Theophany until the 12th of Tobe:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲕϭⲓⲱⲙⲥ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You were baptized and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ أعتمدت وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="PaschaWeek | Pascha | FeastOfTheCross | (FuneralTune ^ FuneralPrayer) | GeneralFuneralPrayer">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               On the two Feasts of the Cross, during Holy Pascha Week, and during funerals:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲩⲁϣⲕ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You were crucified and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ صلبت وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="!ThirdProstration ^ (Joyful29thOfTheMonthRaw | PentecostPeriod | (Sundays ^ ApostlesFastToLastDayOfHathor))">
         <ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">         
         On joyful days (see note in About Menu for details):
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
<ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲕⲧⲱⲛⲕ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You have risen and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ قمت وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="Other">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               On standard days of the year and on fasting days:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲕⲓ̀ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You have come and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنَّكَ أتيتَ وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group> 
</ns0:Role>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">Litanies</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">طلبةٌ</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
         
      <ns0:Role id="Reader">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               1. Behold, I am about to stand before the just judge terrified and trembling because of my many sins. For a life spent in pleasures deserves condemnation. But repent, O my soul, so long as you dwell on this earth, for inside the grave, dust does not praise. And in death, no one remembers, neither in Hades, does anyone give thanks. Therefore arise from the slumber of laziness, and entreat the Savior, repenting and saying, “God, have mercy on me and save me.”
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               1. هوذا أنا عتيدٌ أنْ أقِفَ أمامَ الديَّانِ العادِلِ، مرعوباً ومُرتعِباً مِنْ كثرةِ ذُنوبي، لأنَّ العُمرَ المُنقضي في الملاهي يستوجِبُ الدينونةَ. لكِنْ توبي يا نفسي ما دُمتِ في الأرضِ ساكِنةً، لأنَّ التُرابَ في القبرِ لا يُسبِّحُ. وليسَ في الموتى مَنْ يذْكُرُ، ولا في الجحيمِ مَنْ يشْكُرُ. بلْ اِنهَضي مِنْ رِقادِ الكسلِ وتضرَّعي إلى المُخلِّصِّ بالتوبةِ قائلةً: اللهُمَّ ارحمْني وخلِّصْني.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Role>
                
      <ns0:Role id="People">
      <ns0:Text forceLanguage="Coptic">
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲇⲟⲝⲁ Ⲡⲁⲧⲣⲓ ⲕⲉ Ⲩⲓⲱ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲱ Ⲡⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁⲧⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجدُ للآبِ والابنِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Role>
<ns0:Role id="Reader">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               2. If life were everlasting, and this world ever-existing, you would have an excuse, O my soul. But if your wicked deeds and ugly evils were exposed before the just judge, what answer would you give while you are lying on the bed of sins, negligent in disciplining the flesh!? O Christ our God, before Your awesome seat of judgment I am terrified, and before Your council of judgment I submit, and from the light of Your divine radiance I tremble, I, the wretched and defiled, who lies on my bed, negligent in my life. But I take example of the publican, beating my chest and saying, “O God, forgive me and have mercy on me, a sinner.”
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               2. لو كانَ العُمرُ ثابِتاً وهذا العالمُ مُؤبَّداً، لكانَ لكِ يا نفسي حُجَّةٌ واضِحةٌ، لكِنْ إذا انكشفتْ أفعالُكِ الرديئةُ وشُرورُكِ القبيحةُ أمامَ الديَّانِ العادِلِ، فأيَّ جوابٍ تُجيبينَ وأنتِ على سريرِ الخطايا مُنطرِحةً، وفى إخضاعِ الجسدِ مُتهاوِنةً؟ أيها المسيحُ إلهُنا لكُرسي حُكمِكَ المرهوبِ أفزعُ، ولمجلِسِ دينونتِكَ أخشعُ، ولنورِ شُعاعِ لاهوتِكَ أجزعُ، أنا الشقيُّ المُتدنِّسُ، الراقِدُ على فِراشي المُتهاوِنُ في حياتي. لكنِّي أتخِذُ صورةَ العشَّارِ قارِعاً صدري، قائلاً: اللهُمَّ اغفرْ لي فإنِّي خاطئٌ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Role>
            
      <ns0:Role id="People">
      <ns0:Text forceLanguage="Coptic">
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲕⲉ ⲛⲩⲛ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲓ̀ ⲕⲉ ⲓⲥ ⲧⲟⲩⲥ ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲁⲥ ⲧⲱⲛ ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲱⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.         
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.      
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Role>
<ns0:Role id="Reader">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               3. O holy Virgin, overshadow your servant with your instant help, and keep the waves of evil thoughts away from me, and raise up my ailing soul for prayer and vigil, for it has gone into a deep sleep. For you are a capable, compassionate and helpful mother, the bearer of the fountain of life, my King and my God, Jesus Christ, my hope.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               3. أيتها العذراءُ الطاهِرةُ أسبِلي ظِلَّكِ السريعَ المعونةِ على عبدِكِ. وابعِدي أمواجَ الأفكارِ الرديئةِ عنِّي. وانهِضي نفسي المريضةَ للصلاةِ والسهرِ، لأنَّها استغْرَقَتْ في سُباتٍ عميقٍ. فإنَّكِ أمٌ قادِرةٌ رحيمةٌ مُعينةٌ، والِدةُ يُنبوعِ الحياةِ، ملِكي وإلهي، يسوعَ المسيحِ رجائي.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Role>
   </ns0:Section>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">Graciously Accord, O Lord</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">تَفضَّلْ يا ربُّ</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
      
      <ns0:Text>      
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲁⲣⲓⲕⲁⲧⲁⲝⲓⲟⲓⲛ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲕⲁ̀ⲣⲉϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲁⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉⲛⲟⲓ ⲛ̀ⲁⲑⲛⲟⲃⲓ: ⲕ̀ⲥ̀ⲙⲁⲣⲱⲟⲩⲧ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲫϯ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲉⲛⲓⲟϯ: ⲕ̀ⲉⲣϩⲟⲩⲟ̀ ⲥ̀ⲙⲁⲣⲱⲟⲩⲧ ϥ̀ⲙⲉϩ ⲛ̀ⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">            
            Graciously accord, O Lord, to keep us this night without sin. Blessed are You, O Lord, God of our fathers, and exceedingly blessed and glorified be Your name forever. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            تَفضَّلْ يا ربُّ أنْ تَحْفَظَنا في هَذهِ الليلةِ بِغَيرِ خَطيئةٍ. مُبارَكٌ أَنْتَ أيُّها الرَّبُّ إلهُ آبائِنا، ومُتَزايدٌ بَرَكةً، واسْمُكَ القُدّوسُ مَمْلوءٌ مَجْداً إلى الأبَدِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>  
      
      <ns0:Text>      
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥϣⲱⲡⲓ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲛⲁⲓ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲛⲉⲣϩⲉⲗⲡⲓⲥ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ: ϫⲉ ⲛⲉⲛⲃⲁⲗ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲟⲛ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲥⲉⲉⲣϩⲉⲗⲡⲓⲥ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ ϫⲉ ⲛ̀ⲑⲟⲕ ⲉⲑⲛⲁϯ ⲛ̀ⲧⲟⲩϧ̀ⲣⲉ ⲛⲱⲟⲩ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡ̀ⲥⲏⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲏⲓⲥ. Ⲥⲱⲧⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ Ⲫϯ Ⲡⲉⲛⲥ̅ⲱ̅ⲣ̅ ϯϩⲉⲗⲡⲓⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲁⲩⲣⲏϫϥ ⲙ̀ⲡ̀ⲕⲁϩⲓ ⲧⲏⲣϥ. Ⲛⲑⲟⲕ ⲇⲉ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲁ̀ⲣⲉϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲩϫⲟⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲓⲧⲟⲧϥ ⲙ̀ⲡⲁⲓϫⲱⲟⲩ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ  ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.            
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">            
            Let Your mercy, O Lord, be upon us, according to our hope in You, for the eyes of everyone wait upon You, for You give them their food in due season. Hear us, O God our Savior, the hope of all the regions of the earth. And You, O Lord, keep us safe from this generation and forever. Amen.            
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            فَلْتكُنْ رَحمَتُكَ عَليْنا يا ربُّ كَمِثْلِ اتِّكالِنا عَليْكَ. لأنَّ أعْيُنَ الكُلِّ تَترَجّاكَ. لأنَّكَ أنْتَ الَّذي تُعْطيهِم طَعامَهُم في حينِهِ. اسْمَعنا يا اللَّهُ مُخلِّصُنا. يا رَجاءَ أقْطارِ الأرْضِ كُلِّها. وأنْتَ يا رَبُّ تَحْفظُنا وتُنَجِّينا، مِنْ هَذا الجيلِ وإلى الأبَدِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
      
      <ns0:Text>      
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲕⲥ̀ⲙⲁⲣⲱⲟⲩⲧ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲙⲁⲧ̀ⲥⲁⲃⲟⲓ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉⲕⲙⲉⲑⲙⲏⲓ: ⲕ̀ⲥ̀ⲙⲁⲣⲱⲟⲩⲧ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲙⲁⲕⲁϯ ⲛⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉⲕⲙⲉⲑⲙⲏⲓ: ⲕ̀ⲥ̀ ⲙⲁⲣⲱⲟⲩⲧ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲙⲁⲫ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ ⲛⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉⲕⲙⲉⲑⲙⲏⲓ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Blessed are You, O Lord; teach me Your statutes. Blessed are You, O Lord; make me to understand Your commandments. Blessed are You, O Lord; enlighten me with Your righteousness.            
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            مُبارَكٌ أنْتَ يا ربُّ عَلِّمْني عَدْلَكَ. مُبارَكٌ أنْتَ يا ربُّ فَهِّمْني حُقوقَكَ. مُبارَكٌ أنْتَ يا ربُّ أنِرْ لي بِرَّكَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
      
      <ns0:Text>      
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">            
            Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲡⲉⲕⲛⲁⲓ ϣⲟⲡ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ: ⲛⲓϩ̀ⲃⲏⲟⲩⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲉⲕϫⲓϫ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲭⲁⲩ ⲛ̀ⲥⲱⲕ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲕϣⲱⲡⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲙⲁⲙ̀ⲫⲱⲧ ⲓⲥϫⲉⲛ ϫⲱⲟⲩ ϣⲁ ϫⲱⲟⲩ. Ⲁⲛⲟⲕ ⲁⲓϫⲟⲥ ϫⲉ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲏⲓ: ⲙⲁⲧⲟⲩϫⲟ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲯⲩⲭⲏ ϫⲉ ⲁⲓⲉⲣⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ: Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲁⲓⲫⲱⲧ ϩⲁⲣⲟⲕ: ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲧ ⲙⲁⲧ̀ⲥⲁⲃⲟⲓ ⲉ̀ⲓ̀ⲣⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲧⲉϩⲛⲁⲕ ϫⲉ ⲛ̀ⲑⲟⲕ ⲡⲉ Ⲡⲁⲛⲟⲩϯ: ⲥ̀ⲭⲏ ϧⲁⲧⲟⲧⲕ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ϯⲙⲟⲩⲙⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡ̀ⲱⲛϧ: ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲉⲕⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲉⲛⲉ̀ⲛⲁⲩ ⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ: ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲛⲁⲓ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉⲧⲥⲱⲟⲩⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲑⲙⲏⲓ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉⲧⲥⲟⲩⲧⲱⲛ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲟⲩϩⲏⲧ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Your mercy, O Lord, endures forever. Despise not, O Lord, the works of Your hands. You have been my refuge from generation to generation. I asked the Lord and said, "Have mercy on me; heal my soul, for I have sinned against You." Lord, I have fled unto You, save me, and teach me to do Your will, for You are my God, and with You is the fountain of life. In Your light, shall we see light. Let Your mercy come unto those who know You and Your righteousness unto the upright in heart.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يا ربُّ رَحْمَتُكَ دائِمَةٌ إلى الأبَدِ. أعْمالُ يَديْكَ يا ربُّ لا تَرفُضْها. لأنَّكَ يا ربُّ صِرْتَ لي مَلجأً مِنْ جيلٍ إلى جيلٍ. أَنا طَلبْتُ الرَّبَّ وقُلْتُ: ارْحَمْني وخَلِّصْ نَفْسي، فإنّي أخْطَأتُ إليكَ. يا ربُّ الْتَجأتُ إليكَ فَخلِّصْني، وعَلِّمْني أنْ أصْنَعَ مَشيئتَكَ، لأنَّكَ أنْتَ هُوَ إلَهي، وعِنْدَكَ يُنْبوعُ الْحَياةِ، وبِنورِكَ يا ربُّ نُعاينُ النّورَ. فلْتَأتِ رَحْمتُكَ للَّذينَ يَعْرِفونَكَ، وبِرُّكَ للْمُسْتقيمي القُلوبِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
      
      <ns0:Text>    
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ϥⲉⲣϣⲁⲩ ⲛⲁⲕ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲓⲥ̀ⲙⲟⲩ: ϥ̀ⲉⲣϣⲁⲩ ⲛⲁⲕ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲓϩⲱⲥ: ϥ̀ⲉⲣⲡ̀ⲣⲉⲡⲓ ⲛⲁⲕ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ: Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̅ⲛ̅ⲁ̅ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅: ⲫⲏⲉⲧϣⲟⲡ ⲓⲥϫⲉⲛ ϩⲏ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯⲛⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲓⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ  ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
         </ns0:Language>  
         <ns0:Language id="English">            
            To You belongs blessing. To You belongs praise. To You belongs glory, O Father, Son and Holy Spirit, existing from the beginning, now, and forever and ever. Amen.            
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لَكَ تجِبُ البَركَةُ. لَكَ يَحِقُّ التَّسْبيحُ. لَكَ يَنْبغي التَّمْجيدُ، أيُّها الآبُ، والابْنُ، والرُّوحُ القُدُسُ، الكائِنُ منْذُ البَدْءِ، والآنَ وإلى أبَدِ الأبَدِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
      
      <ns0:Text>      
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲛⲁⲛⲉ ⲟⲩⲱⲛϩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲉ̀ⲉⲣⲯⲁⲗⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ ⲡⲉⲧϭⲟⲥⲓ: ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ϫⲓⲛⲫⲓⲣⲓ ⲉ̀ⲡⲉⲕⲛⲁⲓ ⲛ̀ϩⲁⲛⲁ̀ⲧⲟⲟⲩⲓ̀ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲑⲙⲏⲓ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲣϩ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">            
            It is good to give thanks to the Lord, and to sing praises unto Your name, O Most High; to show forth Your mercy every morning, and Your righteousness every night.            
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            جَيِّدٌ هُوَ الاعْتِرافُ للرَّبِّ، والتَّرْتيلُ لاسْمِكَ أيُّها العَلُّيُّ. أنْ يُخْبَرَ برَحْمتِكَ في الغَدَواتِ، وحَقِّكَ في كُلِّ لَيلةٍ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Trisagion</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">الثلاث تقديسات</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ...</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲓⲥⲭⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲁ̀ⲑⲁⲛⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲟ̀ ⲉⲕ ⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲩ ⲅⲉⲛⲛⲉⲑⲏⲥ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, who was born of the Virgin, have mercy upon us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         قُدّوسٌ اللَّهُ، قُدّوسٌ القَويُّ، قُدّوسٌ الحَيُّ الَّذي لا يَموتُ، الَّذي وُلِدَ مِنَ العَذْراءِ ارحَمْنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲓⲥⲭⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲁ̀ⲑⲁⲛⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲟ̀ ⲥ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲣⲱⲑⲓⲥ ⲇⲓ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ: ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, who was crucified for us, have mercy upon us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         قُدّوسٌ اللَّهُ، قُدّوسٌ القَويُّ، قُدّوسٌ الحَيُّ الَّذي لا يَموتُ، الَّذي صُلِبَ عنّا ارحَمْنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲓⲥⲭⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲁ̀ⲑⲁⲛⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲟ̀ ⲁ̀ⲛⲁⲥⲧⲁⲥ ⲉⲕ ⲧⲱⲛ ⲛⲉⲕⲣⲱⲛ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲛⲉⲗⲑⲱⲛ ⲓⲥ ⲧⲟⲩⲥ ⲟⲩⲣⲁⲛⲟⲥ: ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, who rose from the dead and ascended into the heavens, have mercy upon us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         قُدّوسٌ اللَّهُ، قُدّوسٌ القَويُّ، قُدّوسٌ الحَيُّ الَّذي لا يَموتُ، الَّذي قامَ مِنَ الأمْواتِ، وصَعِدَ إلى السَّماواتِ ارحَمْنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲇⲟⲝⲁ Ⲡⲁⲧⲣⲓ ⲕⲉ Ⲩⲓⲱ: ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲱ Ⲡⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁⲧⲓ: ⲕⲉ ⲛⲩⲛ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲓ̀ ⲕⲉ ⲓⲥⲧⲟⲩⲥ: ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲁⲥ ⲧⲱⲛ ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲱⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit. Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجْدُ للآبِ والابن والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، الآنَ وكلَّ أَوانٍ وإلى دَهْرِ الدّهورِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>   
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲁ ⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ: ⲡⲁⲛⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲁ ⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ: ϯⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا، أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا، أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲡⲁⲣⲁⲡⲧⲱⲙⲁ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Lord, forgive us our sins. O Lord, forgive us our iniquities. O Lord, forgive us our trespasses.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا خَطايانا، ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا آثامَنا، ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا زَلاّتِنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ϫⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲓⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉⲧϣⲱⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲗⲁⲟⲥ: ⲙⲁⲧⲁⲗϭⲱⲟⲩ ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅: ⲛⲉⲛⲓⲟϯ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲉⲛⲥ̀ⲛⲏⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲉⲛⲕⲟⲧ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲙⲁⲙ̀ⲧⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲛⲟⲩⲯⲩⲭⲏ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Lord, visit the sick of Your people, heal them for the sake of Your holy name. Our fathers and brethren who have fallen asleep, O Lord, repose their souls.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ياربُّ افْتَقدْ مَرْضَى شَعْبِكَ. اشْفِهمْ مِنْ أجْلِ اسْمِكَ القُدُّوسِ. آباؤُنا وإخْوَتُنا الَّذينَ رَقدوا ياربُّ نَيِّحْ نُفوسَهُم.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲓⲁⲑⲛⲟⲃⲓ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲡⲓⲁⲑⲛⲟⲃⲓ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲁ̀ⲣⲓⲃⲟⲏ̀ⲑⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ ϣⲉⲡ ⲡⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O You who are without sin, Lord, have mercy on us. O You who are without sin, Lord, help us and receive our supplications.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         يا مَنْ هُوَ بِلا خَطيئَةٍ ياربُّ ارحَمْنا. يا الَّذي بِلا خَطيئَةٍ ياربُّ أَعِنّا واقْبَلْ طَلباتِنا إليكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ ⲫⲱⲕ ⲡⲉ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲁ̀ⲙⲁϩⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ: Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲩⲗⲟⲅⲏⲥⲟⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.            
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         For Yours is the glory, the dominion, and triple holiness. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord bless us. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         لأنَّ لَكَ المجْدَ والعِزَّةَ والتَّقْديسَ المثلَّثَ، ياربُّ ارحَمْ، ياربُّ ارْحَمْ، ياربُّ بارِكْ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>   
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Our Father</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">أبانا الذي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲧⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲁ ⲛ̀ϫⲟⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Make us worthy to pray thankfully:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اللهُمَّ اجعلْنا مُستحقينَ أن نقولَ بشكرٍ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ Ⲡⲉⲛⲓⲱⲧ ⲉⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be Thy name.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أبانا الذي في السماواتِ ليتقدسِ اسمُكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲥⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ: ⲡⲉⲧⲉϩⲛⲁⲕ ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥϣⲱⲡⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲕⲁϩⲓ:  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Thy kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليأتِ ملكوتُكَ، لتكُن مشيئتُكَ، كما في السماءِ كذلكَ على الأرضِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲓⲕ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲣⲁⲥϯ ⲙⲏⲓϥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲫⲟⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲣⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Give us this day our daily bread and forgive us our trespasses, as we forgive those who trespass against us and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         خبزَنا الذي للغدِّ أعطِنا اليومَ، واغفِرْ لنا ذنوبَنا كما نغفِرُ نحنُ أيضاً للمُذنبينَ إلينا، ولا تُدخِلنا في تجرِبةٍ لكِنْ نجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ: ϫⲉ ⲑⲱⲕ ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In Christ Jesus our Lord. For Thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, forever. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِّنا. لأنَّ لكَ المُلكَ والقوةَ والمجدَ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Hail to You</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">السّلامُ لَكِ...</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
      
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲛⲉ ⲧⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟ: ⲱ̀ ⲑⲏⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅ ⲉⲑⲙⲉϩ ⲛ̀ⲱ̀ⲟⲩ: ⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲛ̀ⲥⲏⲟⲩ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ϯⲙⲁⲥⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲑ̀ⲙⲁⲩ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Hail to you. We ask you, O saint, full of glory, the ever-virgin, the Theotokos, the Mother of Christ,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         السَّلامُ لَكِ، نَسْألُكِ أيَّتُها القِدّيسَةُ الممْتَلِئةُ مَجْداً، العَذْراءُ كلَّ حينٍ، والِدةُ الإلَهِ، أمُّ المسيحِ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲛⲓⲟⲩⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲉⲩⲭⲏ: ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ϣⲱⲓ ϩⲁ ⲡⲉϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲉⲛⲣⲓⲧ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Lift up our prayers unto your beloved Son, that He may forgive us our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اصْعدي صَلَواتِنا إلى ابْنِكِ الحَبيبِ، ليغْفِرَ لَنا خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲑⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲥⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ: ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Hail to the holy Virgin, who has brought forth unto us the true Light, Christ our God.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         السَّلامُ لِلَّتي وَلَدَتْ لَنا النّورَ الحَقيقيَّ المسيحَ إلَهَنا. العَذْراءُ القدّيسَةُ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁϯϩⲟ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲉⲣⲟⲩⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲉⲛⲯⲩⲭⲏ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Ask the Lord on our behalf, that He may have mercy on our souls, and forgive us our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اسْألي الرَّبَّ عنّا ليَصْنَعَ رَحْمَةً مَعَ نُفوسِنا، ويغفِرَ لَنا خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ Ⲙⲁⲣⲓⲁⲙ: ϯⲑⲉⲟ̀ⲧⲟⲕⲟⲥ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅: ϯⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲧⲁⲧⲏⲥ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲛϩⲟⲧ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡ̀ⲅⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲣⲱⲙⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Virgin Mary, the holy Theotokos, the faithful advocate for all mankind,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أيَّتُها العَذْراءُ مَرْيَمُ والِدةُ الإلهِ، القِدّيسَةُ الشَّفيعَةُ الأمينَةُ لجنْسِ البَشرِيّةِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲡ̀ⲣⲉⲥⲃⲉⲩⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅ ⲫⲏⲉⲧⲁⲣⲉϫ̀ⲫⲟϥ: ϩⲟⲡⲱⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲉⲣϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Intercede on our behalf before Christ whom you bore, that He may grant us the forgiveness of our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اشْفَعي فينا أَمامَ المَسيحِ الَّذي وَلدْتِهِ، لِكَيْ يُنْعِمَ لنا بغُفْرانِ خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲛⲉ ⲱ̀ ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ: ϯⲟⲩⲣⲱ ⲙ̀ⲙⲏⲓ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲗⲏⲑⲓⲛⲏ: ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲡ̀ϣⲟⲩϣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲅⲉⲛⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲣⲉϫ̀ⲫⲟ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲛ̀Ⲉⲙⲙⲁⲛⲟⲩⲏⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Hail to you, O Virgin, / the right and true Queen. / Hail to the pride of our race / who bore to us Immanuel.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         السَّلامُ لكِ أيَّتُها العَذْراءُ الملكةُ الحقيقيَّةُ الحقانِيَّةُ السَّلامُ لفَخرِ جِنسِنا ولدْتِ لنا عِمَّانوئيلَ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲁ̀ⲣⲓⲡⲉⲛⲙⲉⲩⲓ̀: ⲱ̀ ϯⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲧⲁⲧⲏⲥ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲛϩⲟⲧ: ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲉⲛⲟ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲓⲏ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We ask you to remember us, / O our faithful advocate, / before our Lord Jesus Christ / that He may forgive us our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نسألُكِ أن تَذكُرينا أيَّتُها الشفيعةُ المؤتمنةُ أمامَ ربِّنا يسوعَ المسيحِ ليغفِرَ لنا خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">     
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Introduction to the Creed</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">بدء قانون الإيمان</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>      
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϭⲓⲥⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟ ⲑ̀ⲙⲁⲩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: ⲧⲉⲛϯⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲉ ⲱ̀ ⲑⲏⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁⲥⲛⲟⲩϯ: ϫⲉ ⲁ̀ⲣⲉⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲡ̀ⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲕⲟⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲧⲏⲣϥ: ⲁϥⲓ̀ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁϥⲥⲱϯ ⲛ̀ⲛⲉⲛⲯⲩⲭⲏ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We exalt you, the Mother of the true Light. We glorify you, O saint, the Theotokos, for you have brought forth unto us the Savior of the whole world; He came and saved our souls. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نُعظِّمُكِ يا أمَّ النُّورِ الحَقيقيِّ. ونُمجِّدُكِ أيَّتُها العَذْراءُ القِدّيسةُ والِدةُ الإلهِ. لأنَّكِ وَلدْتِ لَنا مُخلِّصَ العالَمِ. أتَى وخَلَّصَ نُفُوسَنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>      
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲟⲩⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲁⲕ ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲏⲃ ⲡⲉⲛⲟⲩⲣⲟ Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅: ⲡ̀ϣⲟⲩϣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲁ̀ⲡⲟⲥⲧⲟⲗⲟⲥ: ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲗⲟⲙ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲙⲁⲣⲧⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲡ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲇⲓⲕⲉⲟⲥ: ⲡ̀ⲧⲁϫⲣⲟ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲉ̀ⲕⲕ̀ⲗⲏⲥⲓⲁ: ⲡ̀ⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲛⲟⲃⲓ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory be to You, our Master, our King, Christ, the pride of the apostles, the crown of the martyrs, the joy of the righteous, the firmness of the churches, the forgiveness of sins.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجْدُ لكَ يا سَيِّدَنا ومَلِكَنا المسيحَ: فَخْرَ الرُّسُلِ، إكْليلَ الشُهداءِ، تَهْليلَ الصِدّيقينَ، ثَباتَ الكَنائسِ، غُفْرانَ الخَطايا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>      
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲧⲉⲛϩⲓⲱⲓϣ ⲛ̀ϯⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ⲉⲥϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲙⲉⲑⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ: ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲥ: ⲧⲉⲛϯⲱⲟⲩ ⲛⲁⲥ. Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ: Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ: Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲩⲗⲟⲅⲏⲥⲟⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We proclaim the Holy Trinity in one Godhead. We worship Him. We glorify Him. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord bless us. Amen.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نُبشِّرُ بالثَّالوثِ القُدُّوسِ: لاهوتٌ واحِدٌ. نَسجُدُ لهُ ونُمجِّدُهُ. ياربُّ ارحَمْ، ياربُّ ارحَمْ، ياربُّ بارِكْ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">      
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">The Orthodox Creed</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">قانون الإيمان المقدس الأرثوذكسي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
         
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛⲛⲁϩϯ ⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ: Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲡⲓⲡⲁⲛⲧⲟⲕⲣⲁⲧⲱⲣ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁϥⲑⲁⲙⲓⲟ ⲛ̀ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡ̀ⲕⲁϩⲓ: ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲩⲛⲁⲩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛ̀ⲥⲉⲛⲁⲩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ ⲁⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We believe in one God, God the Father, the Pantocrator, Creator of heaven and earth, and of all things seen and unseen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نؤمنُ بإلهٍ واحدٍ اللهِ الآبِ ضابطِ الكلِ خالقِ السماءِ والأرضِ. ما يُرَى وما لا يُرَى
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛⲛⲁϩϯ ⲉ̀ⲟⲩϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲡϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲙ̀Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲡⲓⲙⲟⲛⲟⲅⲉⲛⲏⲥ: ⲡⲓⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ϧⲁϫⲱⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲉ̀ⲱⲛ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We believe in one Lord, Jesus Christ, the only-begotten Son of God, begotten of the Father before all ages.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نؤمنُ بربٍ واحدٍ يسوعَ، المسيحِ، ابنِ اللهِ الوحيدِ المولودِ مِنَ الآبِ قبلَ كلِّ الدهورِ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲟⲩⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ: ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: ⲟⲩⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲡⲉ ⲟⲩⲑⲁⲙⲓⲟ ⲁⲛ ⲡⲉ ⲟⲩⲟ̀ⲙⲟⲟⲩⲥⲓⲟⲥ ⲡⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ϣⲱⲡⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲓⲧⲟⲧϥ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Light of Light, true God of true God; begotten, not created; of one essence with the Father; by whom all things were made.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نورٍ مِنْ نورٍ إلهِ حقٍ مِنْ إلهِ حقٍ، مولودٍ غيرِ مخلوقٍ، مساوٍ للآبِ في الجوهرِ الذي بِهِ كانَ كلُّ شيءٍ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲉⲑⲃⲏⲧⲉⲛ ⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲛ ϧⲁ ⲛⲓⲣⲱⲙⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲟⲩϫⲁⲓ: ⲁϥⲓ̀ ⲉ̀ⲡⲉⲥⲏⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ: ⲁϥϭⲓⲥⲁⲣⲝ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲙⲁⲣⲓⲁ ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁϥⲉⲣⲣⲱⲙⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Who for us men and for our salvation came down from heaven, was incarnate of the Holy Spirit and of the Virgin Mary, and became man.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         هذا الذي مِنْ أجلِنا نحنُ البشرَ ومِنْ أجلِ خلاصِنا نزِلَ مِنَ السماءِ وتجسدَ مِنَ الرّوحِ القُدُسِ ومِنْ مريمَ العذراءِ وتأنسَ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="CovenantThursday | JoyousSaturday">
         <ns0:Group>            
            <ns0:Season id="JoyousSaturday">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲣⲱⲛⲓⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟϥ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲟⲛⲧⲓⲟⲥ Ⲡⲓⲗⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲁϥϣⲉⲡⲉⲙⲕⲁϩ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲕⲟⲥϥ. 
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     And He was crucified for us under Pontius Pilate, suffered and was buried;  
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وصُلِبَ عنَّا على عهدِ بيلاطسَ البُنطيِّ، تألّمَ وقُبِرَ
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
         </ns0:Group>
         
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Skip to “Yes, we believe in the Holy Spirit...” 
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="Other">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲣⲱⲛⲓⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟϥ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲟⲛⲧⲓⲟⲥ Ⲡⲓⲗⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲁϥϣⲉⲡⲉⲙⲕⲁϩ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲕⲟⲥϥ. Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁϥⲧⲱⲛϥ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲏⲉⲑⲙⲱⲟⲩⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁϩϣⲟⲙⲧ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ⲛⲓⲅ̀ⲣⲁⲫⲏ. 
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               And He was crucified for us under Pontius Pilate, suffered and was buried, and on the third day He rose from the dead according to the Scriptures. 
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وصُلِبَ عنَّا على عهدِ بيلاطسَ البُنطيِّ، تألّمَ وقُبِرَ وقامَ مِنْ بينِ الأمواتِ في اليومِ الثالثِ كما في الكتبِ
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲁϥϣⲉⲛⲁϥ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ϣⲱⲓ ⲉ̀ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲁϥϩⲉⲙⲥⲓ ⲥⲁⲟⲩⲓⲛⲁⲙ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉϥⲓⲱⲧ. Ⲕⲉ ⲡⲁⲗⲓⲛ ϥ̀ⲛⲏⲟⲩ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲉϥⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ϯϩⲁⲡ ⲉ̀ⲛⲏⲉⲧⲟⲛϧ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉⲑⲙⲱⲟⲩⲧ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲧⲉϥⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲟⲩⲁⲑⲙⲟⲩⲛⲕ ⲧⲉ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Ascended into the heavens; He sits at the right hand of His Father, and He is coming again in His glory to judge the living and the dead, whose kingdom shall have no end.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وصَعِدَ إلى السماواتِ وجلسَ عن يمينِ أبيهِ وأيضاً يأتي في مجدِهِ ليُدينَ الأحياءَ والأمواتَ الذي ليسَ لمُلكِهِ انقضاءٌ
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲥⲉ ⲧⲉⲛⲛⲁϩϯ ⲉ̀Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲛ̀ⲣⲉϥϯ ⲙ̀ⲡ̀ⲱⲛϧ: ⲫⲏⲉⲑⲛⲏⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲫ̀ⲓⲱⲧ: ⲥⲉⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟϥ ⲥⲉϯ ⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲁϥ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡϣⲏⲣⲓ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁϥⲥⲁϫⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲫⲏⲧⲏⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Yes, we believe in the Holy Spirit, the Lord, the Giver of Life, who proceeds from the Father, who with the Father and the Son, is worshiped and glorified, who spoke by the prophets.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نَعَم نؤمنُ بالرّوحِ القُدُسِ الربِّ المحيي المنبثقِ مِنَ الآبِ، نسجدُ لهُ ونمجدُهُ معَ الآبِ والابنِ الناطقِ في الأنبياءِ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲉⲟⲩⲓ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲁ ⲛ̀ⲕⲁⲑⲟⲗⲓⲕⲏ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲡⲟⲥⲧⲟⲗⲓⲕⲏ ⲛ̀ⲉⲕⲕ̀ⲗⲏⲥⲓⲁ̀. Ⲧⲉⲛⲉⲣⲟ̀ⲙⲟⲗⲟⲅⲓⲛ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲙⲥ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲛⲟⲃⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         And in one holy, catholic (universal), and apostolic Church. We confess one baptism, for the remission of sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وبكنيسةٍ واحدةٍ مُقدسَةٍ جامعةٍ رسوليةٍ. ونعترفُ بمعموديةٍ واحدةٍ لمغفِرةِ الخطايا
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>         
      <ns0:Season id="(FuneralTune ^ FuneralPrayer) | GeneralFuneralPrayer">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               The last verse is chanted in the “Golgotha” tune:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="Other">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               The people chant the last sentence in a loud voice.
            </ns0:Language>         
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               ثم يقول الشعب جهراً هذه الجملة الأخيرة مِنْ قانون الإيمان، وهي:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϫⲟⲩϣⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϧⲁⲧ̀ϩⲏ ⲛ̀ϯⲁ̀ⲛⲁⲥⲧⲁⲥⲓⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲣⲉϥⲙⲱⲟⲩⲧ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱⲛϧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲓⲉ̀ⲱⲛ ⲉⲑⲛⲏⲟⲩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We look for the resurrection of the dead, and the life of the age to come. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وننتظرُ قيامةَ الأمواتِ، وحياةَ الدهرِ الآتي. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Role id="Priest">
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord hear us and have mercy on us and forgive us our sins. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ياربُّ اسمَعْنا وارحَمْنا واغفِرْ لنا خطايانا. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Role>
<ns0:Text forceLanguage="Coptic">
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ (ⲙ̅ⲁ̅)
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Lord have mercy (41)          
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ياربُّ ارحَمْ (41)
      </ns0:Language>   
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">Holy, Holy, Holy</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Holy, holy, holy, Lord of Sabaoth. Heaven and earth are full of Your glory and honor. Have mercy on us, O God the Father, the Pantocrator. O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Lord, God of hosts, be with us. For we have no helper in our hardships and tribulations but You. Absolve, forgive, and remit, O God, our transgressions; those which we have committed willingly and those which we have committed unwillingly, those which we have committed knowingly and those which we have committed unknowingly, the hidden and the manifest, O Lord forgive us, for the sake of Your holy name which is called upon us. Let it be according to Your mercy, O Lord, and not according to our sins.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ، ربُّ الصباؤوتِ. السماءُ والأرضُ مملوءتانِ مِنْ مجدِكَ وكرامتِكَ. ارحَمْنا يا اللهُ الآبُ ضابطُ الكلِّ. أيها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا. أيها الربُّ إلهُ القواتِ كُن معنا، لأنَّهُ ليسَ لنا مُعينٌ في شدائدِنا وضيقاتِنا سِواكَ. حلِّ واغفِرْ واصفحْ لنا يا اللهُ عَن سيئاتِنا، التي صنعناها بإرادتِنا والتي صنعناها بغيرِ إرادتِنا، التي فعلناها بمعرفةٍ والتي فعلناها بغيرِ معرفةٍ، الخفيةِ والظاهرةِ. ياربُّ اغفِرْها لنا، مِنْ أجلِ اسمِكَ القُدُّوسِ الذي دُعِيَ علينا. كرحمتِكَ ياربُّ وليسَ كخطايانا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Our Father</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">أبانا الذي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲧⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲁ ⲛ̀ϫⲟⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Make us worthy to pray thankfully:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اللهُمَّ اجعلْنا مُستحقينَ أن نقولَ بشكرٍ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ Ⲡⲉⲛⲓⲱⲧ ⲉⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be Thy name.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أبانا الذي في السماواتِ ليتقدسِ اسمُكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲥⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ: ⲡⲉⲧⲉϩⲛⲁⲕ ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥϣⲱⲡⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲕⲁϩⲓ:  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Thy kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليأتِ ملكوتُكَ، لتكُن مشيئتُكَ، كما في السماءِ كذلكَ على الأرضِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲓⲕ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲣⲁⲥϯ ⲙⲏⲓϥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲫⲟⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲣⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Give us this day our daily bread and forgive us our trespasses, as we forgive those who trespass against us and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         خبزَنا الذي للغدِّ أعطِنا اليومَ، واغفِرْ لنا ذنوبَنا كما نغفِرُ نحنُ أيضاً للمُذنبينَ إلينا، ولا تُدخِلنا في تجرِبةٍ لكِنْ نجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ: ϫⲉ ⲑⲱⲕ ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In Christ Jesus our Lord. For Thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, forever. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِّنا. لأنَّ لكَ المُلكَ والقوةَ والمجدَ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">   
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Absolution
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            التحليلُ
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Lord, all our sins which we committed against You in this day, whether in deeds or in words or in thoughts or through all senses, please remit and forgive us, for the sake of Your holy name, as You are Good and Lover of Mankind. God, grant us a peaceful night and a sleep free from all anxiety. And send us an angel of peace to protect us from every evil, and every affliction, and every temptation of the enemy; through the grace, compassion and love of mankind of Your only-begotten Son, our Lord, God and Savior Jesus Christ, to whom is due, with You and with the Holy Spirit, the Life-Giver who is of one essence with You, all glory, honor and dominion. Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يا ربُّ جميعُ ما أخطأنا بهِ إلَيكَ في هذا اليومِ، إنْ كانَ بالفِعلِ أو بالقولِ أو بالفِكرِ أو بجميعِ الحواسِّ، فاصفحْ واغفِرْ لنا مِنْ أجلِ اسمِكَ القُدُّوسِ، كصالِحٍ ومُحِبٍّ للبشرِ. وانعِمْ علينا اللهُمَّ بليلةٍ سالِمةٍ، وبهذا النومِ طاهِراً مِنْ كلِّ قلقٍ. وارسِلْ لنا ملاكَ السلامةِ ليحرُسَنا مِنْ كلِّ شرٍ، ومِنْ كلِّ ضربةٍ، ومِنْ كلِّ تجرِبةِ العدوِّ. بالنعمةِ والرأفاتِ ومحبةِ البشرِ اللواتي لابنِكَ الوحيدِ ربِّنا وإلهِنا ومُخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ. هذا الذي مِنْ قِبَلِهِ يليقُ بِكَ معهُ المجدُ والإكرامُ والعِزَّةُ. معَ الرُّوحِ القُدُسِ المُحيي المُساوي لكَ، الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
         
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">Conclusion of Every Hour</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">طلبةٌ تقالُ آخرَ كلِّ ساعةٍٍ</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Have mercy on us, O God, and have mercy on us, who at all times and in every hour, in heaven and on earth, is worshipped and glorified; Christ our God, the good, the long suffering, the abundant in mercy, and the great in compassion, who loves the righteous and has mercy on the sinners of whom I am chief, who does not wish the death of the sinner but rather that he returns and lives, who calls all to salvation for the promise of the good things to come.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ارحَمْنا يا اللهُ ثمَّ ارحَمْنا، يا مَنْ في كلِّ وقتٍ وكلِّ ساعةٍ، في السماءِ وعلى الأرضِ، مسجودٌ لهُ ومُمجَّدٌ. المسيحُ إلهُنا الصالحُ، الطويلُ الرّوحِ، الكثيرُ الرحمةِ، الجزيلُ التحننِ، الذي يحبُّ الصديقينَ ويرحمُ الخطاةَ الذينَ أوَّلُهُم أنا. الذي لا يشاءُ موتَ الخاطئِ مثلَ ما يرجعُ ويحيا. الدَّاعي الكلَّ إلى الخلاصِ لأجلِ الموعدِ بالخيراتِ المُنتظَرةِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Lord receive from us our prayers in this hour and in every hour. Ease our life and guide us to fulfill Your commandments. Sanctify our spirits. Cleanse our bodies. Conduct our thoughts. Purify our intentions. Heal our diseases. Forgive our sins. Deliver us from every evil grief and distress of heart. Surround us by Your holy angels, that, by their camp, we may be guarded and guided, and attain the unity of faith, and the knowledge of Your imperceptible and infinite glory. For You are blessed forever. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ياربُّ اقبَلْ مِنَّا في هذهِ الساعةِ وكلِّ ساعةٍ طلباتِنا. سهِّلْ حياتَنا، وارشِدْنا إلى العملِ بوصاياكَ. قدِّسْ أرواحَنا. طهِّرْ أجسامَنا. قوِّمْ أفكارَنا. نَقِّ نياتِنا. اشفِ أمراضَنا واغفِرْ خطايانا. ونجِّنا مِنْ كلِّ حزنٍ رديءٍ ووجعِ قلبٍ. أحِطنا بملائكتِكَ القديسينَ، لكي نكونَ بمعسكرِهِم محفوظينَ ومُرشَدينَ، لنصِلَ إلى اتِّحادِ الإيمانِ وإلى معرفةِ مجدِكَ غيرِ المحسوسِ وغيرِ المحدودِ، فإنَّكَ مُبارَكٌ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
</ns0:Document>