<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" Agpeya="true">   
   <Title>
      <Language id="English">Communion Agpeya Prayers</Language>
   </Title>
   
   <Section expanded="true">         
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Prayer Before Communion
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            صلاة قبل التناول
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            O Lord, I am not worthy that You should come under the roof of my house, for I am sinful, but only say the word and my soul shall be healed. Say unto my soul, “Your sins are forgiven.” I am barren and in need of Your righteousness, Your compassion, Your mercy, and Your love. You humbled Yourself and descended from the heavens in unutterable glory to our lowly state and accepted to be born in a manger. O holy Savior, do not reject my humble and miserable soul, which is waiting for Your glorified coming, but accept to come into my soul to cleanse it. As You did not refuse to enter into the leper’s house to heal him, please, O Lord, enter into my soul and heal me. Do not forbid me from receiving Your holy Body and Your precious Blood. As You did not forbid the woman, who was a sinner, from kissing Your feet. May my communion with You banish every defilement and mortify my evil desires. Help me obey Your life-giving commandments, and heal my soul and body from all sins, that I may accept Your gifts. May Your grace dwell in me and may Your Spirit abide in me and make me united with You, that I may live for the glory of Your holy name. Amen.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            يارب إني غير مستحق أن تدخل تحت سقف بيتي لأني إنسان خاطئ، فقُل كلمة أولاً لتبرأ نفسي. قل لنفسي: مغفورة لكِ خطاياكِ. إني مقفر وخال من كل صلاح، وليس لي سوى تحننك ورأفتك ومحبتك للبشر. وأنت قد تنازلت من سماء مجدك غير المُدرَك إلى ذلنا، وارتضيت أن تُولَدَ في مذود البقر. فلا ترفض يا مخلصي القدوس أن تُقْبِل إلى نفسي الذليلة الحقيرة التي تنتظر حضورك البهيّ. إنك لم تستنكف من دخول بيت الأبرص لتشفيه، فاسمح يا إلهي بالدخول إلى نفسي لتطهرها. لم تمنع الخاطئة من تقبيل قدميك، فلا تحرمني الدنو منك لتناول جسدك الطاهر ودمك الأقدس، بل فليصر تناولي للإشتراك معك، ولإبادة كل ما هو دنس، ولإماتة أهوائي الدنيئة، وللعمل بوصاياك المحيية، ولشفاء نفسي وجسدي من كل خطية، ولقبول مواهبك، ولسُكنى نعمتك، ولحلول روحك، وللإتحاد بك، والثبات فيك، لأحيا لمجد اسمك القدوس، آمين.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
   
   <Section expanded="true">         
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Prayer Before Communion (by Saint John Chrysostom)
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            صلاه قبل التناول للقديس يوحنا ذهبي الفم
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            O Lord my God, I know that I am not worthy nor sufficient that You should enter under my roof into the habitation of my soul, for it is all deserted and in ruins, and there is not a fitting place in me for You to lay Your head. But as from the heights of Your glory You humbled Yourself, so now bear me in my humility; as You deigned to lie in a manger in a cave, so now also come into the manger of my mute soul and corrupt body. As You did not refrain from entering into the house of Simon the leper, or shrink from eating there with sinners, so also vouchsafe to enter the house of my poor soul, all leprous and full of sin. You did not reject the sinful woman who ventured to draw near to touch You, so also have pity on me, a sinner, approaching to touch You. Grant that I may partake of Your all-holy Body and precious Blood for the sanctification, enlightenment and strengthening of my weak soul and body; for relief from the burden of my many sins; for my preservation against all the snares of the devil; for victory over all my sinful and evil habits; for the mortification of my passions; for obedience in Your commandments; for growth in Your divine grace and for the inheritance of Your kingdom. For it is not with a careless heart that I approach You, O Christ my God, but I come trusting in Your infinite goodness, and fearing lest I may be drawn afar from You and become the prey of the wolf of souls. Therefore, I pray to You, O Master, who alone are holy, that You would sanctify my soul and body, my mind and heart and reins, and renew me entirely. Implant in my members  the fear of You, be my helper and guide, directing my life in the path of peace, and make me worthy to stand at Your right hand with Your saints through the prayers and intercessions of Your pure Mother, of the heavenly powers, and of all the saints who from all ages have been well-pleasing unto You. Amen.
         </Language>       
         <Language id="Arabic">
            أيها الربّ إلهي. إنني عالمٌ بأنني لستُ أهلاً ولا كفوءاً لأنْ تدخلَ تحتَ سقفِ بيتِ نفسي، لأني بجملتي مُقفرٌ وساقطٌ. وليس فيَّ مكانٌ لكَ أهلٌ لتُسندَ إليهِ رأسَكََ. لكن كما تواضعتَ منحدراً من العلو لأجلنا. تواضع الأن أيضاً لذلي وتواضعي. وكما ارتضيتَ أنْ تضطجعَ في مغارةٍ ومذودِ البهائم، هكذا أرتضِ أن تدخلَ في مذودِ نفسي البهيميّة وجسدي الدنس. وكما لم تستنكف أن تدخل وتأكل مع الْخُطَاةِ في بيت سمعان الأبرص. هكذا أرتضِ بأن تدخل إلى بيت نفسي الذليلة أنا الأبرص الخاطئ. وكما لم تقصِ شبيهتي الزانية الخاطئةِ لما أتتْ إليكَ ولمست قدميكَ. هكذا أيضاً تحنن عليّ أنا الخاطئ إذ أنا متقدمٌ ولألمسُكَ. وكما لم ترذل فم تلك الدنس الرجس عند تقبيله إياك. لا ترذل فمي أنا أيضاً الادنس والأرجس من تلك ولا شفتيّ الرجستين الطفستين غير الطاهرتين ولا لساني الأنجس. بل فلتصر لي جمرة جسدك الكُلي القداسة ودمك الكريم: لتقديس نفسي وجسدي الذليلين وإستنارتهما وصحتهما. لتخفيف ثقل آثامي الكثيرة. وللصيانة من كل فعل شيطاني. ولإبطال عاداتي الخبيثة السيئة ومنعها. ولإماتة الأهواء. ولإتقان وصاياك. ولزيادة نعمتك الإلهيّة. وللتأهل لملكوتك. لأني لست متقدماً إليك أيّها المسيح الإله كمزدرٍ بكَ. بل بما أني واثقٌ بصلاحك الذي لا يوصف. ولئلا بطول تباعدي عن شركتك أصيرُ فريسةً للذئب العقلي. فلذلك أتضرعُ إليك أيّها السيد بما أنك قدوسٌ وحدك: قدّس نفسي وجسدي وعقلي وقلبي وكليتي وأحشائي. وجددني بجملتي. وأغرس خوفك في أعضائي. وأجعل تقديسك غير ممحوّ مني. وكنْ لي معيناً وناصراً. ودبر بسلام حياتي. وأجعلني أهلاً للوقوف عن ميامنك مع قدّيسيك. بصلوات وشفاعات الكلّية الطهارة والدتك وخدامكَ غير الهيوليّين والقوّات الطاهرة وجميع القدّيسيين الذين أرضوكَ منذ الدهر. آمين.
         </Language>  
      </Text>
   </Section>
   
   <Section expanded="true">     
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">Another Prayer Before Communion (by Saint John Chrysostom)</Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">صلاة قبل التناول  للقدّيس يوحنا ذهبي الفم</Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            I believe, O Lord, and I confess that You are truly Christ, the Son of the living God, who came into the world to save sinners, of whom I am chief. And I believe that this is truly Your own immaculate Body and that this is truly Your own precious Blood. Therefore, I pray You, have mercy upon me and forgive my transgressions both voluntary and involuntary, of word and of deed, of knowledge and of ignorance. Make me worthy to partake without condemnation of Your immaculate Mysteries, unto the remission of my sins and unto life everlasting. Amen.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            أؤمن ياربي وأعترف أنك أنت بالحقيقة هو المسيح، إبن الله الحي، الذي جاء إلى العالم ليخلص الخطاة الذين أولهم أنا. أؤمن أن هذا حقاً هو جسدك الطاهر وهذا حقاً هو دمك الكريم. فلهذا أطلب إليك ارحمني واغفر لي آثامي التي فعلتها بإرادتي والتي فعلتها بغير إرادتي، التي فعلتها بالقول أو بالفعل، بمعرفة أو بغير معرفة. اجعلني مستحقاً أن أتناول من أسرارك الطاهرة بغير دينونة، لمغفرة خطاياي ولحياة أبدية. آمين.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>

   <Section expanded="true">     
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">Another Prayer Before Communion (by St. Basil the Great)</Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">صلاه قبل التناول  للقدّيس باسيليوس الكبير</Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            O Lord and Master, Jesus Christ, our God, fountain of life and immortality, creator of all things, visible and invisible; Con-substantial and Co-eternal Son of the eternal Father , who in Your exceeding great love, became incarnate in the latter days, and was crucified for us ungrateful and wicked children, and by Your own Blood renewed our nature corrupted by sin. O immortal King, receive me, a repentant sinner. Incline Your ear toward me and hear my prayer.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            أيّها الربّ يسوع المسيح إلهنا يا ينبوع الحياة وعدم الموت. الصانع كلّ البرايا المنظورة وغير المنظورة. ابن الآب الذي لا بدء لهُ الُمساوي لهُ في الأزليّة وعدم الابتداء. يا منْ لإفراط صلاحك لبست جسداً في الأيام الأخيرة. وصلبْتَ وذُبحت من أجلنا نحنُ الكنوديّين والفاقدي المعرفة. وبدمك الخاصّ أعدْت جبلة طبيعتنا المنفسدة من تلقاء الخطيئة. أنت أيّها الملكُ الذي لا يموت. تقبّل توبتي أيضاُ أنا الخاطئ. وأمل أذنيكَ إليّ واستمع كلامي. 
         </Language>
      </Text>
      
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            I have sinned, O Lord, I have sinned against heaven and before You, and I am not worthy to lift up my eyes to the majesty of Your glory, for I have offended Your goodness, and broken Your commandments, and disobeyed Your laws. But You, O Lord, most loving, longsuffering, and merciful, have not given me over to perish in my sins, but awaited my return.  For You, O Lover of Mankind, have said by Your prophet that You have no pleasure in the death of a sinner, but rather that he should turn from his wickedness and live. You do not desire, O Master, to destroy the works of Your hands or that they should perish, but You wished that all men should be saved and come to the knowledge of the truth.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            لأنّني أخطأتُ يا ربّ. قد أخطأتُ إلى السماء وأمامكَ ولستُ مستحقاً أن أتفرّسَ في علوّ مجدك. لأني أغضبتُ صلاحكَ إذ خالفتُ وصاياك وما أطعتُ أوامرك. لكنْ أنت يا ربّ بما أنك غير حقودٍ وطويلُ الأناةِ وجزيلُ الرحمة. لم تسلمني لأن أهلك بآثامي متوقعاً رجعتي على كلّ حالٍ. لأنك يا محبّ البشر قد قلت بوساطة نبيّك: أني لستُ أشاءُ مؤثراً موت الخاطئ إلى أن يرجع ويحيا. لأنك أيّها السيد لم تؤثر أن تُهلك جبلة يديك ولا تسرّ بهلاك البشر. بل تشاء أن يخلص الكلّ ويُقبلوا إلى معرفة الحق. 
         </Language>
      </Text>
          
      <Text>          
         <Language id="English">
            Therefore, I, although unworthy both of heavenly and of earthly and temporary life, even I, a wretched sinner who have given myself over to every evil desire, do not despair of salvation, though I have been wholly subject to sin, a slave to passion, and have defiled Your image within me, I who am Your creation and Your work. But trusting in Your infinite compassion I draw near unto You. So, receive me, also, O Christ the Lover of Mankind, as You did receive the sinful woman, the thief, the publican, and the lost son. Take away the heavy burden of my sins, You who take away the sins of the world, and heal the infirmities of men, and call all who are weary and heavy laden to Yourself and give them rest. You who did not come to call the righteous but sinners to repentance, cleanse me from all stain of body and spirit and teach me to fulfill holiness in Your fear, that with the witness of my conscience grace,  I may receive a grace of Your Father and Holy Spirit, dwelling and abiding in me.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            فلذلك وإن كنتُ أنا غير مُستحقّ للسماء ولا للأرض ولا لهذه الحياة الزمنية. إذ قدْ أخضعتُ نفسي بجملتها للخطيئة وعبّدتها للّذات وعطّلت صورتك. لكنْ بما أنّي صنعتك وجبلتك لم أيأس منْ خلاصي أنا اشقيّ. فأتقدّم واثقاً بتحننك الذي لا يُحصى. فاقبلني أنا أيضاً أيّها المسيح المحبّ البشر كما قبلت الزّانية واللص والعشّار والابن الشاطر. وارفع عنّي ّحِمل الخطايا الثقيل يا رافع خطيئة العالم وشافي أمراض البشر. يا من تدعو المتعبين والثقيليّ الأحمال إليك وتُريحهم. يا من لم تأتي لتدعو صدّيقين بل خطأة إلى التوبة. وطهرني من كلّ أدناس الجسد والروح. وعلمني أن أتقن القداسة بخوفك. لكي إذا ما أقتبلتُ نصيب قُدساتك بشهادةٍ نقيّةٍ لضميري أتحدُ بجسدك المقدّسِ ودمك الكريم. وأحواك ساكناً وثابتاً فيّ مع أبيك وروحك القدّوس.
         </Language>
      </Text>
      
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            Grant, O Lord Jesus Christ, my God, that the partaking of Your precious and life-giving Mysteries may not be to my condemnation nor may not, through the weakness of my soul and body, be received unworthily; but grant that even to my last breath, I may partake of a portion of Your holy gifts without condemnation, unto the communion of Your Holy Spirit, as a preparation for eternal life and for a good defense at Your dreaded judgment seat; so that I together with all Your saints, may also receive those incorruptible good things which You have prepared for those who love You, O Lord in whom You are glorified forever. Amen.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            نعم أّيها الربّ يسوع المسيح إلهي. ولا يكن لي تناول أسرارك الطاهرة المحيّية لمحاكمةٍ. ولا أصير ضعيفاً بالنفس والجسدِ من تلقاء تناولي إياها بعدم أستحقاق. بل أعطني حتى نسمتي الأخيرةِ أن أقبل بغير دينونةٍ نصيب قدساتك لشركة الروح القدّس ولزاد الحياة الأبدية ولجوابٍ حسنِ القبولِ لدى منبركَ الرهيبِ. لكي أصير أنا أيضاً مع كلّ مختاريكَ شريكا لخيراتك غير الفاسدة التي أعددتها للذين يحبّونكَ يا ربّ. الذين لم تزل بهم ممجداً إلى مدى الدهر. آمين.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
   
   <Section expanded="true">         
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Prayer After Communion
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            صلاة بعد التناول
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            My heart is filled with joy and my tongue with gladness. My spirit glorifies the Lord, and my soul rejoices in God my Savior. I have come to You, O Lord, clothe me with a radiant garment and make me worthy to enter into Your wedding. Let my communion with You today be forever, for through it, I increase, grow firm in virtue, and am strengthened in faith and in hope. Let my communion be a sign of Your salvation, a raiment of grace, a garment of new birth, purity and righteousness of my body and soul, and preparation for the eternal love and joy. I surrender myself and my will to Your compassion, O Lord, and I call to You my senses and my mind, to bless them and make them according to Your will. Enlighten my heart and awaken my conscience. Disperse all the shadows of the adversaries. Still the storm, walk with me and guide me. Give me comfort, quench my thirst, and abide with me for the day is coming to an end, and accompany me until daybreak. For You alone are my goal and my joy, now and forever. Amen.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            قد امتلأ قلبي فرحاً، ولساني تهليلاً. فلتعظم نفسي الرب، وتبتهج روحي بالله مخلصي. لقد أقبلت إليك يارب لتلبسني حُلة نقية للدخول إلى عُرسك. فليكن اتحادي بك اليوم دائماً، لأني به أزداد في الفضيلة ثباتاً ونمواً، ويشتد إيماني، ويتقوّى رجائي. فليصر تناولي علامة للخلاص ولِباساً للنعمة، وحُلّة للميلاد الجديد، وطهارة وقداسة للنفس والجسد، ونقاوة للحب، وفرحاً وسروراً أبدياً، ولجواب حسن القبول أمام منبرك الرهيب. وأسلم ذاتي بين حنوِّكَ. فاجعلني واحداً معك، وسَيِّرنِي تحت إرادتك. استدع إليك عقلي وحواسي وإرادتي لتباركها وتكون طوع مشيئتك. أحيي قلبي، وأيقظ ضميري، شتِّت جميع خيالات العدو، وقل للزوابِع أن تسكت. سِرْ معي وهَدِّئ روعي، ارْوِ عَطَشِي، واضرم لهيب محبتك في قلبي. تلاف بحنو ورفق كل ما ينقصني. امكث معي لأن النهار قد مال. ورافقني إلى أن ينسم النهار. فإنك وحدك غايتي وسعادتي. أنت وحدك يارب إلى الأبد، آمين.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
   
   <Section expanded="true">      
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Another Prayer After Communion (by Saint Basil the Great)
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            O Lord, Christ our God, King of the ages, and Creator of all, I thank You for all the good things which You have bestowed upon me, and for this communion of Your immaculate and life-giving Mysteries. Therefore, I entreat You, O Good One and Lover of Mankind, keep me in Your tabernacle and under the shadow of Your wings. Grant that, with a pure conscience, even unto my last breath, I may worthily partake of Your holy things, unto the remission of my sins and unto life eternal. For You are the Bread of life, the fountain of all holiness, the giver of good things, and unto You we ascribe glory, O Father, Son and Holy Spirit, now and forever, and unto the age of all ages. Amen.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            أيها الرب، المسيح إلهنا، ملك الدهور، وخالق الجميع، أشكرك على كل النعم التي أنعمت بها عليَّ، وعلى التناول من أسرارك الطاهرة المحيية. فلهذا أتضرع إليك، أيها الصالح محب البشر، إحفظني في خيمتك وتحت ظل جناحيك. أعطني أن أتناول بإستحقاق وبضمير نقي من أسرارك المقدسة لمغفرة خطاياي وللحياة الأبدية حتى النفس الأخير. لأنك أنت هو خبز الحياة، ينبوع القداسة، رازق الخيرات، وأنت الذي نرسل لك المجد أيها الآب والإبن والروح القدس، الآن وكل أوان وإلى دهر الدهور. آمين.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
   
   <Section expanded="true">      
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Another Prayer After Communion
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            صلاة بعد التناول
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            How great is Your generosity, O God, which You prepared for those who fear You! How sweet is Your grace and love for those who love You! I thank You, my Lord, who cares for me and gave me this holy, mysterious and everlasting food by which You open for us the way to eternal life. Keep me under the shadow of Your wings, and grant that, with a pure conscience, even until my last breath, I may worthily partake of Your holy things, for the remission of my sins and for life eternal. Enflame in me the fire of Your love, and keep the gift of Your grace in me, neither for judgment nor for falling into condemnation, but for gaining glory and purity of soul and body in order to live in You and for You. Guide me into Your righteousness. Fill my heart with Your grace. Sanctify my life with Your Holy Spirit, for Yours is the glory with Your gracious Father and the Holy Spirit, now and forever. Amen. 
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            ما أعظم جودك يا الله الذي أدخرته لخائفيك! ما أعذب نعمتك ومحبتك للذين يحبونك! أشكرك يا إلهي المعتني بي الذي منحتني هذا الطعام المقدس السري غير البائد، وفتحت لنا به سبيل الدخول إلى الحياة الأبدية أضرم فيَّ نار محبتك، وأحفظ موهبة نعمتك فيّ لا للدينونة ولا للوقوع في الدينونة، لكن لنوال المجد، وطهارة النفس والجسد، لكي أحيا بك،  وأعيش لأجلك، وأكمل ببرك فاهدني إلى بِرَّك، واملأني من نعمتك، وقدسني بروحك. لك المجد مع أبيك الصالح وروحك القدوس، من الأن والى الأبد، أمين.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
</Document>