<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" Agpeya="true">   
   <Title>
      <Language id="English">Meal Agpeya Prayers</Language>
   </Title>
   
   <Section expanded="true">      
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Prayer Before Meals
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            صلاة قبل الأكل
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            Blessed are You, O Lord who supported us from our youth and granted us Your blessings, and prepared food for every creature; for the eyes of everyone wait upon You, for You give them their food in due season. You open Your hands and fill all living things. To You is due glory, praise, blessing, and thanksgiving for the food that You have prepared for us. Stretch out Your right hand and bless this food set before us for the nourishment of our bodies. Let it be for power and health of our lives. Grant salvation, grace, blessing, and purity to all those who partake of it. Lift our minds to You at all times to seek our spiritual and eternal food. Grant that we may labor for the everlasting food that is for eternal life. Grant us to be partakers of Your evening banquet. Grant us the food of blessing, the cup of salvation, and fill our hearts with joy. Teach us, since You are the pleasure in all things, that when eating, drinking or laboring, we do it all for the glory of Your holy name. For Yours is the glory, forever and ever. Amen.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            تباركت يارب يا من تعولنا منذ حداثتنا، وتهبنا خيراتك، وتهيئ الغذاء للجميع. لأن أعين الكل تترجاك، وأنت تعطيهم طعامهم في حينه. تفتح يدك فتُشبع كل حي من رضاك، لك المجد والتسبيح والبركة والشكر على كل ما أعددت لنا من الطعام. فتفضل يارب وأبسط يمينك وبارك هذا الطعام الموضوع على هذه المائدة المُعَدّة لغذاء أجسادنا. اجعله شفاء وقوة لحياتنا الجسدية، وامنح خلاصاً ونعمة وبركة وطهراً لكل المتناولين منه. ارفع عقولنا إليك كل حين لطلب طعامنا الروحي غير البائد. اعطنا أن نعمل للطعام الباقي للحياة الأبدية، وهَب لنا نصيباً في الإشتراك في وليمتك السمائية. امنحنا خبز البركة، وكأس الخلاص، واملأ قلوبنا من البهجة والفرح. انعم علينا بحياة مطمئنة هادئة، وسعادة في النفس، وصحة في الجسد. علمنا أن نطلب رضاك في كل شيء، حتى إذا أكلنا أو شربنا أو عملنا أي شيء، نعمله لمجد اسمك القدوس، لأن لك المجد إلى الأبد، آمين.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
   
   <Section expanded="true">      
      <Title>
         <Language id="English">
            Prayer After Meals
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            صلاة بعد الأكل
         </Language>
      </Title>
            
      <Text>
         <Language id="English">
            O Lord, we are not worthy of the least of all Your mercies which You have shown us today. O Lord, rich in mercies, who supports us and fills our hearts with plenty, joy and happiness, blessed be Your name. O Lord, he who eats, eats to the Lord and gives thanks to God; and he who drinks, drinks to the Lord and gives thanks to God. Therefore, if we eat or drink or do anything, we do it to the glory of God and we give Him thanks. O Lord, let us be hungry for the bread of life, for whoever eats of it never dies but lives forever. Also, let us be thirsty for the living water, for whoever drinks of it shall never thirst, but it becomes a well in him which springs up to everlasting life. We give You thanks, O Almighty God, for these and all Your blessings, through Christ Jesus our Lord. For Thine is the kingdom and the power and the glory forever and ever. Amen.
         </Language>
         <Language id="Arabic">
            نشكرك أيها الرب الإله ضابط الكل، لأنك أنت الذي أعددت لنا هذه المائدة، التي هي دليل المحبة لنا نحن عبيدك، الذين نلنا من خيرات الأرض. نسألك يا سيدنا، ليَكثُر ما فضل عنا كبركة الخمس خبزات والسمكتين، هذه التي عُلت بها جموعاً كثيرة في البرية. صِر لنا عوناً وقوة، نحن جميع الآخذين منه، والذين صنعوا معنا رحمة، والذين خدمونا، والمتكئون معنا عبيدك. هب لهم مجازاتك المملوءة خلاصاً. عوِّضهم عن أتعابهم. لأن اسمك القدوس مبارك ومملوء مجداً، أيها الآب والابن والروح القدس، الآن وكل أوان وإلى دهر الدهور، آمين.
         </Language>
      </Text>
   </Section>
</Document>