<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<ns0:Document xmlns:ns0="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" Agpeya="true">
   <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">The First Hour (Prime)</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">صلاة باكر</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         6:00 AM: To commemorate the Resurrection of our Lord Jesus Christ. To be prayed in the morning to give thanks to God for the beginning of a new day, and to glorify Him for His Resurrection.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بهذهِ الصلاةِ نشكرُ اللهَ على انقضاءِ الليلِ بسلامٍ، ونطلبُ مِنْ أجلِ نهارٍ مُضيءٍ بالأعمالِ الصالحةِ، ونذكرُ قيامةَ السيدِ المسيحِ في باكرِ النهارِ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
            
   <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Introduction of Every Hour</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">مُقدِمةُ كلِّ ساعةٍ</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
    
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ ⲫ̀ⲣⲁⲛ ⲙ̀Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In the name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, one God. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         باسمِ الآبِ والابنِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ الإلهِ الواحدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         <ns0:span class="Coptic">Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ</ns0:span>. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord bless us. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         <ns0:span class="Coptic">Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ.</ns0:span>  ياربُّ ارحَمْ. ياربُّ ارحَمْ. ياربُّ بارِكْ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit. Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجدُ للآبِ والابنِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Our Father</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">أبانا الذي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲧⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲁ ⲛ̀ϫⲟⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Make us worthy to pray thankfully:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اللهُمَّ اجعلْنا مُستحقينَ أن نقولَ بشكرٍ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ Ⲡⲉⲛⲓⲱⲧ ⲉⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be Thy name.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أبانا الذي في السماواتِ ليتقدسِ اسمُكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲥⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ: ⲡⲉⲧⲉϩⲛⲁⲕ ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥϣⲱⲡⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲕⲁϩⲓ:  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Thy kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليأتِ ملكوتُكَ، لتكُن مشيئتُكَ، كما في السماءِ كذلكَ على الأرضِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲓⲕ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲣⲁⲥϯ ⲙⲏⲓϥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲫⲟⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲣⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Give us this day our daily bread and forgive us our trespasses, as we forgive those who trespass against us and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         خبزَنا الذي للغدِّ أعطِنا اليومَ، واغفِرْ لنا ذنوبَنا كما نغفِرُ نحنُ أيضاً للمُذنبينَ إلينا، ولا تُدخِلنا في تجرِبةٍ لكِنْ نجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ: ϫⲉ ⲑⲱⲕ ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In Christ Jesus our Lord. For Thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, forever. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِّنا. لأنَّ لكَ المُلكَ والقوةَ والمجدَ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">The Prayer of Thanksgiving</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">صلاةُ الشكر</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>

      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲛϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲟⲧϥ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲉϥⲉⲣⲡⲉⲑⲛⲁⲛⲉϥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲏⲧ: Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲛⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Let us give thanks to the beneficent and merciful God, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         فلنشكرْ صانعَ الخيراتِ، الرحومَ اللهَ أبا ربِّنا وإلَهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>   
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ ⲁϥⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲕⲉⲡⲁⲍⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲁϥⲉⲣⲃⲟⲏ̀ⲑⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁϥⲁ̀ⲣⲉϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁϥϣⲟⲡⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟϥ ⲁϥϯⲁ̀ⲥⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁϥϯⲧⲟⲧⲉⲛ ⲁϥⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲓⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩ ⲑⲁⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         For He has covered us, helped us, guarded us, accepted us to Himself, spared us, supported us, and has brought us to this hour.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         لأنهُ سترَنا وأعانَنا وحفظَنا وقبلَنا إليهِ وأشفقَ علَينا وعضدَنا وأتى بِنا إلى هذهِ الساعةِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲛⲑⲟϥ ⲟⲛ ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟϥ ϩⲟⲡⲱⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲁ̀ⲣⲉϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲁⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲛϧ: ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲓⲣⲏⲛⲏ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲓⲡⲁⲛⲧⲟⲕⲣⲁⲧⲱⲣ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Let us also ask Him, the Lord our God, the Pantocrator, to guard us in all peace this holy day and all the days of our life.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         هو أيضاً فلنسألْهُ أن يحفظَنا في هذا اليومِ المُقدسِ، وكلِّ أيامِ حياتِنا بكلِّ سلامٍ، الضابطَ الكلِّ الربَّ إلهَنا.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲛⲏⲃ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲡⲓⲡⲁⲛⲧⲟⲕⲣⲁⲧⲱⲣ: Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲛⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Master, Lord, God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أيها السيدُ الربُّ الإلهُ ضابطُ الكلِّ، أبو ربِّنا وإلَهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>   
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲟⲧⲕ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         we thank You for everything, concerning everything, and in everything.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نشكرُكَ على كلِّ حالٍ، ومِنْ أجلِ كلِّ حالٍ، وفي كلِّ حالٍ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ ⲁⲕⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲕⲉⲡⲁⲍⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲁⲕⲉⲣⲃⲟⲏ̀ⲑⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁⲕⲁ̀ⲣⲉϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁⲕϣⲟⲡⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ: ⲁⲕϯⲁ̀ⲥⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ: ⲁⲕϯⲧⲟⲧⲉⲛ ⲁⲕⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲓⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩ ⲑⲁⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         For You have covered us, helped us, guarded us, accepted us to Yourself, spared us, supported us, and have brought us to this hour.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         لأنكَ سترتَنا وأعنتَنا وحفظتَنا، وقبلتَنا إليكَ، وأشفقتَ علينا وعضَّدتَنا وأتيتَ بنا إلى هذهِ الساعةِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲧⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲧⲉⲛⲧⲱⲃϩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ ⲡⲓⲙⲁⲓⲣⲱⲙⲓ: ⲙⲏⲓⲥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉⲑⲣⲉⲛϫⲱⲕ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲙ̀ⲡⲁⲓⲕⲉⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲫⲁⲓ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲛϧ: ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲓⲣⲏⲛⲏ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲧⲉⲕϩⲟϯ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Therefore, we ask and entreat Your goodness, O Lover of Mankind, grant us to complete this holy day and all the days of our life in all peace with Your fear.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         مِنْ أجلِ هذا نسألُ ونطلبُ مِنْ صلاحِكَ يا محبَّ البشرِ، امنحنا أن نكمِّلَ هذا اليومَ المُقدسَ، وكلَّ أيامِ حياتِنا بكلِّ سلامٍ معَ خوفِكَ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲑⲟⲛⲟⲥ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ⲉ̀ⲛⲉⲣⲅⲓⲁ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡ̀ⲥⲁⲧⲁⲛⲁⲥ: ⲡ̀ⲥⲟϭⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ϩⲁⲛⲣⲱⲙⲓ ⲉⲩϩⲱⲟⲩ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡ̀ⲧⲱⲛϥ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ϣⲱⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ϩⲁⲛϫⲁϫⲓ ⲛⲏⲉⲧϩⲏⲡ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉⲑⲟⲩⲱⲛϩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         All envy, all temptation, all the work of Satan, the counsel of wicked men and the rising up of enemies, hidden and manifest,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         كلُّ حسدٍ وكلُّ تجربةٍ وكلُّ فعلِ الشيطانِ، ومؤامرةُ الناسِ الأشرارِ، وقيامُ الأعداءِ الخفيينَ والظاهرينَ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="!Agpeya">
         <ns0:Comment>         
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               The priest bows his head toward the East and signs himself with the sign of the cross, saying:
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               يطامن الكاهن رأسه إلى الشرق ويرشم ذاته بمثال الصليب قائلاً:
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Comment>         
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲁ̀ⲗⲓⲧⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁⲣⲟⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         take them away from us
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         انزعْها عنَّا.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="!Agpeya">
         <ns0:Comment>         
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Then he turns toward the west from his right and makes the sign of the cross over the people, saying the following. If the Pope, a metropolitan, or a bishop is present, he makes the sign of the cross over the people and says the following instead of the priest.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               ثم يلتفت إلى الغرب عن يمينه ويرشم الشعب قائلاً:[إذا كان الأب البابا أو المطران أو الأسقف حاضراً فهو الذي يرشم الشعب ويقول ذلك.]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲉⲕⲗⲁⲟⲥ ⲧⲏⲣϥ
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         and from all Your people,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وعن سائرِ شعبِكَ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="Baptism | Unction | LiturgyOfTheWaters | Engagement | Crowning | FuneralPrayer | GeneralFuneralPrayer | Ordination">
         <ns0:Group>
            <ns0:Season id="ConsecrationOfWaters | BathingPrayer | LiturgyOfTheWaters">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲕⲟⲗⲩⲙⲃⲏⲑⲣⲁ ⲑⲁⲓ
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this basin,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذه الفسقيةِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="AbsolutionOfWoman">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲥ̀ϩⲓⲙⲓ ⲑⲁⲓ:
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this woman,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذه المرأةِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Unction">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉⲧϣⲱⲛⲓ 
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this infirm person,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذا المريضِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Engagement">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉⲧⲁϥⲱⲡ ⲛ̀ⲥⲁ ⲑⲁⲓ
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this betrothed couple,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذين الخطيبين
                  </ns0:Language>
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Crowning">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲛⲁⲓⲡⲁⲧϣⲉⲗⲉⲧ ⲛⲁⲓ
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this bridegroom and bride,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذين العروسين.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="(FuneralPrayer ^ !FuneralMemorial) | GeneralFuneralPrayer">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲯⲩⲭⲏ ⲑⲁⲓ 
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this soul,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن هذه النفسِ.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
            
            <ns0:Season id="Ordination">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     and from this Your servant,
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وعن عبدك هذا.
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
         </ns0:Group>
         
         <ns0:Group>
            <ns0:Season id="!Agpeya">
               <ns0:Comment>         
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     Then he turns towards the East, making the sign of the cross, saying:
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     ثم يلتفت إلى الشرق قائلا:
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Comment>
            </ns0:Season>
         </ns0:Group>
      </ns0:Season>

      <ns0:Season id="HomeBlessing">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲁⲓⲏⲓ ⲫⲁⲓ
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               and from this house,
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وعن هذا البيتِ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>

      <ns0:Season id="!OfferingOfLamb ^ !Agpeya ^ !Ordination">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲉⲕⲕ̀ⲗⲏⲥⲓⲁ̀ ⲑⲁⲓ
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               and from this church,
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وعن هذه الكنيسةِ.
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
         
         <ns0:Comment>         
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Then he turns toward the East, making the sign of the cross on the altar, saying:
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               ثم يلتفت إلى الشرق ويرشم على المذبح قائلاً:
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="OfferingOfLamb">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲓⲧ̀ⲣⲁⲡⲉⲍⲁ ⲑⲁⲓ
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               and from this table,
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وعن هذه المائدة،
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲁⲓⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲕ ⲫⲁⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         and from this Your holy place.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وعن موضعِكَ المُقدسِ هذا.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲛⲏ ⲇⲉ ⲉⲑⲛⲁⲛⲉⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉⲧⲉⲣⲛⲟϥⲣⲓ ⲥⲁϩⲛⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲱⲟⲩ ⲛⲁⲛ: ϫⲉ ⲛ̀ⲑⲟⲕ ⲡⲉ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲕϯ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲉⲣϣⲓϣⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲉ̀ϩⲱⲙⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ⲛⲓϩⲟϥ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓϭ̀ⲗⲏ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲧⲏⲣⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲓϫⲁϫⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         But those things which are good and profitable do provide for us, for it is You who have given us the authority to tread on serpents and scorpions, and upon all the power of the enemy.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أمَّا الصالحاتُ والنافعاتُ فارزقنا إياها لأنكَ أنتَ الذي أعطيتَنا السلطانَ أن ندوسَ على الحياتِ والعقاربَ وعلى كلِّ قوةِ العدوِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ: ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         And lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ولا تُدْخِلْنا في تجربةٍ لكن نَجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲓϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓⲙⲉⲧϣⲉⲛϩⲏⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲙⲁⲓⲣⲱⲙⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲙⲟⲛⲟⲅⲉⲛⲏⲥ ⲛ̀Ϣⲏⲣⲓ: Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲛⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Through the grace, compassion, and love-of-mankind of Your only-begotten Son, our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالنعمةِ والرأفاتِ ومحبةِ البشرِ اللواتي لابنِكَ الوحيدِ، ربِّنا وإلهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲓⲧⲟⲧϥ ⲉ̀ⲣⲉ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲧⲁⲓⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲁ̀ⲙⲁϩⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲕⲩⲛⲏⲥⲓⲥ: ⲉⲣⲡ̀ⲣⲉⲡⲓ ⲛⲁⲕ ⲛⲉⲙⲁϥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲛ̀ⲣⲉϥⲧⲁⲛϧⲟ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ⲟ̀ⲙⲟⲟⲩⲥⲓⲟⲥ ⲛⲉⲙⲁⲕ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         through whom the glory, honor, dominion, and worship are due unto You, with Him and the Holy Spirit, the Giver of Life, who is of one essence with You,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         هذا الذي مِنْ قبَلِه، المجدُ والكرامةُ والعزة والسجودُ، تليقُ بكَ معَهُ، ومعَ الرّوحِ القُدُسِ المُحيي المساوي لكَ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϯⲛⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛ̀ⲥⲏⲟⲩ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲙ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         now and at all times and unto the age of all ages. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ كلِّها. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 50
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ الخمسونَ
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲏⲓ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ⲡⲉⲕⲛⲓϣϯ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲓ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ⲡ̀ⲁ̀ϣⲁⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧϣⲉⲛϩⲏⲧ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲥⲱⲗϫ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲁ̀ⲙⲟⲛⲓⲁ̀: ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲣⲁϧⲧ ⲛ̀ϩⲟⲩⲟ̀ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲧⲁⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲁⲛⲟⲃⲓ: ϫⲉ ⲧⲁⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ̀ ⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲕ ϯⲥⲱⲟⲩⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲥ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲁⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡⲁⲙ̀ⲑⲟ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗⲛ̀ⲥⲏⲟⲩ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Have mercy upon me, O God, according to Your great mercy; and according to the multitude of Your compassions blot out my iniquity. Wash me thoroughly from my iniquity, and cleanse me from my sin. For I am conscious of my iniquity; and my sin is at all times before me.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ارحَمْنِي يا اللهُ كَعَظيمِ رَحْمتِكَ، ومِثْلِ كَثْرةِ رَأفتِكَ امْحُ إثْمِي واغْسلْنِي كَثيراً مِنْ إثْمِي، ومِنْ خَطيئَتِي طهِّرْنِي. لأنِّي أنا عارِفٌ بإثْمِي، وخَطيئَتِي أمَامِي في كلِّ حينٍ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲛⲑⲟⲕ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁⲩⲁⲧⲕ ⲁⲓⲉⲣⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ ⲁⲓⲁⲓϥ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕⲙ̀ⲑⲟ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ϩⲟⲡⲱⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲁⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲉⲕⲥⲁϫⲓ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲕ ϭⲣⲟ ⲉⲕⲛⲁϭⲓϩⲁⲡ. Hⲏⲡⲡⲉ ⲅⲁⲣ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ̀ ⲁⲩⲉⲣⲃⲟⲕⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲓ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲁ̀ ⲧⲁⲙⲁⲩ ϭⲓϣϣⲱⲟⲩ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲓ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Against You only I have sinned, and done evil before You, that You might be just in Your sayings, and might overcome when You are judged. For, behold, I was conceived in iniquities, and in sins my mother conceived me.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لَكَ وحْدَكَ أخْطأْتُ، والشَّرَّ قدامَكَ صَنعْتُ، لِكيْ تَتَبرَّرَ في أقْوالِكَ، وتَغْلبَ إذَا حوكِمْتَ. لأنِّي هَأنَذَا بالإثْمِ حُبِلَ بِي، وبالَخَطايَا ولدَتْني أمِّي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Hⲏⲡⲡⲉ ⲅⲁⲣ ⲁⲕⲙⲉⲛⲣⲉ ⲑ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: ⲛⲏⲉⲧϩⲏⲡ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛ̀ⲥⲉⲟⲩⲱⲛϩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲁⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲥⲟⲫⲓⲁ ⲁⲕⲧⲁⲙⲟⲓ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ. Ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲛⲟⲩϫϧ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕϣⲉⲛϩⲩⲥⲱⲡⲟⲛ: ⲉⲓⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲣⲁϧⲧ ⲉⲓⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲃⲁϣ ⲉ̀ϩⲟⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲭⲓⲱⲛ: ⲉⲕⲉⲑ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲱⲧⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲟⲩⲟⲩⲛⲟϥ: ⲉⲩⲉ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲛⲓⲕⲁⲥ ⲉⲧⲑⲉⲃⲓⲏⲟⲩⲧ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            For, behold, You have loved the truth; You have manifested to me the hidden and unrevealed things of Your wisdom. You shall sprinkle me with Your hyssop, and I shall be purified. You shall wash me, and I shall be made whiter than snow. You shall make me to hear gladness and joy; the humbled bones shall rejoice.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لأنَّكَ هَكَذا قَدْ أحْبَبتَ الحقَّ، إذْ أوْضَحتَ لِي غَوامِضَ حِكْمتِكَ ومَسْتُورَاتِها. تَنضَحُ عَليَّ بِزُوفَاكَ فأُطَهَّرُ، تَغْسلُنِي فَأبْيضُّ أكْثَرَ مِنَ الثَّلجِ. تُسْمعُنِي سُرُوراً وفَرحاً، فتَبْتهجُ عِظامِي المتواضِعةُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲙⲁⲧⲁⲥⲑⲟ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕϩⲟ ⲥⲁⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲛⲟⲃⲓ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛⲁⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ̀ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲥⲟⲗϫⲟⲩ. Ⲟⲩϩⲏⲧ ⲉϥⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲥⲟⲛⲧϥ ⲛ̀ϧⲏⲧ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ: ⲟⲩⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉϥⲥⲟⲩⲧⲱⲛ ⲁ̀ⲣⲓⲧϥ ⲙ̀ⲃⲉⲣⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲏⲉⲧⲥⲁϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲃⲉⲣⲃⲱⲣⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲉⲕϩⲟ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲡⲉⲕⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲟⲗϥ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁⲣⲟⲓ. Ⲙⲟⲓ ⲛⲏⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲟⲩϫⲁⲓ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲛ̀ϩⲏⲅⲉⲙⲱⲛⲓⲕⲟⲛ ⲙⲁⲧⲁϫⲣⲟⲓ: ⲉⲓⲉ̀ⲧ̀ⲥⲁⲃⲉ ⲛⲓⲁⲛⲟⲙⲟⲥ ϩⲓ ⲛⲉⲕⲙⲱⲓⲧ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛⲓⲁⲥⲉⲃⲏⲥ ⲉⲩⲉ̀ⲕⲟⲧⲟⲩ ϩⲁⲣⲟⲕ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Turn away Your face from my sins, and blot out all my iniquities. Create in me a clean heart, O God; and renew a right spirit in my inward parts. Do not cast me away from Your face; and do not remove Your Holy Spirit from me. Give me the joy of Your salvation, and uphold me with a directing spirit. Then I shall teach the transgressors Your ways; and the ungodly men shall turn to You.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اصْرِفْ وجْهَكَ عَنْ خَطايَايَ وامْحُ كلَّ آثَامِي. قَلباً نَقياً اخْلقْ فيَّ يا اللهُ، ورُوحاً مُسْتَقيماً جدِّدهُ في أحْشَائِي. لا تَطْرحْنِي مِنْ قُدَّامِ وجْهِكَ، ورُوحُكَ القُدُّوسُ لا تَنْزعْهُ مِنِّي. امْنَحْنِي بَهْجةَ خَلاصِكَ، وبرُوحٍ رئاسيٍ اعْضُدْنِي فأُعلِّمُ الأثَمَةَ طُرُقَكَ، والمنَافِقونَ إليكَ يَرجِعونَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϧⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛⲥ̀ⲛⲟϥ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ: Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲧⲁⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣⲓⲁ: ⲉϥⲉ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲁⲗⲁⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧⲉⲕⲇⲓⲕⲉⲟⲥⲩⲛⲏ. Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲛⲁⲥ̀ⲫⲟⲧⲟⲩ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲉ ⲣⲱⲓ ϫⲱ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕⲥ̀ⲙⲟⲩ: ϫⲉ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉ ⲁⲕⲟⲩⲱϣ ϣⲟⲩϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ: ⲛⲁⲓⲛⲁϯ ⲟⲛ ⲡⲉ: ϩⲁⲛϭⲗⲓⲗ ⲛ̀ϫⲟϥϫⲉϥ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲕϯⲙⲁϯ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲟⲩ. Ⲡⲓϣⲟⲩϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲟⲩⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉϥⲧⲉⲛⲛⲏⲟⲩⲧ ⲡⲉ: ⲟⲩϩⲏⲧ ⲉϥⲧⲉⲛⲛⲏⲟⲩⲧ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲉϥⲉ̀ⲑⲉⲃⲓⲏⲟⲩⲧ ⲫⲁⲓ ⲛ̀ⲛⲉ Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ϣⲟϣϥ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Deliver me from blood, O God, the God of my salvation, and my tongue shall rejoice in Your righteousness. O Lord, You shall open my lips, and my mouth shall declare Your praise. For if You desired sacrifice, I would have given it; You do not take pleasure in burnt offerings. The sacrifice of God is a broken spirit; a broken and humbled heart God shall not despise.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            نَجِّنِي مِنَ الدِّماءِ يا اللهُ إلَهَ خَلاصِي، فيَبتهِجُ لِسانِي بعَدلِكَ. ياربُّ افْتَحْ شَفتَيَّ، فَيُخبرُ فَمِي بَتَسْبيحِكَ. لأنَّكَ لَوْ آثَرتَ الذَّبيحةَ لَكُنْتُ الآنَ أعْطِي؛ ولَكنَّكَ لا تُسرُّ بالَمُحْرقَاتِ فالذَبيحَةُ للهِ رُوحٌ مُنْسحقٌ. القَلْبُ المنْكسِرُ والمتَواضِعُ لا يُرْذلُهُ اللهُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲁⲣⲓⲡⲉⲑⲛⲁⲛⲉϥ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲉⲕϯⲙⲁϯ ⲉ̀Ⲥⲓⲱⲛ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲛⲓⲥⲟⲃⲧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ Ⲓⲉⲣⲟⲩⲥⲁⲗⲏⲙ ⲙⲁⲣⲟⲩⲕⲟⲧⲟⲩ: ⲧⲟⲧⲉ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ϯⲙⲁϯ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ϩⲁⲛϣⲟⲩϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲉⲑⲙⲏⲓ: ⲟⲩⲁⲛⲁⲫⲟⲣⲁ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲁⲛϭⲗⲓⲗ: ⲧⲟⲧⲉ ⲉⲩⲉ̀ⲓ̀ⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ϩⲁⲛⲙⲁⲥⲓ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ⲱϣⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲉⲕⲙⲁⲛ̀ⲉⲣϣⲱⲟⲩϣⲓ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Do good, O Lord, in Your good pleasure to Zion; and let the walls of Jerusalem be built. Then You shall be pleased with sacrifices of righteousness, offering, and burnt sacrifices: then they shall offer calves upon Your altar. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أنْعِمْ ياربُّ بِمَسرتِكَ عَلى صِهْيَونَ ولْتُبنَ أسْوَارُ أورُشَلِيمَ. حِينَئذٍ تُسرُّ بذَبائِحِ العدلِ، قرباناً ومُحْرقَاتٍ. حينَئذٍ يُقرِّبونَ عَلى مَذابِحِكَ العُجُولَ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>     
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">       
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Come Let Us Kneel Down
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            هلمّ نسجدُ
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Come let us kneel down, let us ask Christ our God.    
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            هلمَّ نسجدُ، هلمَّ نسألُ المسيحَ إلهَنا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Come let us kneel down, let us beseech Christ our King.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            هلمَّ نسجدُ، هلمَّ نطلبُ مِنَ المسيحِ ملكِنا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Come let us kneel down, let us entreat Christ our Savior.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            هلمَّ نسجدُ، هلمَّ نتضرعُ إلى المسيحِ مخلِّصِنا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord Jesus Christ, the Word of God, our God, through the intercession of Saint Mary and all Your saints, preserve us, and bring us to a good start. Have mercy on us according to Your will forever. 	
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يا ربَّنا يسوعَ المسيحَ كلمةَ اللهِ إلهَنا، بشفاعةِ القديسةِ مريمَ وجميعِ قديسيكَ، إحفظْنا ولنبدأ بدءاً حسناً. ارحَمْنا كإرادتِكَ إلى الأبدِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The night has passed; we thank You, O Lord, and we ask You to keep us this day away from sin and deliver us.  
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الليلُ عبَرَ، نشكرُكَ ياربُّ ونسألُ أن تحفظَنا في هذا اليومِ بغيرِ خَطيئَةٍ وانقذْنا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>

   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Pauline Epistle (Ephesians 4:1-5)
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            البولس من رسالة أفسس  4: 1-5
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>

      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            I, therefore, the prisoner of the Lord, beseech you to walk worthy of the calling with which you were called, with all lowliness and meekness, with longsuffering, bearing with one another in love, endeavoring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. There is one body, and one Spirit, just as you were called in one hope of your calling; one Lord, one faith, one baptism.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أسألُكُم، أنا الأسيرَ في الربِّ أن تسلكوا كما يحقُّ للدعوةِ التي دُعيتُمْ إليها، بكلِّ تواضعِ القلبِ والوداعةِ وطولِ الأناةِ، محتمِلينَ بعضُكم بعضاً بالمحبةِ، مسرِعينَ إلى حفظِ وَحدانيَّةِ الرّوحِ برباطِ الصُلحِ الكامِلِ لكي تكونوا جسَداً واحِداً ورُوحاً واحِداً، كما دُعيتُمْ في رجاءِ دعوتِكم الواحِدِ. ربٌّ واحِدٌ. وإيمانٌ واحِدٌ. ومعموديَّةٌ واحِدةٌ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>

   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Faith of the Church
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            من إيمان الكنيسة
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>

      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            One is God the Father of everyone. One is His Son, Jesus Christ the Word, who took flesh and died and rose from the dead on the third day, and raised us with Him. One is the Holy Spirit, the Comforter, one in His hypostasis, proceeding from the Father, purifying the whole creation, and teaching us to worship the Holy Trinity, one in divinity and one in essence. We praise Him and bless Him forever. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            واحدٌ هو اللهُ أبو كلِّ أحدٍ. واحدٌ هو أيضاً ابنُهُ يسوعُ المسيحُ الكلمةُ، الذي تجسدَ وماتَ وقامَ مِنَ الأمواتِ في اليومِ الثالثِ وأقامَنا معَهُ. واحدٌ هو الرّوحُ القُدُسُ المُعزِّي الواحدُ بأقنومِهِ، منبثقٌ مِنَ الآبِ، يطهِّرُ كلَّ البرِيَّةِ. يعلِّمُنا أن نسجدَ للثالوثِ القُدُّوسِ بلاهوتٍ واحدٍ وطبيعةٍ واحدةٍ، نسبِّحُهُ ونبارِكُهُ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Role id="Introduction">
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Morning Prayer of this blessed day, we offer to Christ our King and our God, beseeching Him to forgive us our sins.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            صلاةُ باكرٍ مِنَ النهارِ المبارَكِ، أقدِّمُها للمسيحِ ملكي وإلهي، وأرجوهُ أن يغفِرَ لي خطايايَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Role>
         
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         From the Psalms of our teacher David the prophet.  May his blessings be upon us all. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         مِنْ مزاميرِ مُعلِّمِنا داودَ النبي بركاتِهِ علينا. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>    
<ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         The following psalms are reserved to be prayed by the priest:
         <ns0:ul>
            <ns0:li>Psalm 1</ns0:li>
            <ns0:li>Psalm 15</ns0:li>
            <ns0:li>Psalm 142</ns0:li>
         </ns0:ul>
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 1 - Blessed is the man who...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الأول - طوبى للرجلِ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
     <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Blessed is the man who has not walked in the counsel of the ungodly, and has not stood in the way of the sinners, and has not sat in the seat of the evil men. But his will is in the law of the Lord; and in His law he shall meditate day and night. He shall be like the tree which is planted by the streams of water, which shall yield its fruit in its due season, and its leaf shall not scatter, and in everything he does he prospers.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            طوبى للرجلِ الذي لم يسلكْ في مشورةِ المُنافقينَ. وفي طريقِ الخطاةِ لم يقفْ، وفي مجلسِ المستهزئينَ لم يجلسْ. لكِنْ في ناموسِ الربِّ إرادتُهُ، وفي ناموسِهِ يلهجُ نهاراً وليلاً. فيكونُ كالشجرةِ المغروسةِ على مجاري المياهِ التي تُعطي ثمرَها في حينِهِ. وورقُها لا ينتثرُ، وكلُّ ما يصنعُ ينجحُ فيهِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Not so are the ungodly, not so; but rather they are like the chaff which the wind scatters upon the face of the earth. Therefore the ungodly shall not stand in judgment, nor the sinners in the council of the righteous. For the Lord knows the way of the righteous, but the way of the ungodly shall perish. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ليسَ كذلكَ المنافِقونَ، ليسَ كذلكَ. لكنَّهُم كالهباءِ الذي تذرِّيهِ الريحُ عَن وجهِ الأرضِ. فلهذا لا يقومُ المنافِقونَ في الدينونةِ، ولا الخطاةُ في مجمعِ الصديقينَ. لأنَّ الربَّ يعرفُ طريقَ الأبرارِ، وأمَّا طريقُ المنافِقينَ فتُبادُ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 2 - Why did the nations rage...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الثاني - لماذا ارتجتْ الأمم...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Why did the nations rage, and the peoples meditate on vain things? The kings of the earth stood up, and the rulers gathered together against the Lord and against His Christ; saying, “Let us break through their bonds, and cast away their yoke from us.”
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لماذا ارتجتْ الأممُ، وتفكرتْ الشعوبُ في الباطلِ. قامَ ملوكُ الأرضِ وتآمرَ الرؤساءُ معاً على الربِّ وعلى مسيحِهِ قائلينَ: لنقطعْ أغلالَهُما، ولنطرحْ عنَّا نيرَهُما.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            He who dwells in the heavens shall laugh at them, and the Lord shall mock them. Then He shall speak to them in His anger, and in His wrath He shall trouble them.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الساكنُ في السماواتِ يضحكُ بهِم، والربُّ يستهزئُ بهِم. حينئذٍ يكلمُهُم بغضبِهِ، وبرجزِهِ يُرجفهُم.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            “But I have been established king by Him on Zion, His holy mountain, proclaiming the ordinance of the Lord: the Lord said to Me, `You are My Son, today I have begotten You. Ask Me, and I will give You the nations for Your inheritance, and Your authority to the end of the earth. You shall shepherd them with a rod of iron; You shall crush them as a potter's vessel.’”
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أنا أقمتُهُ ملِكاً على صهيونَ جبلِ قدسِهِ، لأكرزَ بأمرِ الربِّ. الربُّ قالَ لي: أنتَ ابني، وأنا اليومَ ولدتُكَ. اسألْني فأعطيكَ الأممَ ميراثَكَ، وسلطانَكَ إلى أقطارِ الأرضِ. لترعاهُم بقضيبٍ مِنْ حديدٍ. ومثلَ آنيةِ الفخارِ تسحقُهُم.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Now, understand, O kings; be instructed, all you who judge the earth, serve the Lord with fear, and rejoice in Him with trembling. Take hold of instruction, lest the Lord be angry, and you perish from the way of righteousness, whenever His wrath shall be suddenly kindled. Blessed are all who trust in Him. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            فالآنَ أيها الملوكُ افهموا، وتأدبوا يا جميعَ قضاةِ الأرضِ اعبدوا الربَّ بخشيةٍ. وهللوا لهُ برعدةٍ. الزموا الأدبَ لئلا يغضبَ الربُّ فتضلُّوا عَن طريقِ الحقِّ. عندما يتَّقدُ غضبُهُ بسرعةٍ، طوبى لجميعِ المتكلينَ عليهِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 3 - O Lord, why have they...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الثالث - يا ربّ لماذا كثر...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord, why have they who afflict me multiplied? Many have risen up upon me. Many say unto my soul, “There is no salvation for him in his God.” But You, O Lord, are my supporter, my glory, and the elevation of my head.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ياربُّ لماذا كثُرَ الذينَ يحزنونَني، كثيرونَ قاموا عليَّ. كثيرونَ يقولونَ لنفسي، ليسَ لهُ خلاصٌ بإلهِهِ. أنتَ ياربُّ أنتَ هو ناصري، مجدي ورافعُ رأسي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            With my voice I cried unto the Lord, and He heard me out of His holy mountain. I laid down and slept; and I arose; for the Lord is He who supports me. I will not be afraid of ten thousands of people, who surround me; who have risen upon me. Rise, O Lord, save me, O my God, for You have smitten all who are enemies to me without cause. The teeth of the sinners You have broken. Salvation is the Lord’s, and His blessing is upon His people. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            بصَوتي إلى الربِّ صرختُ. فاستجابَ لي مِنْ جبلِ قُدسِهِ. أنا اضطجعتُ ونِمتُ، ثم استيقَظتُ لأنَّ الربَّ ناصري. فلا أخافُ مِنْ ربواتِ الجموعِ المُحيطينَ بي القائمينَ عليَّ. قُمْ ياربُّ خلِّصْني يا إلهي، لأنكَ ضربتَ كلَّ مَنْ يُعاديني باطِلاً. أسنانُ الخطاةِ سحقتَها. للربِّ الخلاصُ وعلى شعبِهِ بركتُهُ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 4 - When I cried out...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الرابع - إذ دعوتُ استجبتَ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            When I cried out, God of my righteousness heard me: in tribulation You have made room for me; have compassion upon me, O Lord, and hear my prayer.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            إذ دعوتُ استجبْتَ لي يا إلهَ برِّي. في الشدِّةِ فرَّجتَ عنِّي. تراءفْ عليَّ ياربُّ واسمعْ صلاتي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O you, sons of men, how long will your hearts be heavy? Why do you love vanity, and seek falsehood? Know you that the Lord has made His Holy One wondrous. The Lord hears me when I cry to Him. Be angry, and do not sin; feel sorrow upon your beds for what you say in your hearts. Offer the sacrifice of righteousness, and trust in the Lord.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يا بني البشرِ، حتَّى متى تثقلُ قلوبُكُم؟ لماذا تحبُّونَ الباطلَ وتبتغونَ الكذِبَ؟ اعلموا أنَّ الربَّ قد جعلَ صفيَّهُ عجَباً. الربُّ يستجيبُ لي إذا ما صرختُ إليهِ. اغضَبوا ولا تخطئوا، الذي تقولونُهُ في قلوبِكُم اندَموا عليهِ في مضاجِعِكُم. اذبحوا ذبيحةَ البرِّ، وتوَّكلوا على الربِّ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Many say, “Who can show us the good things?” The light of Your countenance, O Lord, has been shined upon us. You have given gladness to my heart; they have been multiplied with the fruit of their wheat and wine and oil. I shall both lie down in peace and sleep, for You alone, O Lord, have caused me to dwell in hope. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            كثيرونَ يقولونَ: مَنْ يُرينا الخيراتِ؟ قد أضاءَ علَينا نورُ وجهِكَ ياربُّ. أعطيتَ سروراً لقلبي أوفرَ مِنَ الذين كثُرتْ حنطتُهم وخمرُهم وزيتُهم. فبالسلامةِ أضطجعُ أيضاً وأنامُ، لأنَّكَ أنتَ وحدَكَ ياربُّ أسكنتَني على الرجاءِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 5 - Hearken, O Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الخامس - أنصتْ يا ربّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Hearken, O Lord, to my words and consider my cry. Observe the voice of my supplication, my King, and my God, for to You, O Lord, I will pray. In the morning You shall hear my voice; in the early morning I shall stand before You, and You will look upon me. For You are not a God who desires iniquity; nor shall he who works evil dwell in You; nor shall the transgressors abide before Your eyes. You have hated, O Lord, all who work iniquity. You will destroy all who speak falsehood. A man of blood and deceit the Lord abhors. 
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أنصِتْ ياربُّ لكلِماتي، واسمَعْ صُراخي. أصغِ إلى صوتِ طلبَتي يا مَلِكي وإلهي، لأني إليكَ أصلِّي. ياربُّ بالغداةِ تسمعُ صوتي، بالغداةِ أقِفُ أمامَكَ وتراني. لأنَّكَ إلهٌ لا تشاءُ الإثمَ، ولا يساكنُكَ مَنْ يصنعُ الشرَّ. ولا يثبتُ مُخالِفو الناموسِ أمامَ عينيكَ. ياربُّ أبغضتَ جميعَ فاعلي الإثمِ، وتُهلِكُ كلَّ الناطقينَ بالكَذبِ. رجلُ الدماءِ والغاشُّ يرذِلُهُ الربُّ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>

      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         But as for me, according to the multitude of Your mercy I shall enter Your house; I shall worship before Your holy temple in Your fear.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أمَّا أنا فبكثرةِ رحمتِكَ أدخلُ بيتَكَ، وأسجدُ قدَّامَ هيكلِ قدسِكَ بمخافتِكَ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Guide me, O Lord, in Your righteousness; for the sake of my enemies, make my way straight before You. For in their mouth there is no truth; their heart is vain; their throat is an open tomb; with their tongues they have done deceit. Judge them, O God; let them fall down in all their counsels. Wipe them out according to the abundance of their ungodliness; for they have provoked You, O Lord.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اهدِني ياربُّ ببرِّكَ. مِنْ أجلِ أعدائي سهِّلْ أمامي طريقَكَ. لأنَّ ليسَ في أفواهِهِم صِدقٌ. باطِلٌ هو قلبُهُم. حنجرتُهُم قبرٌ مفتوحٌ. وبألسنتِهِم قد غشُّوا. فدِنْهُم يا اللهُ. وليَسقطوا مِنْ جميعِ مؤامراتِهِم وككثرةِ نفاقِهِم استأصلْهُم، لأنَّهُم قد أغضَبوكَ ياربُّ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            But let all who hope in You be glad; they shall rejoice forever, and You shall dwell in them; and all who love Your name shall be proud in You. For You, O Lord, have blessed the righteous; as a shield of favor You have crowned us. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            وليفرحْ جميعُ المتَّكلينَ عليكَ، إلى الأبدِ يُسرُّونَ وتحِلُّ فيهِم. ويفتخرُ بكَ كلُّ الذين يحبُّون اسمَكَ. لأنَّكَ أنتَ بارَكتَ الصِدِّيقَ ياربُّ. كما بتُرسِ المسرَّةِ كلَّلتَنا. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 6 - O Lord, do not rebuke me...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور السادس - يا ربّ لا تُبكّتني...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord, do not rebuke me in Your anger, nor chasten me in Your wrath. Have mercy on me, O Lord, for I am weak; heal me, O Lord, for my bones are troubled, and my soul is grievously troubled. But You, O Lord, how long? Return, deliver my soul; revive me for the sake of Your mercy. For in death there is no one who is remembering You; and in Hades who is able to give thanks to You? I became wearied in my groaning; I shall wash my bed every night; I shall wet my couch with my tears. My eye is troubled because of anger; I have grown old because of all my enemies.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ياربُّ لا تُبكِّتْني بغضبِكَ، ولا تؤدِّبْني بسخطِكَ. ارحَمْني ياربُّ فإنِّي ضعيفٌ، اشفِني ياربُّ فإنَّ عظامي قد اضطربَتْ ونفسي قد انزعجَتْ جداً. وأنتَ ياربُّ فإلى متى؟ عُدْ ونجِّ نفسي، وأحيني مِنْ أجلِ رحمتِكَ. لأنَّه ليسَ في الموتِ مَنْ يذكرُكَ ولا في الجحيمِ مَنْ يعترفُ لكَ. تعبتُ في تنهُّدي. أعوِّمُ كلَّ ليلةٍ سَريري، وبدموعي أبِلُّ فِراشي. تعكَّرتْ مِنَ الغضبِ عينايَ. شاخَتْ مِنْ سائرِ أعدائي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Depart away from me, all who do iniquity, for the Lord has heard the voice of my weeping. The Lord has heard my petition; the Lord has accepted my prayer. All my enemies shall be put to shame and greatly troubled; they shall be turned back and put to shame speedily. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ابعدوا عنِّي يا جميعَ فاعلي الإثمِ. لأنَّ الربَّ قد سمعَ صوتَ بُكائي. الربُّ سمعَ تضرُّعي، الربُّ لصلاتي قبِلَ، فليخزَ وليضطرِبْ جداً جميعُ أعدائي، وليرتدُّوا إلى ورائهِم بالخزي سريعاً جِداً. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 8 - O Lord, our Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الثامن - أيها الربّ ربّنا...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord, our Lord, how wonderful Your name became in all the earth! For the greatness of Your splendor has been exalted above the heavens. Out of the mouth of babes and sucklings You have prepared praise, because of Your enemies, that You might put down an enemy and avenger.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أيها الربُّ ربُّنا، ما أعجبَ اسمَكَ في الأرضِ كلِّها! لأنهُ قد ارتفعَ عظمُ جلالِكَ فوقَ السماواتِ. مِنْ أفواهِ الأطفالِ والرُضعانِ هيأتَ سُبْحاً، مِنْ أجلِ أعدائكَ، لتُسكِتَ عدواً ومُنتقماً.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            For I will regard the heavens, the work of Your fingers; the moon and stars You have established. What is man, that You have been mindful of him? Or the son of man, that You have visited him? You made him a little less than angels; You have crowned him with glory and honor; and You have set him upon the works of Your hands. You have put everything under his feet; all the sheep and oxen, and the beasts of the field, and the birds of the sky, and the fish of the sea that pass through the paths of the seas. O Lord our Lord, how wonderful Your name became in all the earth! ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لأنِّي أرى السماواتِ أعمالَ أصابعِكَ. القمرُ والنجومُ أنتَ أسستَها. مَنْ هو الإنسانُ حتى تذكُرَه، أو ابنُ الإنسانِ حتى تفتقِدَه؟! أنقصتَهُ قليلاً عن الملائكةِ. بالمجدِ والكرامةِ توَّجتَهُ، وعلى أعمالِ يديكَ أقمتَهُ. كلَّ شيءٍ أخضعتَ تحتَ قدميهِ، الغنمَ والبقرَ جميعاً وأيضاً بهائمَ الحقلِ، وطيورَ السماءِ وأسماكَ البحرِ السالكةَ في البحارِ. أيها الربُّ ربُّنا. ما أعجبَ اسمَكَ في الأرضِ كلِّها. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 11 - Save me O Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الحادي عشر - خلصني يا ربّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Save me O Lord, for the godly one has ceased, and the truths have diminished from the children of men. Every one has spoken vanities to his friend. Deceiving lips are in their hearts, and thus they have spoken with their hearts. The Lord shall wipe out every deceiving lip, and every tongue that speaks great words; those who have said, “We will magnify our tongues; our lips are our own: who is lord over us?” “Because of the misery of the poor and the sighing of the oppressed, now I will rise,” says the Lord, “I will set them in salvation, and I will be revealed in it.”
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            خلِّصْني ياربُّ فإنَّ البارَّ قد فني، وقد قلَّتْ الأمانةُ مِنْ بني البشرِ. تكلَّمَ كلُّ واحدٍ مع قريبِهِ بالأباطيلِ. شفاهٌ غاشةٌ في قلوبِهِم وبقلوبِهِم تخاطبوا. يستأصِلُ الربُّ جميعَ الشفاهِ الغاشَّةِ، واللسانَ الناطقَ بالعظائمِ. الذين قالوا: نعظِّمُ ألسنتَنا شفاهُنا معنا، فمَنْ هو ربٌّ علينا؟! مِنْ أجلِ شقاءِ المساكينَ وتنهُّدِ البائسينَ الآنَ أقومُ، يقولُ الربُّ، أصنعُ الخلاصَ علانيةً.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The words of the Lord are pure words, as silver tried in the fire, proved in the earth, purified seven times. You, O Lord, shall keep us, and shall preserve us from this generation, and forever. The ungodly walk around: according to Your greatness You have prolonged the lives of the children of men. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            كلامُ الربِّ كلامٌ نقيٌ، فضةٌ محماةٌ مجربةٌ في الأرضِ، قد صُفيَّتْ سبعةَ أضعافٍ. وأنتَ ياربُّ تنجِّينا وتحفظُنا مِنْ هذا الجيلِ وإلى الدهرِ. المنافقونَ حولَنا يمشونَ. مِثلَ ارتفاعِكَ أكثرتَ أعمارَ بني البشرِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 12 -  How long, O Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الثاني عشر - إلى متى يا ربّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            How long, O Lord, do You forget me, for ever? How long do You turn Your face away from me? How long do I put these counsels in my soul, and these sorrows in my heart for the whole day? How long does my enemy exalt over me?
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            إلى متى ياربُّ تنساني؟ إلى الانقضاءِ؟ حتَّى متى تصرفُ وجهكَ عنِّي؟ إلى متى أردِّدُ هذهِ المشوراتِ في نفسي، وهذهِ الأوجاعَ في قلبي النهارَ كلَّهُ؟ إلى متى يرتفعُ عدوي عليَّ؟
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Look, hearken to me, O Lord my God: enlighten my eyes, lest I sleep in death; lest my enemy say, “I have prevailed against him;” those who distress me will rejoice if ever I stumble. But I have hoped in Your mercy; my heart will rejoice in Your salvation. I will praise the Lord who has done good to me, and I will sing to the name of the Lord Most High. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            انظرْ واستجِبْ لي يا ربِّي وإلهي. أنِرْ عينيَّ لئلا أنامُ نومَ الموتِ، لئلا يقولُ عدوِّي: إنِّي قد قويتُ علَيهِ. الذين يُحزنونَني يتهلَّلونَ إن أنا زللتُ. أمَّا أنا فعلى رحمتِكَ توَّكلتُ. يبتهجُ قلبي بخلاصِكَ. أسبِّحُ الربَّ المُحسنَ إليَّ، وأرتلُ لاسمِ الربِّ العليِّ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 14 - O Lord, who shall abide...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الرابع عشر - يا ربّ مَنْ يسكن...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord, who shall abide in Your dwelling place? And who can rest upon Your holy mountain? It is he who walks blamelessly, doing righteousness, speaking truth in his heart, he who has not spoken deceitfully with his tongue, neither has done evil to his friend, nor taken up a reproach against his neighbors. The evil worker is disdained before him, but he glorifies those who fear the Lord. He gives oath to his friend and does not turn away from him. He has not given his money on usury, and has not received bribes against the godly. He who does these things shall not stumble forever. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ياربُّ مَنْ يسكنُ في مسكنِكَ، ومَنْ يحلُّ في جبلِ قدسِكَ؟ السالكُ بلا عيبٍ والفاعلُ البرَّ، والمتكلمُ بالحقِّ في قلبِهِ، الذي لا يغشُّ بلسانِهِ، ولا يصنعُ بقريبِهِ سوءاً، ولا يقبلُ عاراً على جيرانِهِ. فاعلُ الشرَّ مرذولٌ أمامَهُ، ويمجِّدُّ الذين يتَّقونَ الربَّ. الذي يحلفُ لقريبِهِ ولا يغدرُ بهِ. ولا يُعطي فضَّتَهُ بالرِّبا، ولا يقبلُ الرِّشوةَ على الأبرياءِ. الذي يصنعُ هذا لا يتزعزعُ إلى الأبدِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 15 - Keep me, O Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الخامس عشر - إحفظني يا ربّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Keep me, O Lord, for I have hoped in You. I said to the Lord, “You are my Lord, and You have no need of my goodness.” He has manifested His wonders to His saints who are in His earth, and He has wrought all His desires in them. Their ailments have been multiplied who hastened after another god. I will not assemble their meetings of blood, nor make mention of their names with my lips. The Lord is the portion of my inheritance and my cup. You are He who brings my inheritance back to me. The measuring lines have fallen to me among the best, and my inheritance is confirmed for me.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            إحفظْني ياربُّ فإنِّي عليكَ توَّكلتُ. قلتُ للربِّ: أنتَ ربِّي، ولا تحتاجُ إلى صلاحي. أظهرَ عجائبَهُ لقديسيهِ الذين في أرضِهِ، وصنعَ فيهِم كلَّ مشيئاتِهِ. كثُرَتْ أمراضُهُم الذين أسرعوا وراءَ آخرٍ. لا أجمعُ مجامِعَهُم مِنَ الدماءِ، ولا أذكرُ أسماءَهُم بشفتيَّ. الربُّ هو نصيبُ مِيراثي وكأسي. أنتَ الذي تردُّ إليَّ مِيراثي. حبالُ المساحةِ وقعتْ لي في أرضٍ خصبةٍ، وإنَّ ميراثي لثابتٌ لي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            I will bless the Lord who has given me understanding; my reins too have instructed me even till the night. I foresaw the Lord always before me; He is on my right hand, that I should not be moved. Therefore my heart rejoiced and my tongue exulted; moreover also my flesh shall live in hope: because You shall not leave my soul in Hades, neither shall You suffer Your holy One to see corruption. You have made known to me the ways of life; You will fill me with joy with Your face; delight is in Your right hand forever.  ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أبارِكُ الربَّ الذي أفهمَني. وأيضاً إلى الليل تُنذِرُني كليتايَ. تقدمتُ فرأيتُ الربَّ أمامي في كلِّ حينٍ، لأنَّهُ عَن يميني لكي لا أتزعزعَ. مِنْ أجلِ هذا فرِحَ قلبي وتهلَّلَ لساني. وأيضاً جسدي يسكنُ على الرجاءِ. لأنَّكَ لا تتركُ نفسي في الجحيمِ. ولا تدَعُ قدوسَّكَ يرى فساداً. قد عرَّفتَني سُبُلَ الحياةِ. تملأُني فرحاً مع وجهِكَ. البهجةُ في يمينِكَ إلى الانقضاءِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 18 - The heavens declare...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الثامن عشر - السماواتُ تحدّثُ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The heavens declare the glory of God, and the firmament proclaims the work of His hands. Day to day utters speech, and night to night proclaims knowledge. There are no speeches or words, in which their voice is not heard. Their sound has gone out upon all the earth, and their words have reached to the ends of the world. In the sun He has set His dwelling, and it comes forth as a bridegroom out of his chamber; it shall exult as a giant running his course. Its going forth is from the extremity of heaven, and its goal is to the other end of heaven, and nothing will be hidden from its heat.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            السماواتُ تحدِّثُ بمجدِ اللهِ، والفَلَكُ يخبرُ بعملِ يديهِ. يومٌ إلى يومٍ يُبدي قولاً. وليلٌ إلى ليلٍ يُظهِرُ عِلماً. لا قولَ ولا كلامَ. لا تُسمَعُ أصواتُهُم، في كلِّ الأرضِ خرجَ منطِقُهُم. وإلى أقصى المسكونةِ بلغَتْ أقوالُهُم. جعلَ في الشمسِ مظلَّتَهُ. وهي مثلِ العريسِ الخارجِ مِنْ خدرِهِ. تتهلَّلُ مِثلِ الجبارِ الذي يسرعُ في طريقِهِ. مِنْ أقصى السماءِ خروجُها، ومنتهاها إلى أقصى السماءِ ولا شيءٌ يختفي مِنْ حرارتِها.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The law of the Lord is pure, converting souls; the testimony of the Lord is faithful, instructing the babes. The ordinances of the Lord are straight, rejoicing the heart; the commandment of the Lord is a light, enlightening the eyes from afar. The fear of the Lord is pure, enduring forever and ever; the judgments of the Lord are true, and justified altogether. The desires of His heart are chosen more than gold and precious stone, and sweeter than honey and the honeycomb. For Your servant keeps them; and in keeping them there is great reward.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ناموسُ الربِّ بِلا عيبٍ، يردُّ النفوسَ. شهادةُ الربِّ صادقةٌ، تعلِّمُ الأطفالَ. فرائضُ الربِّ مستقيمةٌ، تفرِّحُ القلبَ. وصيةُ الربِّ مضيئةٌّ، تنيرُ العينينِ عن بُعدٍ. خشيةُ الربِّ زكيةٌ، دائمةٌ إلى أبدِ الأبدِ. أحكامُ الربِّ أحكامُ حقٍّ وعادلةٌ معاً. شهوةُ قلبِهِ مختارةٌ. أفضلَ مِنَ الذهبِ والحجرِ الكثيرِ الثمنِ، وأحلى مِنَ العسلِ والشَّهدِ. عبدُكَ يحفظُها، وفي حفظِها ثوابٌ عظيمٌ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Who can understand transgressions? From my secret sins cleanse me, O Lord, and from the attack of strangers spare Your servant. Let them not have dominion over me, then I shall be blameless, and I shall be cleansed from great sin. All the sayings of my mouth, and the meditation of my heart, shall be pleasing continually before You. O Lord, You are my helper, and my Savior. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الهفواتُ مَنْ يشعرُ بِها؟ مِنَ الخطايا المُستَتِرةِ ياربُّ طهِّرْني، ومِنَ الغُرباءِ احفظْ عبدَكَ حتَّى لا يتسلَّطوا عليَّ، فحينئذٍ أكونُ بِلا عيبٍ، وأتنقَّى مِنْ خَطيئَةٍ عظيمةٍ. وتكونُ جميعُ أقوالِ فمِي وفكرُ قلبي مرضيَّةً أمامَكَ في كلِّ حينٍ. ياربُّ أنتَ مُعيني ومُخلِّصي. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 24 - To You, O Lord...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الرابع والعشرون - إليكَ يا ربّ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            To You, O Lord, I have lifted up my soul. O my God, I have trusted in You; let me not be ashamed forever, nor let my enemies mock me. For all who wait for You shall not be ashamed; let them be ashamed who wrought iniquity in vain. Show me Your ways, O Lord, and teach me Your paths. Lead me to Your truth, and teach me; for You are God my Savior; and for You I have waited the whole day. Remember, O Lord, Your compassions and Your mercies, for they exist from everlasting. The sins of my youth and those of my ignorance do not remember; and according to Your mercy remember me, for the sake of Your goodness, O Lord.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            إليكَ ياربُّ رفعتُ نفسي، يا إلهي عليكَ توَّكلتُ. فلا تُخزِني إلى الأبدِ، ولا تشْمتْ بي أعدائي. لأنَّ جميعَ الذين ينتظرونَكَ لا يُخزَونَ. ليُخزَ الذين يصنعون الإثمَ باطِلاً. أظهِرْ لي ياربُّ طُرقَكَ، وعلِّمْني سُبُلَكَ. اهدِني إلى عدلِكَ وعلِّمْني. لأنَّكَ أنتَ هو اللهُ مُخلِّصي، وإياكَ انتظرتُ النهارَ كلَّهُ. اذكُرْ ياربُّ رأفاتِكَ ومراحِمَكَ، لأنَّها ثابتةٌ مُنذُ الأزلِ. خطايا شبابي وجهالاتي لا تذكُرْ. كرحمَتِكَ اذكُرْني أنتَ مِنْ أجلِ صلاحِكَ ياربُّ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            For good and upright is the Lord; therefore He shall set a law for those who sin in the way. He shall guide the meek in judgment. He shall teach the meek His ways. All the ways of the Lord are mercy and truth to those who keep His covenant and His testimonies. For the sake of Your name, O Lord, You shall forgive my sin, for it is great.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الربُّ صالِحٌ ومُستقيمٌ، لذلِكَ يُرشِدُ الذين يُخطئونَ في الطريقِ. يَهدي الودعاءَ في الحُكمِ، يُعلِّمُ الودعاءَ طُرُقَهُ. جميعُ طُرُقِ الربِّ رحمةٌ وحقٌ لحافِظي عهدِهِ وشهاداتِهِ. مِنْ أجلِ اسمِكَ ياربُّ اغفِرْ لي خَطيئَتِي لأنَّها كثيرةٌ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Who is the man that fears the Lord? He shall set a law for him in the way which pleases Him. His soul shall dwell in good things, and his seed shall inherit the earth. The Lord is the strength of those who fear Him, and the name of the Lord is for those who revere Him, and His covenant He will manifest to them. My eyes are ever looking towards the Lord, for He will draw my feet out of the snare.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            مَنْ هو الإنسانُ الخائفُ الربَّ، يُرشِدُهُ في الطريقِ التي ارتضاها. نفسُهُ في الخيراتِ تثبتُ، ونسلُهُ يرثُ الأرضَ. الربُّ عِزٌّ لخائفيهِ، واسمُ الربِّ لأتقيائِهِ. ولهُم يُعلنُ عهدَهُ. عينايَ تنظُرانِ إلى الربِّ في كلِّ حينٍ، لأنَّهُ يجتذِبُ مِنَ الفخِّ رِجلِي.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Look upon me, and have mercy on me, for I am an only child and poor. The afflictions of my heart have been multiplied; bring me out of my troubles. Behold my lowliness and my toil, and forgive all my sins. Look upon my enemies, for they have multiplied, and they have hated me with an unjust hatred. Keep my soul, and deliver me. Let me not be put to shame, for I have hoped in You. The harmless and upright joined themselves to me, for I waited for You, O Lord. Deliver Israel, O God, out of all his afflictions. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            انظُرْ إليَّ وارحَمْني، لأنِّي ابنٌ وحيدٌ وفقيرٌ أنا. أحزانُ قلبي قد كثُرَتْ، أخرِجْني مِنْ شَدائدي. انظُرْ إلى ذُلِّي وتعبي. واغفِرْ لي جميعَ خطايايَ. انظُرْ إلى أعدائي فإنَّهُم قد كثُروا وأبغضوني ظُلْماً. احفظْ نَفسي ونجِّني، لا أُخزى لأنِّي عليكَ توَّكلتُ. الذين لا شرَّ فيهِم والمستقيمونَ لصقوا بي، لأنِّي انتظرتُكَ ياربُّ. يا اللهُ أنقِذْ إسرائيلَ مِنْ جميعِ شدائدِهِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 26 - The Lord is my light...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور السادس والعشرون - الربّ نوري...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Lord is my light and my salvation; whom will I fear? The Lord is the defender of my life; of whom will I be afraid? When the wicked drew near against me to eat up my flesh, those who distress me and my enemies, they fainted and fell. Though an army should fight me, my heart shall not be afraid; though war should rise up against me, in this I am confident.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            الربُّ نوري وخلاصي مِمَنْ أخافُ؟! الربُّ حِصنُ حياتي مِمَنْ أجزعُ؟! عِندما يقترِبُ الأشرارُ مني ليأكلوا لَحمي، مُضايقيَّ وَأعدائي عثَروا وسقَطوا. إن يُحاربْني جيشٌ فلَن يخافَ قلبي. وإن قامَ عليَّ قتالٌ ففي هذا أنا أطمئنُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         One thing I have asked of the Lord, this also I will seek, that I should dwell in the house of the Lord all the days of my life, that I should behold the fair beauty of the Lord, and visit His holy temple. For in the day of my afflictions He hid me in His tabernacle; He sheltered me in the secret of His tabernacle; He set me up on a rock. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         واحدةً سألتُ مِنَ الربِّ وإيَّاها ألتمسُ. أن أسكنَ في بيتِ الربِّ كلَّ أيامِ حياتي. لكي أنظرَ نعيمَ الربِّ، وأتفرسَ في هيكلِهِ المُقدسِ. لأنَّه أخفاني في خيمتِهِ. في يومِ شِدَّتي، ستَرَني بسِترِ مظلَّتِهِ. وعلى صخرةٍ رفعَني.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            And now, behold, He has lifted up my head over my enemies; I went round and offered in His tabernacle a sacrifice of joy; I shall sing, and sing psalms to the Lord.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            والآنَ هوذا قد رفعَ رأسي على أعدائي. طُفتُ وذَبحتُ في مظلَّتِهِ ذبيحةَ التهليلِ، أسبِّحُ وأرتِّلُ للربِّ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Hear, O Lord, my voice which I have uttered aloud; have mercy on me, and hearken to me. For You are He to whom my heart said, “I have sought Your face; Your face, O Lord, I will seek.” Do not turn away Your face from me, do not reject Your servant in anger. Be a helper to me, and do not forsake me; and do not overlook me, O God my Savior. For my father and my mother have forsaken me, but the Lord has accepted me unto Himself. Set a law for me, O Lord, in Your ways, and guide me in a right path, because of my enemies. Do not deliver me over to the hands of those who afflict me; for unjust witnesses have risen up against me, and injustice has lied to itself. I believe that I shall see the goodness of the Lord in the land of the living. Wait for the Lord; be of good cheer and let your heart be strengthened, and wait for the Lord. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            استمِعْ يا ربُّ صوتي الذي بِهِ دعوتُكَ. ارحَمْني واستجِبْ لي فإنَّهُ لكَ قالَ قلبي: طلبتُ وجهَكَ، ووجهَكَ يا ربُّ ألتمِسُ. لا تحجُبْ وجهَكَ عنِّي، ولا تنبُذْ بغضبٍ عبدكَ. كُنْ لي مُعيناً، لا تخذِلْني ولا ترفُضْني يا اللهُ مُخلِّصي. فإنَّ أبي وأمِّي قد ترَكاني، وأمَّا الربُّ فقبِلَني. علِّمْني ياربُّ طريقَكَ، واهدِني في سبيلٍ مُستقيمٍ مِنْ أجلِ أعدائي. لا تُسلِّمْني إلى أيدي مُضايقيَّ، لأنَّهُ قد قامَ عليَّ شهودُ زورٍ، وكذِبوا عليَّ ظُلماً. وأنا أؤمِنُ أني أعاينُ خيراتِ الربِّ في أرضِ الأحياءِ. انتظرْ الربَّ، تقوَّ وليتشدَدْ قلبُكَ وانتظرْ الربَّ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 62 - O God, my God...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور الثاني والستون - يا اللهُ إلهي...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O God, my God, I will rise up early unto You; for my soul has thirsted for You, to make my flesh blossom for You, in a barren land and a trackless and dry place. So I have appeared before You in the Holy, to see Your power and Your glory. For Your mercy is chosen more than life; my lips shall praise You. So I will bless You during my life; I will lift up my hands in Your name. My soul shall be filled as with marrow and fatness; and my lips of joy shall praise Your name.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            يا اللهُ إلهي إليكَ أبكِّرُ، عطِشتْ إليكَ نفسي. يشتاقُ إليكَ جسدي، في أرضٍ مقفرةٍ وموضعٍ غيرِ مسلوكٍ ومكانٍ بِلا ماءٍ. هكذا ظهرتُ لكَ في القُدْسِ، لأرى قوّتَكَ ومجدَكَ. لأنَّ رحمتَكَ أفضلَ مِنَ الحياةِ. شفتايَ تُسبِّحانِكَ. لذلكَ أبارِكُكَ في حياتي، وباسمِكَ أرفعُ يديَّ. فتشبعُ نفسي كما مِنْ شحمٍ ودسمٍ. بشفاهِ الابتهاجِ نبارِكُ اسمَكَ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            I have remembered You on my bed; in the time of early morning I have usually meditated on You. For You have become unto me a helper, and under the shadow of Your wings I shall rejoice. My soul has kept very close behind You; Your right hand has upheld me. But those who seek to destroy my soul, shall go into the lowest parts of the earth. They shall be delivered up to the hand of the sword; they shall be portions for foxes. But the king shall rejoice in God; everyone who swears by him shall be proud; for the mouths of those who speak unjust things shall be shut. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            كنتُ أذكرُكَ على فِراشي، وفي أوقاتِ الأسحارِ كنتُ أرتِّلُ لكَ. لأنَّكَ صِرتَ لي عَوناً، وبظلِّ جناحيكَ أبتهِجُ. التحقتْ نفسي وراءَكَ، ويمينُكَ عضَّدَتْني. أمَّا الذين طلبوا نفسي للهلاكِ، فيدخلونَ في أسافلِ الأرضِ. ويُدفعون إلى يدِّ السيفِ، ويكونون أنصِبةً للثعالبِ. أمَّا الملِكُ فيفرحُ باللهِ، ويفتخِرُ كلُّ مَنْ يحلفُ بِهِ. لأنَّ أفواهَ المتكلِّمين بالظلمِ تُسَدُّ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 66 - God shall pity us...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور السادس والستون - ليتراءفْ اللهُ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            God shall pity us, and bless us, and reveal His face upon us and have mercy on us; that Your way may be known on the earth, Your salvation among all nations. Let the peoples, O God, give praise to You; let all the peoples give praise to You. Let the nations rejoice and exult, for You will judge peoples in equity, and guide nations on the earth. Let the peoples, O God, give praise to You; let all the peoples give praise to You. The earth has yielded its fruit. God, our God, shall bless us; God shall bless us, and all the ends of the earth shall fear Him. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ليتراءفْ اللهُ علَينا ويبارِكْنا، وليُظهِرْ وجهَهُ علينا ويرحمْنا. لتُعرَفْ في الأرضِ طريقُكَ، وفي جميعِ الأممِ خلاصُكَ. فلتعترفْ لكَ الشعوبُ يا اللهُ، فلتعترفْ لكَ الشعوبُ كلُّها. لتفرحْ الأممُ وتبتهجُ، لأنَّكَ تحكُمُ في الشعوبِ بالاستقامةِ، وتهدي الأممَ في الأرضِ. فلتعترفْ لكَ الشعوبُ يا اللهُ، فلتعترفْ لكَ الشعوبُ جميعاً. الأرضُ أعطتْ ثمرتَها، فليبارِكْنا اللهُ إلهُنا. ليبارِكْنا اللهُ، فلتَخشَهُ جميعُ أقطارِ الأرضِ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 69 - O God, be mindful...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور التاسع والستون - اللهُمّ التفِتْ إلى معونَتي...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O God, be mindful to my help; make haste, O Lord, to help me. Let them be ashamed and be scorned, those who seek my soul; let them be turned backward and put to shame, those who wish to do evil unto me. Let those who say to me, “Aha, aha,” be turned back in shame immediately. Let all who seek You exult and be glad in You, and let those who love Your salvation say continually, “Let the Lord be magnified.” But I am poor and weak, O God, help me. You are my Helper and Savior, O Lord, do not delay. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            اللهُمَّ التفِتْ إلى معونَتي، ياربُّ أسرعْ وأعِنِّي. ليُخزَ ويخجلْ طالِبو نفسي، وليرتدّْ إلى خلفٍ ويخجلْ الذين يبتغونَ ليَ الشرَّ. وليرجعْ بالخزي سريعاً القائلونَ لي: نَعِمَّاً نَعِمَّاً. وليبتهِجْ ويفرحْ بكَ جميعُ الذين يلتمِسونَكَ، وليقُلْ في كلِّ حينٍ مُحِبُّو خلاصِكَ: فليتعظمْ الربُّ. وأمَّا أنا فمسكينٌ وفقيرٌ، اللهُمَّ أعِنِّي. أنتَ مُعيني ومُخلِّصي ياربُّ فلا تُبطئْ. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 112 - Praise the Lord, O the servants...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمورُ المائةُ والثانيَ عشرَ - سبِّحُوا الربَّ أيها الفِتيانُ...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Praise the Lord, O the servants, praise the name of the Lord. Let the name of the Lord be blessed, from now and forever. From the risings of the sun to its settings, praise the name of the Lord. The Lord is high above all the nations; upon the heavens is His glory.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            سبِّحُوا الربَّ أيها الفِتيانُ، سبِّحُوا اسمَ الربِّ. ليكُنْ اسمُ الربِّ مُبارَكاً مِنَ الآنَ وإلى الأبدِ. مِنْ مشارِقِ الشمسِ إلى مغارِبِها بارِكُوا اسمَ الربِّ. الربُّ عالٍ على كلِّ الأممِ وفوقَ السماواتِ مجدُهُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Who is like the Lord our God? Who dwells in the high places, and looks upon the low things in heaven and on the earth, who lifts up a poor person from the earth, and raises up a needy person from the ash heap, to seat him with the princes, even with the princes of his people, who makes a barren woman in a house, rejoicing as a mother of children. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            مَنْ مِثلِ الربِّ إلهِنا؟! الساكنُ في الأعالي الناظرُ إلى المتواضعينَ في السماءِ وعلى الأرضِ، المُقيمُ المسكينَ مِنَ الترابِ، الرافعُ البائسَ مِنَ المَزبلةِ، لكي يُجلِسَهُ معَ رؤساءِ شعبِهِ. الذي يجعلُ العاقرَ ساكِنةً في بيتٍ أمَّ أولادٍ فرِحةً هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Psalm 142 - O Lord, hear my prayer...
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            المزمور المائة والثاني والأربعون - يا ربّ اسمعْ صلاتي...
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord, hear my prayer; give ear to my supplication in Your truth; hearken to me in Your justice. And do not enter into judgment with Your servant, for in Your sight no one living shall be justified.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ياربُّ اسمعْ صلاتي. انصِتْ إلى طِلبتي بحقِّكَ. استجِبْ لي بعدلِكَ. ولا تدخُلْ في المُحاكمةِ معَ عبدِكَ، فإنَّهُ لن يتزكَّى قدَّامَكَ كلُّ حيٍ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            For the enemy has persecuted my soul; he has humbled my life down to the ground; he has made me to sit in darkness, as those who have been long dead. Therefore, my spirit grieves in me; my heart is troubled within me. I remembered the days of old, and I meditated on all Your doings; I meditated on the works of Your hands. I spread forth my hands unto You; my soul is toward You as a dry land.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            لأنَّ العدوَّ قد اضطهدَ نفسي، وأذلَّ في الأرضِ حياتي. أجلسَني في الظُلماتِ مثلَ الموتى منذُ الدهرِ، إضجرَ فيَّ رُوحي، اضطربَ فيَّ قلبي. تذكَّرتُ الأيامَ الأولى ولَهجتُ في كلِّ أعمالِكَ، وفي صنائعِ يديكَ كنتُ أتأملُ. بسَطتُ إليكَ يديَّ، صارتْ نَفسي لكَ مثلَ أرضٍ بِلا ماءٍ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
       
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Hear me quickly, O Lord, for my spirit has failed; do not turn away Your face from me, or I will be like those who go down to the pit. Let me hear Your mercy in the morning, for in You do I hope; make known to me, O Lord, the way in which I should walk, for I have lifted up my soul to You. Deliver me from my enemies, O Lord, for I have fled to You. Teach me to do Your will, for You are my God; Let Your Holy Spirit guide me in the straight way. You shall revive me, O Lord, for Your name's sake; in Your righteousness You shall bring my soul out of affliction. And in Your mercy You will wipe out my enemies, and destroy all who afflict my soul; for I am Your servant. ALLELUIA.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            استجِبْ لي ياربُّ عاجِلاً، فقد فنيَتْ روحي. لا تحجُبْ وجهَكَ عنِّي، فأشابِهُ الهابطينَ في الجُبِّ. فلأسمَعْ في الغدَواتِ رحمَتَكَ، فإنِّي علَيكَ توكَّلتُ. عرِّفْني ياربُّ الطريقَ التي أسلكُ فيها، لأنِّي إليكَ رفعتُ نفسي. انقِذْني مِنْ أعدائي ياربُّ، فإنِّي لجأتُ إليكَ. علِّمْني أن أصنعَ مشيئتَكَ، لأنكَ أنتَ هو إلهي. روحُكَ القُدُّوسُ فليهدِني إلى الاستقامةِ، مِنْ أجلِ اسمِكَ ياربُّ تُحييني. بحقِّكَ تُخرِجُ مِنَ الشدَّةِ نَفسي، وبرحمتِكَ تستأصِلُ أعدائي. وتُهلِكُ جميعَ مُضايقي نَفسي، لأنِّي أنا هو عبدُكَ أنا. هَلِّلُويا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Role id="Introduction">
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Holy, holy, holy. A reading  from the Holy Gospel according to our teacher Saint John. May his blessings be with us all. Amen. 
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            قدوسٌ، قدوسٌ، قدوسٌ، فصلٌ مِنْ بِشارةِ الإنجيلِ لمُعلِّمِنا مارِ يوحنا البشيرِ بركتِهِ على جميعِنا. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>      
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Role>
   
   <ns0:Role id="Reader">
      <ns0:Section expanded="true">
         <ns0:Title>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Gospel (John 1:1-17)
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               إنجيل يوحنا 1: 1-17
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Title>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. He was in the beginning with God. All things were made by Him, and without Him was not anything made that was made. In Him was life, and the life was the light of men. And the light shines in darkness, and the darkness did not comprehend it.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               في البدءِ كانَ الكَلمةُ، والكَلمةُ كانَ عِندَ اللهِ. وكانَ الكَلمةُ اللهَ. هذا كانَ في البدءِ عِندَ اللهِ. كلُّ شيءٍ بِهِ كانَ، وبغيرِهِ لَم يكُن شيءٌ مِمَّا كانَ. فيهِ كانَتْ الحياةُ، والحياةُ كانَتْ نورَ الناسِ، والنورُ أضاءَ في الظُلمةِ، والظُلمةُ لَم تُدرِكْهُ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
               
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               There was a man sent from God, whose name was John. This man came for a witness, to bear witness of the Light, that all men through him might believe. He was not the Light, but was sent to bear witness to the Light. That was the true Light that gives light to every man coming into the world. He was in the world, and the world was made by Him, and the world did not know Him. He came unto His own, and His own did not receive Him. But as many as received Him, to them He gave power to become children of God, to those who believe in His name; who were born, not of blood, nor of the will of the flesh, nor of the will of man, but of God.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               كانَ إنسانٌ مُرسَلٌ مِنَ اللهِ اسمُهُ يوحنّا. هذا جاءَ للشهادةِ ليَشهدَ للنورِ، ليؤمنَ الكلُّ بواسطتِهِ. لَم يكُنْ هو النورَ، بَل ليشهدَ للنورِ. كانَ النورُ الحقيقي الذي ينيرُ كلَّ إنسانٍ آتياً إلى العالمِ. كانَ في العالمِ، وكُوِّنَ العالمُ بِهِ، ولَم يعرِفْهُ العالمُ. إلى خاصَّتِهِ جاءَ، وخاصَّتُهُ لَم تقبلْهُ. وأمَّا الذينَ قبِلوهُ فأعطاهُم سُلطاناً أن يصيروا أبناءَ اللهِ، الذين يؤمِنونَ باسمِهِ، الذين وُلِدوا ليسَ مِنْ دَمٍ، ولا مِنْ مشيئةِ جسدٍ، ولا مِنْ مشيئةِ رجلٍ، لكِنْ مِنَ اللهِ وُلِدوا.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
               
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               And the Word became flesh, and dwelt among us, and we beheld His glory, the glory as of the only-begotten of His Father, full of grace and truth. John bore witness of Him, and cried out, saying, “This was He of whom I said, `He who comes after me is preferred before me: for He was before me.’” And of His fullness we have all received, and grace for grace. For the law was given by Moses, but grace and truth came through Jesus Christ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               والكَلِمةُ صارَ جسداً وحلَّ بَينَنا، ورأينا مجدَهُ، مِثلَ مجدِ ابنٍ وحيدٍ لأبيهِ مملوءاً نعمةً وحقاً. يوحنّا شهِدَ لهُ وصرخَ قائلاً: "هذا هو الذي قلتُ عنهُ: ’إنَّ الذي يأتي بَعدي كانَ قَبلي، لأنَّهُ كانَ أقدمَ مِنِّي.‘" ونحنُ جميعاً أخذْنا مِنْ مِلئهِ، ونِعمةً عِوَضاً عن نِعمةٍ. لأنَّ الناموسَ بمُوسى أُعطِيَ، أمَّا النِّعمةَ والحقَّ فبيسوعَ المسيحِ صارا.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Section>
   </ns0:Role>
         
   <ns0:Role id="Priest">
       <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲇⲟⲝⲁ ⲥⲓ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ ⲏ̀ⲙⲱⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Glory be to God forever. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            والمجْدُ للهِ دَائماً
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>      
      
      <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         May the sayings of God be fulfilled in peace.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليكمُلْ قولُ اللهِ بسلامٍ.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="NativityPeriod | NativityParamoun | Circumcision">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               From the Paramoun of the Nativity to the Feast of the Circumcision:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲩⲙⲁⲥⲕ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You were born and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ وُلِدتَ وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="TheophanyPeriod | TheophanyParamoun">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               From Paramoun of the Theophany until the 12th of Tobe:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲕϭⲓⲱⲙⲥ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You were baptized and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ أعتمدت وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="PaschaWeek | Pascha | FeastOfTheCross | (FuneralTune ^ FuneralPrayer) | GeneralFuneralPrayer">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               On the two Feasts of the Cross, during Holy Pascha Week, and during funerals:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲩⲁϣⲕ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You were crucified and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ صلبت وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="!ThirdProstration ^ (Joyful29thOfTheMonthRaw | PentecostPeriod | (Sundays ^ ApostlesFastToLastDayOfHathor))">
         <ns0:Comment>
      <ns0:Language id="English">         
         On joyful days (see note in About Menu for details):
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Comment>
<ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲕⲧⲱⲛⲕ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You have risen and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنكَ قمت وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="Other">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               On standard days of the year and on fasting days:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ ⲱ̀ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲉⲕⲓⲱⲧ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲁⲑⲟⲥ: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ϫⲉ ⲁⲕⲓ̀ ⲁⲕⲥⲱϯ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               We worship You, O Christ, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, for You have come and saved us. Have mercy on us.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               نسجدُ لكَ أيها المسيحُ، معَ أبيكَ الصالحِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، لأنَّكَ أتيتَ وخلَّصتَنا. [ارحَمْنا]
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group> 
</ns0:Role>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">Litanies</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">طلبةٌ</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
         
      <ns0:Role id="Reader">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               1. O the true Light who gives light to every man coming into the world, You came into the world through Your love for mankind, and all creation rejoiced in Your coming. You saved our father, Adam, from the deception, and delivered our mother, Eve, from the pangs of death, and gave us the spirit of sonship. Let us, therefore, praise You and bless You, saying:
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               1. أيها النورُ الحقيقيُ الذي يضيءُ لكلِّ إنسانٍ آتٍ إلى العالمِ، أتيتَ إلى العالمِ بمحبتِكَ للبشرِ، وكلُّ الخليقةِ تهلَّلتْ بمجيئِكَ. خلَّصتَ أبانا آدمَ مِنَ الغوايةِ، وعتقتَ أمَّنا حواءَ مِنْ طلقاتِ الموتِ، وأعطيتَنا روحَ البنوةِ، نسبِّحُكَ ونبارِكُكَ قائلينَ:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Role>
            
      <ns0:Role id="People">
      <ns0:Text forceLanguage="Coptic">
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲇⲟⲝⲁ Ⲡⲁⲧⲣⲓ ⲕⲉ Ⲩⲓⲱ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲱ Ⲡⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁⲧⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجدُ للآبِ والابنِ والرّوحِ القُدُسِ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Role>
<ns0:Role id="Reader">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               2. As the daylight shines upon us, O Christ our God, the true Light, let the luminous senses and the bright thoughts shine within us, and do not let the darkness of passions hover over us, that mindfully we may praise You with David, saying, “My eyes hastened to awake before the dawn, that I might meditate on Your sayings.”  Hear our voices according to Your great mercy, and deliver us, O Lord our God, through Your compassion.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               2. إذا ما دخلَ إلينا وقتُ الصباحِ أيها المسيحُ إلهُنا النورُ الحقيقيُ، فلتُشرِقْ فينا الحواسُّ المضيئةُ والأفكارُ النُورانيَّةُ. ولا تُغطِّينا ظلمةُ الآلامِ، لكي نسبِّحَكَ عقليَّاً معَ داودَ قائلينَ: "سبقَتْ عينايَ وقتَ السَحَرِ لأتلوَ في جميعِ أقوالِكَ". اسمَعْ أصواتَنا كعظيمِ رحمتِكَ، ونجِّنا أيها الربُّ إلهُنا بتحنُّنِكَ.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Role>
      
      <ns0:Role id="People">
      <ns0:Text forceLanguage="Coptic">
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲕⲉ ⲛⲩⲛ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲓ̀ ⲕⲉ ⲓⲥ ⲧⲟⲩⲥ ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲁⲥ ⲧⲱⲛ ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲱⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.         
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.      
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Role>
<ns0:Role id="Reader">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               3. You are the honored Mother of the Light; from the risings of the sun to its settings praises are offered to you, O Theotokos, the second heaven, for you are the bright and unchanging flower, and the ever-virgin mother; for the Father chose you, and the Holy Spirit overshadowed you, and the Son condescended and took flesh from you. Therefore, ask Him to give salvation to the world which He created, and to deliver it from all tribulations. Let us praise Him a new praise and bless Him. Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               3. أنتِ هي أمُّ النورِ المكرَّمةُ، مِنْ مشارِقِ الشمسِ إلى مغارِبِها يقدِّمونَ لكِ تمجيداتٍ يا والدةَ الإلهِ السماءَ الثانيةَ، لأنكِ أنتِ هي الزهرةُ النيّرةُ غيرُ المُتغيِّرةِ والأمُّ الباقيةُ عذراءً، لأنَّ الآبَ اختارَكِ، والرّوحَ القُدُسَ ظلَّلَكِ، والابنَ تنازلَ وتجسدَ منكِ. فاسأليهِ أن يعطيَ الخلاصَ للعالمِ الذي خلقَهُ، وأن ينجيَّهُ مِنَ التجاربِ. نسبِّحُهُ تسبيحاً جديداً ونبارِكُهُ الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى الأبدِ. آمين.
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Role>
   </ns0:Section>
    
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            The Gloria
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            تسبِحةُ الملائكةِ
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲛϩⲱⲥ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲓⲁⲅⲅⲉⲗⲟⲥ ϫⲉ ⲟⲩⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲏⲉⲧϭⲟⲥⲓ ⲙ̀Ⲫϯ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲟⲩϩⲓⲣⲏⲛⲏ ϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲕⲁϩⲓ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲟⲩϯⲙⲁϯ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲣⲱⲙⲓ. Ⲧⲉⲛϩⲱⲥ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ ⲧⲉⲛⲥ̀ⲙⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ: ⲧⲉⲛϣⲉⲙϣⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ: ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲕ: ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱⲛϩ ⲛⲁⲕ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ⲧⲉⲛⲥⲁϫⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲉⲕⲱ̀ⲟⲩ: ⲧⲉⲛϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲟⲧⲕ: ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲛⲓϣϯ ⲛ̀ⲱ̀ⲟⲩ. Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲡⲓⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲉⲧϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: Ⲫϯ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲡⲓⲡⲁⲛⲧⲟⲕⲣⲁⲧⲱⲣ: Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲡⲓϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁⲩⲁⲧϥ ⲡⲓⲙⲟⲛⲟⲅⲉⲛⲏⲥ Ⲓⲏ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̅ⲛ̅ⲁ̅ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Let us praise with the angels, saying, “Glory to God in the highest, peace on earth, and good will toward men.” We praise You, we bless You, we serve You, we worship You, we confess to You, we glorify You, we give thanks to You for Your great glory, O Lord, King of heaven, God the Father, the Pantocrator. O Lord, the one and only-begotten Son, Jesus Christ, and the Holy Spirit.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            فَلْنُسبِّحْ مَعَ الملائِكةِ قائِلينَ: المجْدُ للهِ في الأعالي، وعَلى الأرْضِ السَّلامُ، وَفي النّاسِ المسَرَّةُ؛ نُسَبِّحُكَ، نُبارِكُكَ، نَخْدمُكَ، نَسْجُدُ لَكَ، نَعْترِفُ لكَ، نَنْطقُ بمَجْدِكَ، نَشْكُرُكَ مِنْ أجْل عِظَمِ مَجْدِكَ. أيها الرَّبُّ المالِكُ عَلى السَّمواتِ، اللهُ الآبُ ضابِطُ الكُلِّ. والرَّبُ الابنُ الواحدُ الوَحيدُ يسوعُ المسيحُ، والرّوحُ القُدُسُ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲫϯ ⲡⲓϩⲓⲏⲃ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ Ⲫϯ: ⲡⲓϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲫⲏⲉⲧⲱ̀ⲗⲓ ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲓⲕⲟⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲫⲏⲉⲧⲱ̀ⲗⲓ ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲓⲕⲟⲥⲙⲟⲥ ϣⲉⲡ ⲡⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ. Ⲫⲏⲉⲧϩⲉⲙⲥⲓ ⲥⲁⲟⲩⲓ̀ⲛⲁⲙ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲉϥⲓⲱⲧ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ. Ⲛⲑⲟⲕ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁⲩⲁⲧⲕ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅: ⲛ̀ⲑⲟⲕ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁⲩⲁⲧⲕ ⲉⲧϭⲟⲥⲓ: Ⲡⲁⲟ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲓⲏ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅: ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡⲓⲡ̅ⲛ̅ⲁ̅ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅: ⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲙ̀Ⲫϯ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord God, Lamb of God, Son of the Father, who takes away the sin of the world, have mercy on us. O You who takes away the sin of the world, receive our prayers unto You, who sits at the right hand of His Father, have mercy on us. You only are the Holy, You only are the Most High, my Lord Jesus Christ, with the Holy Spirit. Glory be to God the Father. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أيها الرِّبُّ الإلَهُ، حَمَلَ اللهِ، ابْنَ الآبِ، رافِعَ خَطِيئَةِ العالَمِ ارحَمْنا. يا حَامِلَ خَطيئَةِ العالَمِ، اقْبَل طَلَباتِنا إليكَ. أيها الجالسُ عَنْ يَمينِ أبيهِ ارحَمْنا. أنْتَ وحْدَكَ القُدُّوسُ. أنْتَ وحْدَكَ العالي يا ربِّي يسوعُ المسيحُ، والرّوحُ القُدُسُ. مَجْداً للهِ الآبِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ϯⲛⲁⲥ̀ⲙⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ ⲙ̀ⲙⲏⲛⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲏⲛⲓ: ϯⲛⲁⲥ̀ⲙⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ ⲛⲉⲙ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ  ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Every day I will bless You and praise Your holy name forever and unto the age of ages. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أُبارِكُكَ كُلَّ يَومٍ، وأسبِّحُ اسْمَكَ القُدُّوسَ، إلى الأبَدِ وإلى أبَدِ الأبَدِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
            Ⲓⲥϫⲉⲛ ϫⲱⲣϩ ⲁ̀ⲡⲁⲡ̅ⲛ̅ⲁ̅ ϣⲱⲣⲡ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟϥ ⲉ̀ⲓ̀ ϩⲁⲣⲟⲕ Ⲡⲁⲛⲟⲩϯ: ϫⲉ ϩⲁⲛⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ ⲛⲉ ⲛⲉⲕⲟⲩⲁϩⲥⲁϩⲛⲓ ϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲕⲁϩⲓ. Ⲛⲁⲓⲉⲣⲙⲉⲗⲉⲧⲁⲛ ϩⲓ ⲛⲉⲕⲙⲱⲓⲧ ϫⲉ ⲁⲕϣⲱⲡⲓ ⲛⲏⲓ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲃⲟⲏ̀ⲑⲟⲥ: ϩⲁⲛⲁ̀ⲧⲟⲟⲩⲓ̀ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲥⲱⲧⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲧ̀ⲥ̀ⲙⲏ: ϣⲱⲣⲡ ⲉⲓⲉ̀ⲧⲁϩⲟⲓ ⲛⲁϩⲣⲁⲕ ⲉⲕⲉ̀ⲛⲁⲩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲓ.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            From the night season, my soul awakes early unto You, O my God, for Your precepts are a light upon the earth. I was meditating on Your ways, for You have become a helper unto me. In the morning You shall hear my voice. Early I will stand before You, and You shall see me.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            مُنْذُ اللَّيلِ روحي تُبَكِّرُ إليكَ يا إلَهي، لأنَّ أوامِرَكَ هِيَ نورٌ عَلى الأرْضِ. كنْتُ أتْلو في طُرقِكَ، لأنَّكَ صِرْتَ لِي مُعيناً. باكراً ياربُّ تَسْمعُ صوْتي، بالغَداةِ أقِفُ أمامَكَ وتَراني.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Trisagion</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">الثلاث تقديسات</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ...</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲓⲥⲭⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲁ̀ⲑⲁⲛⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲟ̀ ⲉⲕ ⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲩ ⲅⲉⲛⲛⲉⲑⲏⲥ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, who was born of the Virgin, have mercy upon us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         قُدّوسٌ اللَّهُ، قُدّوسٌ القَويُّ، قُدّوسٌ الحَيُّ الَّذي لا يَموتُ، الَّذي وُلِدَ مِنَ العَذْراءِ ارحَمْنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲓⲥⲭⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲁ̀ⲑⲁⲛⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲟ̀ ⲥ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲣⲱⲑⲓⲥ ⲇⲓ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ: ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, who was crucified for us, have mercy upon us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         قُدّوسٌ اللَّهُ، قُدّوسٌ القَويُّ، قُدّوسٌ الحَيُّ الَّذي لا يَموتُ، الَّذي صُلِبَ عنّا ارحَمْنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲟ̀ Ⲑⲉⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲓⲥⲭⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ ⲁ̀ⲑⲁⲛⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲟ̀ ⲁ̀ⲛⲁⲥⲧⲁⲥ ⲉⲕ ⲧⲱⲛ ⲛⲉⲕⲣⲱⲛ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲛⲉⲗⲑⲱⲛ ⲓⲥ ⲧⲟⲩⲥ ⲟⲩⲣⲁⲛⲟⲥ: ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, who rose from the dead and ascended into the heavens, have mercy upon us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         قُدّوسٌ اللَّهُ، قُدّوسٌ القَويُّ، قُدّوسٌ الحَيُّ الَّذي لا يَموتُ، الَّذي قامَ مِنَ الأمْواتِ، وصَعِدَ إلى السَّماواتِ ارحَمْنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲇⲟⲝⲁ Ⲡⲁⲧⲣⲓ ⲕⲉ Ⲩⲓⲱ: ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲱ Ⲡⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁⲧⲓ: ⲕⲉ ⲛⲩⲛ ⲕⲉ ⲁ̀ⲓ̀ ⲕⲉ ⲓⲥⲧⲟⲩⲥ: ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲁⲥ ⲧⲱⲛ ⲉ̀ⲱ̀ⲛⲱⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Spirit. Now and ever and unto the ages of the ages. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجْدُ للآبِ والابن والرّوحِ القُدُسِ، الآنَ وكلَّ أَوانٍ وإلى دَهْرِ الدّهورِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>   
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲅⲓⲁ ⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ: ⲡⲁⲛⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲁ ⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ ⲏ̀ⲙⲁⲥ: ϯⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا، أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا، أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲙⲓⲁ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲡⲁⲣⲁⲡⲧⲱⲙⲁ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Lord, forgive us our sins. O Lord, forgive us our iniquities. O Lord, forgive us our trespasses.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا خَطايانا، ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا آثامَنا، ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا زَلاّتِنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ϫⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲓⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉⲧϣⲱⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲗⲁⲟⲥ: ⲙⲁⲧⲁⲗϭⲱⲟⲩ ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅: ⲛⲉⲛⲓⲟϯ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲉⲛⲥ̀ⲛⲏⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲉⲛⲕⲟⲧ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲙⲁⲙ̀ⲧⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲛⲟⲩⲯⲩⲭⲏ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Lord, visit the sick of Your people, heal them for the sake of Your holy name. Our fathers and brethren who have fallen asleep, O Lord, repose their souls.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ياربُّ افْتَقدْ مَرْضَى شَعْبِكَ. اشْفِهمْ مِنْ أجْلِ اسْمِكَ القُدُّوسِ. آباؤُنا وإخْوَتُنا الَّذينَ رَقدوا ياربُّ نَيِّحْ نُفوسَهُم.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲓⲁⲑⲛⲟⲃⲓ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲡⲓⲁⲑⲛⲟⲃⲓ Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲁ̀ⲣⲓⲃⲟⲏ̀ⲑⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲛ ϣⲉⲡ ⲡⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟⲕ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O You who are without sin, Lord, have mercy on us. O You who are without sin, Lord, help us and receive our supplications.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         يا مَنْ هُوَ بِلا خَطيئَةٍ ياربُّ ارحَمْنا. يا الَّذي بِلا خَطيئَةٍ ياربُّ أَعِنّا واقْبَلْ طَلباتِنا إليكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ ⲫⲱⲕ ⲡⲉ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲁ̀ⲙⲁϩⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲟⲥ: Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲩⲗⲟⲅⲏⲥⲟⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.            
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         For Yours is the glory, the dominion, and triple holiness. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord bless us. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         لأنَّ لَكَ المجْدَ والعِزَّةَ والتَّقْديسَ المثلَّثَ، ياربُّ ارحَمْ، ياربُّ ارْحَمْ، ياربُّ بارِكْ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>   
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Our Father</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">أبانا الذي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲧⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲁ ⲛ̀ϫⲟⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Make us worthy to pray thankfully:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اللهُمَّ اجعلْنا مُستحقينَ أن نقولَ بشكرٍ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ Ⲡⲉⲛⲓⲱⲧ ⲉⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be Thy name.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أبانا الذي في السماواتِ ليتقدسِ اسمُكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲥⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ: ⲡⲉⲧⲉϩⲛⲁⲕ ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥϣⲱⲡⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲕⲁϩⲓ:  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Thy kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليأتِ ملكوتُكَ، لتكُن مشيئتُكَ، كما في السماءِ كذلكَ على الأرضِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲓⲕ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲣⲁⲥϯ ⲙⲏⲓϥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲫⲟⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲣⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Give us this day our daily bread and forgive us our trespasses, as we forgive those who trespass against us and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         خبزَنا الذي للغدِّ أعطِنا اليومَ، واغفِرْ لنا ذنوبَنا كما نغفِرُ نحنُ أيضاً للمُذنبينَ إلينا، ولا تُدخِلنا في تجرِبةٍ لكِنْ نجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ: ϫⲉ ⲑⲱⲕ ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In Christ Jesus our Lord. For Thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, forever. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِّنا. لأنَّ لكَ المُلكَ والقوةَ والمجدَ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Hail to You</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">السّلامُ لَكِ...</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
      
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲛⲉ ⲧⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲉ̀ⲣⲟ: ⲱ̀ ⲑⲏⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅ ⲉⲑⲙⲉϩ ⲛ̀ⲱ̀ⲟⲩ: ⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲓ ⲙ̀ⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲛ̀ⲥⲏⲟⲩ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ: ϯⲙⲁⲥⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲑ̀ⲙⲁⲩ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Hail to you. We ask you, O saint, full of glory, the ever-virgin, the Theotokos, the Mother of Christ,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         السَّلامُ لَكِ، نَسْألُكِ أيَّتُها القِدّيسَةُ الممْتَلِئةُ مَجْداً، العَذْراءُ كلَّ حينٍ، والِدةُ الإلَهِ، أمُّ المسيحِ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲛⲓⲟⲩⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲉⲩⲭⲏ: ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ϣⲱⲓ ϩⲁ ⲡⲉϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲉⲛⲣⲓⲧ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Lift up our prayers unto your beloved Son, that He may forgive us our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اصْعدي صَلَواتِنا إلى ابْنِكِ الحَبيبِ، ليغْفِرَ لَنا خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲑⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁⲥⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲟⲩϯ: ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Hail to the holy Virgin, who has brought forth unto us the true Light, Christ our God.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         السَّلامُ لِلَّتي وَلَدَتْ لَنا النّورَ الحَقيقيَّ المسيحَ إلَهَنا. العَذْراءُ القدّيسَةُ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁϯϩⲟ ⲙ̀Ⲡⲟ̅ⲥ̅ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲉⲣⲟⲩⲛⲁⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲉⲛⲯⲩⲭⲏ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Ask the Lord on our behalf, that He may have mercy on our souls, and forgive us our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اسْألي الرَّبَّ عنّا ليَصْنَعَ رَحْمَةً مَعَ نُفوسِنا، ويغفِرَ لَنا خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ Ⲙⲁⲣⲓⲁⲙ: ϯⲑⲉⲟ̀ⲧⲟⲕⲟⲥ ⲉ̅ⲑ̅ⲩ̅: ϯⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲧⲁⲧⲏⲥ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲛϩⲟⲧ: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡ̀ⲅⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲣⲱⲙⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         O Virgin Mary, the holy Theotokos, the faithful advocate for all mankind,
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أيَّتُها العَذْراءُ مَرْيَمُ والِدةُ الإلهِ، القِدّيسَةُ الشَّفيعَةُ الأمينَةُ لجنْسِ البَشرِيّةِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>

   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲡ̀ⲣⲉⲥⲃⲉⲩⲓⲛ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ: ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅ ⲫⲏⲉⲧⲁⲣⲉϫ̀ⲫⲟϥ: ϩⲟⲡⲱⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲉⲣϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ ⲛⲁⲛ: ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Intercede on our behalf before Christ whom you bore, that He may grant us the forgiveness of our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اشْفَعي فينا أَمامَ المَسيحِ الَّذي وَلدْتِهِ، لِكَيْ يُنْعِمَ لنا بغُفْرانِ خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲛⲉ ⲱ̀ ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ: ϯⲟⲩⲣⲱ ⲙ̀ⲙⲏⲓ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲗⲏⲑⲓⲛⲏ: ⲭⲉⲣⲉ ⲡ̀ϣⲟⲩϣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲅⲉⲛⲟⲥ: ⲁ̀ⲣⲉϫ̀ⲫⲟ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲛ̀Ⲉⲙⲙⲁⲛⲟⲩⲏⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Hail to you, O Virgin, / the right and true Queen. / Hail to the pride of our race / who bore to us Immanuel.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         السَّلامُ لكِ أيَّتُها العَذْراءُ الملكةُ الحقيقيَّةُ الحقانِيَّةُ السَّلامُ لفَخرِ جِنسِنا ولدْتِ لنا عِمَّانوئيلَ.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϯϩⲟ ⲁ̀ⲣⲓⲡⲉⲛⲙⲉⲩⲓ̀: ⲱ̀ ϯⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲥⲧⲁⲧⲏⲥ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲛϩⲟⲧ: ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲉⲛⲟ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲓⲏ̅ⲥ̅ Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅: ⲛ̀ⲧⲉϥⲭⲁ ⲛⲉⲛⲛⲟⲃⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We ask you to remember us, / O our faithful advocate, / before our Lord Jesus Christ / that He may forgive us our sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نسألُكِ أن تَذكُرينا أيَّتُها الشفيعةُ المؤتمنةُ أمامَ ربِّنا يسوعَ المسيحِ ليغفِرَ لنا خَطايانا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">     
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Introduction to the Creed</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">بدء قانون الإيمان</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>      
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϭⲓⲥⲓ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟ ⲑ̀ⲙⲁⲩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: ⲧⲉⲛϯⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲉ ⲱ̀ ⲑⲏⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁⲥⲛⲟⲩϯ: ϫⲉ ⲁ̀ⲣⲉⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲡ̀ⲥⲱⲧⲏⲣ ⲙ̀ⲡⲓⲕⲟⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲧⲏⲣϥ: ⲁϥⲓ̀ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁϥⲥⲱϯ ⲛ̀ⲛⲉⲛⲯⲩⲭⲏ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We exalt you, the Mother of the true Light. We glorify you, O saint, the Theotokos, for you have brought forth unto us the Savior of the whole world; He came and saved our souls. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نُعظِّمُكِ يا أمَّ النُّورِ الحَقيقيِّ. ونُمجِّدُكِ أيَّتُها العَذْراءُ القِدّيسةُ والِدةُ الإلهِ. لأنَّكِ وَلدْتِ لَنا مُخلِّصَ العالَمِ. أتَى وخَلَّصَ نُفُوسَنا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>      
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲟⲩⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲁⲕ ⲡⲉⲛⲛⲏⲃ ⲡⲉⲛⲟⲩⲣⲟ Ⲡⲭ̅ⲥ̅: ⲡ̀ϣⲟⲩϣⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲁ̀ⲡⲟⲥⲧⲟⲗⲟⲥ: ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲗⲟⲙ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲙⲁⲣⲧⲩⲣⲟⲥ: ⲡ̀ⲑⲉⲗⲏⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲇⲓⲕⲉⲟⲥ: ⲡ̀ⲧⲁϫⲣⲟ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲉ̀ⲕⲕ̀ⲗⲏⲥⲓⲁ: ⲡ̀ⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲛⲟⲃⲓ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Glory be to You, our Master, our King, Christ, the pride of the apostles, the crown of the martyrs, the joy of the righteous, the firmness of the churches, the forgiveness of sins.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         المجْدُ لكَ يا سَيِّدَنا ومَلِكَنا المسيحَ: فَخْرَ الرُّسُلِ، إكْليلَ الشُهداءِ، تَهْليلَ الصِدّيقينَ، ثَباتَ الكَنائسِ، غُفْرانَ الخَطايا.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>      
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲧⲉⲛϩⲓⲱⲓϣ ⲛ̀ϯⲧ̀ⲣⲓⲁⲥ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ: ⲉⲥϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲙⲉⲑⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ: ⲧⲉⲛⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟⲥ: ⲧⲉⲛϯⲱⲟⲩ ⲛⲁⲥ. Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ: Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ: Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉⲩⲗⲟⲅⲏⲥⲟⲛ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We proclaim the Holy Trinity in one Godhead. We worship Him. We glorify Him. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord bless us. Amen.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نُبشِّرُ بالثَّالوثِ القُدُّوسِ: لاهوتٌ واحِدٌ. نَسجُدُ لهُ ونُمجِّدُهُ. ياربُّ ارحَمْ، ياربُّ ارحَمْ، ياربُّ بارِكْ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">      
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">The Orthodox Creed</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">قانون الإيمان المقدس الأرثوذكسي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
         
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛⲛⲁϩϯ ⲉ̀ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ: Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲡⲓⲡⲁⲛⲧⲟⲕⲣⲁⲧⲱⲣ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁϥⲑⲁⲙⲓⲟ ⲛ̀ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡ̀ⲕⲁϩⲓ: ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲟⲩⲛⲁⲩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛ̀ⲥⲉⲛⲁⲩ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ ⲁⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We believe in one God, God the Father, the Pantocrator, Creator of heaven and earth, and of all things seen and unseen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نؤمنُ بإلهٍ واحدٍ اللهِ الآبِ ضابطِ الكلِ خالقِ السماءِ والأرضِ. ما يُرَى وما لا يُرَى
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛⲛⲁϩϯ ⲉ̀ⲟⲩϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲡϣⲏⲣⲓ ⲙ̀Ⲫⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲡⲓⲙⲟⲛⲟⲅⲉⲛⲏⲥ: ⲡⲓⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ϧⲁϫⲱⲟⲩ ⲛ̀ⲛⲓⲉ̀ⲱⲛ ⲧⲏⲣⲟⲩ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We believe in one Lord, Jesus Christ, the only-begotten Son of God, begotten of the Father before all ages.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نؤمنُ بربٍ واحدٍ يسوعَ، المسيحِ، ابنِ اللهِ الوحيدِ المولودِ مِنَ الآبِ قبلَ كلِّ الدهورِ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         ⲟⲩⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲟⲩⲱⲓⲛⲓ: ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩⲛⲟⲩϯ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲫ̀ⲙⲏⲓ: ⲟⲩⲙⲓⲥⲓ ⲡⲉ ⲟⲩⲑⲁⲙⲓⲟ ⲁⲛ ⲡⲉ ⲟⲩⲟ̀ⲙⲟⲟⲩⲥⲓⲟⲥ ⲡⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁ ϩⲱⲃ ⲛⲓⲃⲉⲛ ϣⲱⲡⲓ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲓⲧⲟⲧϥ. 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Light of Light, true God of true God; begotten, not created; of one essence with the Father; by whom all things were made.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نورٍ مِنْ نورٍ إلهِ حقٍ مِنْ إلهِ حقٍ، مولودٍ غيرِ مخلوقٍ، مساوٍ للآبِ في الجوهرِ الذي بِهِ كانَ كلُّ شيءٍ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲫⲁⲓ ⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲉⲑⲃⲏⲧⲉⲛ ⲁ̀ⲛⲟⲛ ϧⲁ ⲛⲓⲣⲱⲙⲓ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉⲑⲃⲉ ⲡⲉⲛⲟⲩϫⲁⲓ: ⲁϥⲓ̀ ⲉ̀ⲡⲉⲥⲏⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ: ⲁϥϭⲓⲥⲁⲣⲝ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲙⲁⲣⲓⲁ ϯⲡⲁⲣⲑⲉⲛⲟⲥ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁϥⲉⲣⲣⲱⲙⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Who for us men and for our salvation came down from heaven, was incarnate of the Holy Spirit and of the Virgin Mary, and became man.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         هذا الذي مِنْ أجلِنا نحنُ البشرَ ومِنْ أجلِ خلاصِنا نزِلَ مِنَ السماءِ وتجسدَ مِنَ الرّوحِ القُدُسِ ومِنْ مريمَ العذراءِ وتأنسَ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>
      <ns0:Season id="CovenantThursday | JoyousSaturday">
         <ns0:Group>            
            <ns0:Season id="JoyousSaturday">
               <ns0:Text>
                  <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
                     Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲣⲱⲛⲓⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟϥ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲟⲛⲧⲓⲟⲥ Ⲡⲓⲗⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲁϥϣⲉⲡⲉⲙⲕⲁϩ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲕⲟⲥϥ. 
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="English">
                     And He was crucified for us under Pontius Pilate, suffered and was buried;  
                  </ns0:Language>
                  <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
                     وصُلِبَ عنَّا على عهدِ بيلاطسَ البُنطيِّ، تألّمَ وقُبِرَ
                  </ns0:Language>         
               </ns0:Text>
            </ns0:Season>
         </ns0:Group>
         
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Skip to “Yes, we believe in the Holy Spirit...” 
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="Other">
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲉⲣⲥ̀ⲧⲁⲩⲣⲱⲛⲓⲛ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟϥ ⲉ̀ϩ̀ⲣⲏⲓ ⲉ̀ϫⲱⲛ ⲛⲁϩⲣⲉⲛ Ⲡⲟⲛⲧⲓⲟⲥ Ⲡⲓⲗⲁⲧⲟⲥ: ⲁϥϣⲉⲡⲉⲙⲕⲁϩ ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁⲩⲕⲟⲥϥ. Ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲁϥⲧⲱⲛϥ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲏⲉⲑⲙⲱⲟⲩⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲉ̀ϩⲟⲟⲩ ⲙ̀ⲙⲁϩϣⲟⲙⲧ ⲕⲁⲧⲁ ⲛⲓⲅ̀ⲣⲁⲫⲏ. 
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               And He was crucified for us under Pontius Pilate, suffered and was buried, and on the third day He rose from the dead according to the Scriptures. 
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وصُلِبَ عنَّا على عهدِ بيلاطسَ البُنطيِّ، تألّمَ وقُبِرَ وقامَ مِنْ بينِ الأمواتِ في اليومِ الثالثِ كما في الكتبِ
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
         
         <ns0:Text>
            <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
               Ⲁϥϣⲉⲛⲁϥ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ϣⲱⲓ ⲉ̀ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲁϥϩⲉⲙⲥⲓ ⲥⲁⲟⲩⲓⲛⲁⲙ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉϥⲓⲱⲧ. Ⲕⲉ ⲡⲁⲗⲓⲛ ϥ̀ⲛⲏⲟⲩ ϧⲉⲛ ⲡⲉϥⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ϯϩⲁⲡ ⲉ̀ⲛⲏⲉⲧⲟⲛϧ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲛⲏⲉⲑⲙⲱⲟⲩⲧ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲧⲉϥⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲟⲩⲁⲑⲙⲟⲩⲛⲕ ⲧⲉ.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="English">
               Ascended into the heavens; He sits at the right hand of His Father, and He is coming again in His glory to judge the living and the dead, whose kingdom shall have no end.
            </ns0:Language>
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               وصَعِدَ إلى السماواتِ وجلسَ عن يمينِ أبيهِ وأيضاً يأتي في مجدِهِ ليُدينَ الأحياءَ والأمواتَ الذي ليسَ لمُلكِهِ انقضاءٌ
            </ns0:Language>         
         </ns0:Text>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲥⲉ ⲧⲉⲛⲛⲁϩϯ ⲉ̀Ⲡⲓⲡ̀ⲛⲉⲩⲙⲁ ⲉⲑⲟⲩⲁⲃ Ⲡϭⲟⲓⲥ ⲛ̀ⲣⲉϥϯ ⲙ̀ⲡ̀ⲱⲛϧ: ⲫⲏⲉⲑⲛⲏⲟⲩ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗϧⲉⲛ Ⲫ̀ⲓⲱⲧ: ⲥⲉⲟⲩⲱϣⲧ ⲙ̀ⲙⲟϥ ⲥⲉϯ ⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ⲛⲁϥ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲫⲓⲱⲧ ⲛⲉⲙ Ⲡϣⲏⲣⲓ: ⲫⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲁϥⲥⲁϫⲓ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲡ̀ⲣⲟⲫⲏⲧⲏⲥ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Yes, we believe in the Holy Spirit, the Lord, the Giver of Life, who proceeds from the Father, who with the Father and the Son, is worshiped and glorified, who spoke by the prophets.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         نَعَم نؤمنُ بالرّوحِ القُدُسِ الربِّ المحيي المنبثقِ مِنَ الآبِ، نسجدُ لهُ ونمجدُهُ معَ الآبِ والابنِ الناطقِ في الأنبياءِ
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲉⲟⲩⲓ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲅⲓⲁ ⲛ̀ⲕⲁⲑⲟⲗⲓⲕⲏ ⲛ̀ⲁ̀ⲡⲟⲥⲧⲟⲗⲓⲕⲏ ⲛ̀ⲉⲕⲕ̀ⲗⲏⲥⲓⲁ̀. Ⲧⲉⲛⲉⲣⲟ̀ⲙⲟⲗⲟⲅⲓⲛ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲙⲥ ⲛ̀ⲟⲩⲱⲧ ⲉ̀ⲡ̀ⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲛⲟⲃⲓ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         And in one holy, catholic (universal), and apostolic Church. We confess one baptism, for the remission of sins.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وبكنيسةٍ واحدةٍ مُقدسَةٍ جامعةٍ رسوليةٍ. ونعترفُ بمعموديةٍ واحدةٍ لمغفِرةِ الخطايا
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Group>         
      <ns0:Season id="(FuneralTune ^ FuneralPrayer) | GeneralFuneralPrayer">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               The last verse is chanted in the “Golgotha” tune:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
      
      <ns0:Season id="Other">
         <ns0:Comment>
            <ns0:Language id="English">         
               The people chant the last sentence in a loud voice.
            </ns0:Language>         
            <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
               ثم يقول الشعب جهراً هذه الجملة الأخيرة مِنْ قانون الإيمان، وهي:
            </ns0:Language>
         </ns0:Comment>
      </ns0:Season>
   </ns0:Group>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲧⲉⲛϫⲟⲩϣⲧ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϧⲁⲧ̀ϩⲏ ⲛ̀ϯⲁ̀ⲛⲁⲥⲧⲁⲥⲓⲥ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲛⲓⲣⲉϥⲙⲱⲟⲩⲧ: ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱⲛϧ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲡⲓⲉ̀ⲱⲛ ⲉⲑⲛⲏⲟⲩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         We look for the resurrection of the dead, and the life of the age to come. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         وننتظرُ قيامةَ الأمواتِ، وحياةَ الدهرِ الآتي. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>         
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Role id="Priest">
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord hear us and have mercy on us and forgive us our sins. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ياربُّ اسمَعْنا وارحَمْنا واغفِرْ لنا خطايانا. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Role>
<ns0:Text forceLanguage="Coptic">
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲉ ⲉ̀ⲗⲉⲏ̀ⲥⲟⲛ (ⲙ̅ⲁ̅)
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Lord have mercy (41)          
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ياربُّ ارحَمْ (41)
      </ns0:Language>   
   </ns0:Text>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">Holy, Holy, Holy</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
      
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Holy, holy, holy, Lord of Sabaoth. Heaven and earth are full of Your glory and honor. Have mercy on us, O God the Father, the Pantocrator. O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Lord, God of hosts, be with us. For we have no helper in our hardships and tribulations but You. Absolve, forgive, and remit, O God, our transgressions; those which we have committed willingly and those which we have committed unwillingly, those which we have committed knowingly and those which we have committed unknowingly, the hidden and the manifest, O Lord forgive us, for the sake of Your holy name which is called upon us. Let it be according to Your mercy, O Lord, and not according to our sins.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ، قُدُّوسٌ، ربُّ الصباؤوتِ. السماءُ والأرضُ مملوءتانِ مِنْ مجدِكَ وكرامتِكَ. ارحَمْنا يا اللهُ الآبُ ضابطُ الكلِّ. أيها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا. أيها الربُّ إلهُ القواتِ كُن معنا، لأنَّهُ ليسَ لنا مُعينٌ في شدائدِنا وضيقاتِنا سِواكَ. حلِّ واغفِرْ واصفحْ لنا يا اللهُ عَن سيئاتِنا، التي صنعناها بإرادتِنا والتي صنعناها بغيرِ إرادتِنا، التي فعلناها بمعرفةٍ والتي فعلناها بغيرِ معرفةٍ، الخفيةِ والظاهرةِ. ياربُّ اغفِرْها لنا، مِنْ أجلِ اسمِكَ القُدُّوسِ الذي دُعِيَ علينا. كرحمتِكَ ياربُّ وليسَ كخطايانا.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
      <ns0:Language id="English">Our Father</ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">أبانا الذي</ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Title>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲁⲣⲓⲧⲉⲛ ⲛ̀ⲉⲙⲡ̀ϣⲁ ⲛ̀ϫⲟⲥ ϧⲉⲛ ⲟⲩϣⲉⲡϩ̀ⲙⲟⲧ:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Make us worthy to pray thankfully:
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         اللهُمَّ اجعلْنا مُستحقينَ أن نقولَ بشكرٍ:
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϫⲉ Ⲡⲉⲛⲓⲱⲧ ⲉⲧ ϧⲉⲛ ⲛⲓⲫⲏⲟⲩⲓ: ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥⲧⲟⲩⲃⲟ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲡⲉⲕⲣⲁⲛ: 
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Our Father who art in heaven, hallowed be Thy name.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         أبانا الذي في السماواتِ ليتقدسِ اسمُكَ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲙⲁⲣⲉⲥⲓ̀ ⲛ̀ϫⲉ ⲧⲉⲕⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ: ⲡⲉⲧⲉϩⲛⲁⲕ ⲙⲁⲣⲉϥϣⲱⲡⲓ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϧⲉⲛ ⲧ̀ⲫⲉ ⲛⲉⲙ ϩⲓϫⲉⲛ ⲡⲓⲕⲁϩⲓ:  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Thy kingdom come, Thy will be done, on earth as it is in heaven.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         ليأتِ ملكوتُكَ، لتكُن مشيئتُكَ، كما في السماءِ كذلكَ على الأرضِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ⲡⲉⲛⲱⲓⲕ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉ ⲣⲁⲥϯ ⲙⲏⲓϥ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲙ̀ⲫⲟⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲭⲁ ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉⲣⲟⲛ ⲛⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ: ⲙ̀ⲫ̀ⲣⲏϯ ϩⲱⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲉⲛⲭⲱ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ⲛ̀ⲛⲏⲉ̀ⲧⲉ ⲟⲩⲟⲛ ⲛ̀ⲧⲁⲛ ⲉ̀ⲣⲱⲟⲩ: ⲟⲩⲟϩ ⲙ̀ⲡⲉⲣⲉⲛⲧⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ϧⲟⲩⲛ ⲉ̀ⲡⲓⲣⲁⲥⲙⲟⲥ ⲁⲗⲗⲁ ⲛⲁϩⲙⲉⲛ ⲉ̀ⲃⲟⲗ ϩⲁ ⲡⲓⲡⲉⲧϩⲱⲟⲩ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         Give us this day our daily bread and forgive us our trespasses, as we forgive those who trespass against us and lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from the evil one.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         خبزَنا الذي للغدِّ أعطِنا اليومَ، واغفِرْ لنا ذنوبَنا كما نغفِرُ نحنُ أيضاً للمُذنبينَ إلينا، ولا تُدخِلنا في تجرِبةٍ لكِنْ نجِّنا مِنَ الشريرِ،
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
   
   <ns0:Text>
      <ns0:Language id="Coptic">
         Ϧⲉⲛ Ⲡⲓⲭ̀ⲣⲓⲥⲧⲟⲥ Ⲓⲏⲥⲟⲩⲥ Ⲡⲉⲛϭⲟⲓⲥ: ϫⲉ ⲑⲱⲕ ⲧⲉ ϯⲙⲉⲧⲟⲩⲣⲟ ⲛⲉⲙ ϯϫⲟⲙ ⲛⲉⲙ ⲡⲓⲱ̀ⲟⲩ ϣⲁ ⲉ̀ⲛⲉϩ: ⲁ̀ⲙⲏⲛ.  
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="English">
         In Christ Jesus our Lord. For Thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glory, forever. Amen.
      </ns0:Language>
      <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
         بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِّنا. لأنَّ لكَ المُلكَ والقوةَ والمجدَ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
      </ns0:Language>
   </ns0:Text>
</ns0:Section>
<ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            First Absolution
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            وهذا التحليلُ
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O Lord, God of hosts, who is existing before all ages and abides forever, who created the sun for daylight, and the night as rest for all men; we thank You, O King of ages, for You have let us pass through the night in peace, and brought us to the daybreak. Therefore, we ask You, O our Master, the King of all ages, let Your face shine upon us, and the light of Your divine knowledge enlighten us. Grant us, O our Master, to be sons of light and sons of day, to pass this day in righteousness, chastity and good conduct, that we may complete all the rest of the days of our life without offence; through the grace, the compassion and the love of mankind of Your only-begotten Son Jesus Christ, and the gift of Your Holy Spirit, now and at all times and forever. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أيها الربُّ إلهُ القواتِ، الكائنُ قبلَ الدهورِ والدائمُ إلى الأبدِ، الذي خلقَ الشمسَ لضياءِ النهارِ، والليلَ راحةً لكلِّ البشرِ، نشكرُكَ يا ملِكَ الدهورِ لأنكَ أجزتَنا هذا الليلِ بسلامٍ وأتيتَ بِنا إلى مبدأِ النهارِ. مِنْ أجلِ هذا نسألُكَ يا ملكَنا ملكَ الدهورِ، ليشرقْ لنا نورُ وجهِكَ، وليُضئْ علينا نورُ علمِكَ الإلهي. واجعلْنا يا سيِّدَنا أن نكونَ بني النورِ وبني النهارِ، لكي نجوزَ هذا اليومِ ببرٍ وطهارةٍ وتدبيرٍ حسنٍ، لنكَمِّلَ بقيةِ أيامِ حياتِنا بلا عثرةٍ. بالنعمةِ والرأفةِ ومحبةِ البشرِ اللواتي لإبنِكَ الوحيدِ يسوعَ المسيحِ، وموهبةِ روحِكَ القُدُّوسِ. الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى الأبدِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">      
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Second Absolution
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            تحليل آخر
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            O God who causes the light to burst forth, who lets His sun shine upon the righteous and the wicked, who created the light which illuminates the whole world, enlighten our minds, our hearts and our understandings, O Master of all, and grant us to please You this present day. Guard us from every bad thing, from every sin, and from every adversative power; through Christ Jesus our Lord, with whom You are blessed, with the Holy Spirit, the Life-Giver and one essence with You, now and at all times and unto the ages of all ages. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            أيها الباعِثُ النورَ فينطلِقُ، المُشرِقُ شمسَهُ على الأبرارِ والأشرارِ، الذي صنعَ النورَ الذي يضيءُ على المسكونةِ، أنِرْ عقولَنا وقلوبَنا وأفهامَنا يا سيِّدَ الكلِّ. هبْ لنا في هذا اليومِ الحاضرِ أن نُرضيَكَ فيهِ. واحرُسْنا مِنْ كلِّ شيءٍ رديءٍ ومِنْ كلِّ خَطيئَةٍ، ومِنْ كلِّ قوةٍ مُضادةٍ بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِّنا. هذا الذي أنتَ مُبارَكٌ معَهُ معَ الرّوحِ القُدُسِ المُحيي المُساوي لكَ، الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
   
   <ns0:Section expanded="true">
      <ns0:Title>
         <ns0:Language id="English">Conclusion of Every Hour</ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">طلبةٌ تقالُ آخرَ كلِّ ساعةٍٍ</ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Title>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Have mercy on us, O God, and have mercy on us, who at all times and in every hour, in heaven and on earth, is worshipped and glorified; Christ our God, the good, the long suffering, the abundant in mercy, and the great in compassion, who loves the righteous and has mercy on the sinners of whom I am chief, who does not wish the death of the sinner but rather that he returns and lives, who calls all to salvation for the promise of the good things to come.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ارحَمْنا يا اللهُ ثمَّ ارحَمْنا، يا مَنْ في كلِّ وقتٍ وكلِّ ساعةٍ، في السماءِ وعلى الأرضِ، مسجودٌ لهُ ومُمجَّدٌ. المسيحُ إلهُنا الصالحُ، الطويلُ الرّوحِ، الكثيرُ الرحمةِ، الجزيلُ التحننِ، الذي يحبُّ الصديقينَ ويرحمُ الخطاةَ الذينَ أوَّلُهُم أنا. الذي لا يشاءُ موتَ الخاطئِ مثلَ ما يرجعُ ويحيا. الدَّاعي الكلَّ إلى الخلاصِ لأجلِ الموعدِ بالخيراتِ المُنتظَرةِ.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
            
      <ns0:Text>
         <ns0:Language id="English">
            Lord receive from us our prayers in this hour and in every hour. Ease our life and guide us to fulfill Your commandments. Sanctify our spirits. Cleanse our bodies. Conduct our thoughts. Purify our intentions. Heal our diseases. Forgive our sins. Deliver us from every evil grief and distress of heart. Surround us by Your holy angels, that, by their camp, we may be guarded and guided, and attain the unity of faith, and the knowledge of Your imperceptible and infinite glory. For You are blessed forever. Amen.
         </ns0:Language>
         <ns0:Language id="Arabic">
            ياربُّ اقبَلْ مِنَّا في هذهِ الساعةِ وكلِّ ساعةٍ طلباتِنا. سهِّلْ حياتَنا، وارشِدْنا إلى العملِ بوصاياكَ. قدِّسْ أرواحَنا. طهِّرْ أجسامَنا. قوِّمْ أفكارَنا. نَقِّ نياتِنا. اشفِ أمراضَنا واغفِرْ خطايانا. ونجِّنا مِنْ كلِّ حزنٍ رديءٍ ووجعِ قلبٍ. أحِطنا بملائكتِكَ القديسينَ، لكي نكونَ بمعسكرِهِم محفوظينَ ومُرشَدينَ، لنصِلَ إلى اتِّحادِ الإيمانِ وإلى معرفةِ مجدِكَ غيرِ المحسوسِ وغيرِ المحدودِ، فإنَّكَ مُبارَكٌ إلى الأبدِ. آمين.
         </ns0:Language>
      </ns0:Text>
   </ns0:Section>
</ns0:Document>